<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Canadian Immigrant</title>
	<atom:link href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca</link>
	<description>Arrive. Succeed. Inspire.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 21:05:32 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>A mother&#8217;s perspectives on a half-empty nest</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/your-stories/a-mothers-perspectives-on-a-half-empty-nest</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Gu Zhenzhen]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 16 Jan 2023 21:05:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Family & Relationships]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Living]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Your Stories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[asian-born immigrants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[parenting]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60400</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Chinese-born Canadian Gu Zhenzhen shares her feelings of emptiness as her children move away from home. But then, she reminds herself that she is walking in her parents' shoes. Zhenzhen moved to Canada in 1990 to begin a new life. </p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/your-stories/a-mothers-perspectives-on-a-half-empty-nest">A mother’s perspectives on a half-empty nest</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div dir="ltr">
<h4 dir="ltr">Chinese-born Canadian Gu Zhenzhen shares her feelings of emptiness as her children move away from home. But then, she reminds herself that she is walking in her parents&#8217; shoes. Zhenzhen moved to Canada in 1990 to begin a new life.</h4>
</div>
<div id="x_ydpe6dbfcdyiv7582423087ydpd9b5edfbyiv1375463285ydpae423976yiv1906208496ydpd465311byiv8648913603ydp638f5424yiv9697182827m_-5034845012801910013ydp6ab37823yiv8449688537ydpaeebd010yiv0466887251ydp8a06c653yiv6559086291ydpd53f6e39yiv2160214211ydp1a961af9yiv3216201363m_3561793322743485967ydpbdd72f89yiv8608860537ydp7172069ayiv9013262128yqtfd70179">
<div dir="ltr">
<p>Two of my four children have moved out and are leading independent lives. So, our nest is half empty.</p>
<p>Of course, I am proud of my children’s independence, but at the same time, I feel a little empty inside. I miss those happy times when we all lived under the same roof. But I cherish our memories and always look forward to their visits back home for special holidays — like the upcoming Chinese New Year on January 22, 2023!</p>
<p>One of my most enjoyable times was spending time with my first-born, an aviation enthusiast, at Toronto Pearson International Airport, watch airplanes from around the world land and take off.  After he graduated from high school, we traveled to Vancouver to celebrate. Riding a bicycle there with my teenage son and his friends along the Pacific coast in famous Stanley Park is also one of my most cherished memories.  I made this unforgettable trip at the urging of a wise friend, “Go with him when he still needs you,” she said.</p>
<p>Just before COVID-19, we visited Melbourne, Australia. At sunset, watching and listening to ocean waves, collecting seashells and finding myself surrounded by seagulls on a sandy beach is one of my fondest memories, too.</p>
<p>I also miss my favourite moments when my third son played Chopin’s <em>Nocturnes</em> or his own pieces for me at home. Now he has left home and taken the music with him. I recently visited him in downtown Toronto. “Can you play Chopin’s <em>Nocturnes</em>?” I asked.</p>
<p>When I complain about my two sons’ absence, my daughter, the youngest of my four children, reminds me that I did the same. A good reminder, indeed!</p>
<p>In 1979, after I graduated from high school, I secretly applied for universities outside my hometown, Beijing. The day I received my acceptance letter from a college in Nanjing, my father wasn’t in a celebratory mood. To him, Nanjing was too far from Beijing. I had to take refuge at my aunt’s house for a few days to wait out the storm. My father eventually came around after he realized that I was among the four per cent of high school graduates who could get into university that year.  I had a dozen family and friends see me off at the Beijing Train Station. From there, this rebellious teenage girl, began a 1,700 km journey to Nanjing to start an independent life at the age of 18.</p>
<p>Eleven years later, I traveled even farther. In 1990, I left China for Canada. Once again, more than a dozen relatives were there to bid goodbye at the Beijing International Airport. After a nearly 10,000 km journey, I was thrilled to arrive in Canada. I still remember that after my very first rock concert at Toronto’s Ontario Place, I ran in a downpour, soaking wet, but as joyous as Gene Kelly’s character in “Singin’ in the Rain”. What I felt at that moment was the enormous pleasure of being free!</p>
<p>So, why don’t I wish my children to enjoy their own independence and freedom? I am not that adventurous teenage girl anymore. I have become a mother of four grown children. I walk in my parents’ shoes.</p>
<p>I look forward to holidays, such as Mid-Autumn Festival, Thanksgiving, Christmas and New Year. On these joyful occasions, our family can reunite and celebrate together with mooncakes, dumplings, a roasted turkey, mashed potatoes and more.</p>
<p>The Chinese New Year, <em>The Year of the Rabbit</em>, arrives on January 22nd, 2023. I can’t wait to welcome my children back, just as my mother welcomed my younger self to return home to Beijing, many years ago.</p>
<p>“Come home more often,” she used to say to me. I have the same wish but have realized that I have to let my kids go; and there is a life after children.</p>
</div>
</div>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/your-stories/a-mothers-perspectives-on-a-half-empty-nest">A mother’s perspectives on a half-empty nest</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Author Nancy Lam reconnects with her roots</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/author-nancy-lam-reconnects-with-her-roots</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ramya Ramanathan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 18:29:57 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Artists]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[People]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Asian-Canadian Culture]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Childhood memories]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Nancy Lam]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60369</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Barrister and solicitor Nancy Lam decided to write her first novel, "The Loyal Daughter", when she lost her mother. The story follows a young woman in a village in China making her way to the crowded streets of Hong Kong, who manages to immigrate to Northern Ontario, and eventually makes Toronto home.  </p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/author-nancy-lam-reconnects-with-her-roots">Author Nancy Lam reconnects with her roots</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Barrister and solicitor Nancy Lam decided to write her first novel, <em>The Loyal Daughter</em>, when she lost her mother. &#8220;I was afraid she and everything she had accomplished would be forgotten — that upset me,&#8221; says Lam. &#8220;I wanted the next generation (at least) to know about her.&#8221;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignleft size-medium wp-image-60370" src="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/TLD_Cover-188x300.jpg" alt="" width="188" height="300" srcset="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/TLD_Cover-188x300.jpg 188w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/TLD_Cover-640x1024.jpg 640w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/TLD_Cover-768x1229.jpg 768w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/TLD_Cover-300x480.jpg 300w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/TLD_Cover-960x1536.jpg 960w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/TLD_Cover-1280x2048.jpg 1280w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/TLD_Cover.jpg 1500w" sizes="(max-width: 188px) 100vw, 188px" />Released in 2022, Lam&#8217;s first novel is fictionalized memoir inspired by her mother&#8217;s life, and her immigration journey to Canada from China. It&#8217;s told from three perspectives – mother, daughter and granddaughter.</p>
<p>The story follows a young woman in a village in China making her way to the crowded streets of Hong Kong, who manages to immigrate to Northern Ontario, and eventually makes Toronto home.</p>
<p>But life is not easy. Stuck in a small apartment above a clothing store, with four kids, her mother, two siblings, and a husband who is never home, her dreams and hopes of building a new life are shattered. Filled with heart-breaking sacrifices, struggles and secrets that shape her identity, <em>The Loyal Daughter</em> speaks to a woman&#8217;s true resilience.</p>
<p>Writing the book was &#8220;cathartic&#8221;, says Lam. &#8220;Writing about and remembering her stories, kept her close to me. I could hear her voice, her critiques, as I wrote and edited. It was my way of honouring her.&#8221; The process reminded Lam of her closeness to her mother and brought back her childhood memories of food, places and experiences. It has also helped reconnect with her roots and embrace her culture.</p>
<p>Lam urges Canadians to take every opportunity to record their stories. &#8220;Your roots, history and family stories are priceless – they make you unique. All immigrant stories are a part of our collective Canadian history. Recording and sharing these stories, makes our country stronger,&#8221; she says.</p>
<p>Lam believes that every immigrant plays an important role in this country.</p>
<p>&#8220;While my mother may not have been a celebrity she was an important immigrant [in her own way] and that’s part of my message – all immigrants, all Canadians, are important even if they never become famous, rich or powerful,&#8221; she says.</p>
<p>The book is now <a href="https://atbaypress.com/books/detail/the-loyal-daughter" target="_blank" rel="noopener">available for purchase</a>.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/author-nancy-lam-reconnects-with-her-roots">Author Nancy Lam reconnects with her roots</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Program to welcome international youth to Canada</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/canadian-program-to-welcome-international-youth-to-canada</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canadian Immigrant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 18:21:32 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[How to Immigrate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Immigrate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IEC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[international experience canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[youth]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60384</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The International Experience Canada (IEC) program is now open to welcome international youth to Canada.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/canadian-program-to-welcome-international-youth-to-canada">Program to welcome international youth to Canada</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p id="wb-cont">The International Experience Canada (IEC) program is now open to welcome international youth to Canada.</p>
<p>Through the IEC program, Canada has youth mobility arrangements <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/services/work-canada/iec1.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">with 36 countries and foreign territories</a> that allow youth from partner countries to work and travel in the country for up to 2 years. Youth who are between 18 to 35 (18 to 30 in some countries) can come work and travel in Canada through this program.</p>
<p>If your country does not feature in the list, you could explore the option of coming to Canada through the IEC program if you use an eligible Recognized Organization. <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/services/work-canada/iec/recognized-organizations.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Click here</a> for the list of organizations. Programs such as these can help you get to know Canada, especially for those who could be considering future immigration opportunities.</p>
<p>Applicants who are already in the IEC pool will begin receiving invitations to apply for their work permit.</p>
<p>This year, Canada will be extending this opportunity to nearly 90,000 international youth. This expansion will also help Canadian employers find the workers they need to fill labour shortages across the country.</p>
<p>Immigration minister Sean Fraser calls this a &#8220;win-win&#8221;. “Our government supports international youth to work and travel in Canada, effectively helping employers find the workers they need. By giving youth the opportunity to gain international travel and work experience, we are strengthening our economy and creating a win-win solution for everyone involved,” he says.</p>
<p><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/services/work-canada/iec1.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Click here for more information about the program</a>.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/canadian-program-to-welcome-international-youth-to-canada">Program to welcome international youth to Canada</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>10 tried and tested money management strategies for students</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/international-students/10-tried-and-tested-money-management-strategies-for-students</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Geneviève Beaupré and Susan Qadeer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 11 Jan 2023 00:27:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Careers & Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[International Students]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Post-Secondary Education]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Study in Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Working]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[budgeting expenses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financial tips]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial tips for international students]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60373</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Managing money as a student can be challenging. There are multiple ways to navigate the costs that come with a post-secondary program. Students can work, cut back on their expenses and/or find creative ways to save money. Here are ten tried and tested strategies.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/international-students/10-tried-and-tested-money-management-strategies-for-students">10 tried and tested money management strategies for students</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Managing money as a student can be challenging. There are multiple ways to navigate the costs that come with a post-secondary program. Students can work, cut back on their expenses and/or find creative ways to save money. Here are ten tried and tested strategies.</p>
<p><strong>1. Explore financial assistance options at school. </strong>One student who could have used more money decided to put in extra time and effort into his academic work to be considered for merit scholarships. He had lots of confidence in his abilities and worked very hard. However, not everyone has those talents and discipline, and scholarships are not a guarantee. While it is an excellent idea to explore financial assistance options such as scholarships, bursaries, grants and loans through your school and other sources, you may have to find other ways to fund your education.</p>
<p><strong>2. Seek out high paying summer jobs. </strong>For decades now, students have found high paying summer work by planting trees. It can be difficult work, especially at the beginning when you are still learning, but it can also get you into good physical shape while earning more than the average salary for summer student jobs. You may also save more since the living conditions are such that you won’t be tempted to spend money.</p>
<p>Some students who find work in high-end restaurants make good money in tips. The summer is also the time when many people take a  vacation, which creates opportunities for temporary workers in administration, hotels, camps and the entertainment industry. Construction work may also increase in the summer months.</p>
<p><strong>3. Find ways to increase your study time. </strong>Other strategies students have used to increase their income during the academic year include working near home or campus to minimize time lost in commuting and finding work that allows for studying while working, such as night desk clerk in a slow-paced environment.</p>
<p><strong>4. Make the most of what you have. </strong>Some students who are partly through a program such as nursing may find career-related work, such as an orderly in a hospital or nursing home or a care worker in a private home. Students with good grades and talents also make use of their abilities as tutors, translators, performers, movers etc. or their cars to offer transportation services. Another common way of making money is to sell what you no longer use or need, but may be of value to others such as books, clothing, jewelry, sports equipment, comics, musical instruments, etc.</p>
<p><strong>5. Keep track of your expenses. </strong>Making money won’t help if you spend more than you earn. Students are encouraged to make a budget so they will know their expenses. Unplanned expenses can include a daily fancy coffee, going out frequently with friends, unplanned meals, impulsive shopping or frequent treats after a difficult or successful day. The best way to know what your money weaknesses are is to keep track of your expenses for a few weeks and if problems are evident, then devise a way around them. This can be done by accumulating receipts or by noting the amount each time you buy something.</p>
<p><strong>6. Allocate funds. </strong>One experienced and well-organized student showed her younger brother how to use monthly envelopes. She had different envelopes with funds allocated for rent, food, transportation and entertainment. When the envelope was empty she knew she was finished with spending for that item for the month. Her brother tried it with limited success at first but after a few months of living on hummus and ramen noodles by month end, he became a smarter meal planner.</p>
<p><strong>7. Set limits on spending. </strong>Another student has found a way to set limits on his expense at his favourite coffee shop. At the beginning of each month, he buys himself an e-gift card based on how much he wants to spend or what he can afford. Once the gift card is out of funds, he does without until the end of the month. Tracking his spending was an eye opener for him in terms of how quickly these small daily purchases can add up.</p>
<p><strong>8. Watch your credit card use. </strong>Always pay off your credit card bill in full and don’t use credit for things you cannot afford. The interest rates are extraordinarily high and can become very difficult to pay off. Credit cards can give you the illusion that you have lots of money, but it is easy to drown in debt if you only make the minimum monthly payment.</p>
<p><strong>9. Find low-cost entertainment.  </strong>Evenings out with friends, especially if they involve food and alcohol, can quickly become expensive. Look for low-cost or free entertainment such as summer outdoor festivals or free nights at your local museum or art gallery. Your school probably has a gym, so why pay for a gym membership? We all need rewards. Know which free or low-cost rewards will sustain you.</p>
<p><strong>10. Compare prices. </strong>Be careful about where you shop for food, clothing, and other items that you need. Prices vary significantly from one store to another and when each item costs more, this can really add up. Some students buy clothing and household items at thrift shops. It is also a great way to reuse items that would otherwise go to landfill.</p>
<p>There is enough to think about when you are a student with assignments and exams; manage your finances and you will lessen one worry. If you do get into financial difficulties, there are free credit counselling services to help.</p>
<p>Making mistakes when it comes to financial management can be costly and stressful; if this tends to be challenging for you, learn from those who are savvy with their money.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/international-students/10-tried-and-tested-money-management-strategies-for-students">10 tried and tested money management strategies for students</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Top government benefits newcomers need to know about</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/featured/top-government-benefits-newcomers-need-to-know-about</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Archna Walia]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 15:37:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Future In Canada]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60362</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Moving to a new country can be an overwhelming experience, so having a little help is always welcome. In Canada, the federal and provincial governments offer help in the form of various benefits designed to help residents meet basic expenses — be it raising children or ensuring old-age income. Such benefits are also one of [&#8230;]</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/featured/top-government-benefits-newcomers-need-to-know-about">Top government benefits newcomers need to know about</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Moving to a new country can be an overwhelming experience, so having a little help is always welcome. In Canada, the federal and provincial governments offer help in the form of various benefits designed to help residents meet basic expenses — be it raising children or ensuring old-age income. Such benefits are also one of the reasons Canada is a preferred destination for immigrants from across the globe.</p>
<p>“It was only because of the government benefits that I was able to enhance my education and kickstart my career in a new country while simultaneously managing the cost of raising a family,” says Balmeet Singh, who immigrated to Canada three years back. Singh is pursuing his master’s degree in supply chain management from Schulich School of Business, York University, with the help of the student financial assistance program.</p>
<p>New to Canada? Here is a list of benefits to be aware of.</p>
<p><strong>Canada Pension Plan (CPP)</strong></p>
<p>The Canada Pension Plan (CPP) supports Canadians after they retire from work with a fixed monthly, taxable amount. Residents who are at least 60 years of age and have made contributions toward CPP during their active work years can access this benefit. The CPP contributions are automatically deducted by employers. Withdrawing the benefit can be deferred to 70 years of age. The amount received every month under CPP depends on several factors, including the amount earned throughout the person’s work life.</p>
<p><strong>READ MORE: Learn how the CPP is being invested for the future benefit of all Canadians in our special guide: <u><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/financial-future-in-canada" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Your Financial Future in Canada</a>.</u></strong><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Old Age Security (OAS)</strong></p>
<p>Canadians over 65 years of age can also receive the monthly, taxable Old Age Security (OAS) benefit to manage living expenses, if their annual income is under a certain threshold (in 2022, it’s less than $129,757).  The amount depends on the recipient’s time spent in Canada after turning 18 years of age. You must have resided in Canada for at least 10 years. If you lived in Canada for less than 40 years, your payment will be based on your number of years in Canada divided by 40.</p>
<p>While the benefit begins when you turn 65, there is the option to defer it until 70 years. The payment increases after turning 75 years old. In most cases, the beneficiary will automatically be enrolled for the benefit.</p>
<p><u><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/services/benefits/publicpensions/cpp/old-age-security.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Learn more about OAS here</a>.</u></p>
<p><strong>Guaranteed Income Supplement (GIS)</strong></p>
<p>The Guaranteed Income Supplement (GIS) further supports low-income seniors who receive or are eligible to receive OAS payments. Seniors who do not meet the income threshold (depending on their marital status) can receive this additional tax-free monthly payment.</p>
<p><u><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/services/benefits/publicpensions/cpp/old-age-security/guaranteed-income-supplement/benefit-amount.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Learn more here</a>.</u></p>
<p><strong>CPP Disability Benefit </strong></p>
<p>This financial assistance is for Canadian residents who have made contributions to CPP, and who have a physical or mental disability, or a long-term disability. It is paid to individuals only until they are 65 years of age, after which it is turned to regular CPP benefit. Dependent children of the recipients of the disability benefit may also receive a monthly payment.</p>
<p><u><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/services/benefits/publicpensions/cpp/cpp-disability-benefit.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Learn more here</a>.</u></p>
<p><strong>Canada Child Benefit (CCB) </strong></p>
<p>The Canada Child Benefit (CCB) is a non-taxable, monthly amount given by the government to parents of children under 18 years of age to help offset some of the expenses of raising children. The monthly amount depends upon the parent’s income and the number of children and is reassessed every year based on your tax return.</p>
<p>If your child is under age 18 with a severe and prolonged physical or mental impairment, you may also be eligible for the child disability benefit.</p>
<p><u><a href="www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/services/child-family-benefits/canada-child-benefit-overview/canada-child-benefit-we-calculate-your-ccb.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Learn more here</a>.</u></p>
<p><strong>Canada Learning Bond (CLB) </strong></p>
<p>The Canada Learning Bond (CLB) is an amount the government adds to the Registered Education Savings Plan (RESP) for children (born after 2004) of low-income families. The purpose of the bond is to help pay for the tuition for the child’s education after high school. The lifetime eligibility of the bond is $2,000. To apply, parents need to open a RESP account for their child and are given the option to complete a CLB application.</p>
<p><strong>Student Financial Assistance Program<br />
</strong>Each Canadian province offers financial assistance to students enrolled in a full-time or part-time program to help them pay for college or university. These are given in the form of either a loan (which you need to repay), a grant (which you do not have to repay) or both. While the eligibility criteria and details are different for each province, the assistance is usually offered to Canadian citizens or permanent residents.</p>
<p><u><a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/services/benefits/education/student-aid/grants-loans/province-apply.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Find out about student aid in your province here</a>.</u></p>
<p>Need more information or guidance about government benefits as a newcomer and how to apply? Contact your local immigrant settlement organization to help with this and other aspects of your settlement journey in Canada.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/featured/top-government-benefits-newcomers-need-to-know-about">Top government benefits newcomers need to know about</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Caring for a child with special needs: Strategies for newcomer families</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/wellness/caring-for-a-child-with-special-needs-strategies-for-newcomer-families</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Nandini Tirumala]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 21:56:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Living]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Parenting]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[children]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[disabilities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[newcomer families]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[special needs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60357</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Learning that your child is born with a chronic illness or has special needs can be devastating for all families; but even more so for newcomer families as they navigate an unfamiliar healthcare system, without traditional sources of community support.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/wellness/caring-for-a-child-with-special-needs-strategies-for-newcomer-families">Caring for a child with special needs: Strategies for newcomer families</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Learning that your child is born with a chronic illness or has special needs can be devastating for all families. But it can be isolating and extremely challenging for newcomer families as they navigate an unfamiliar healthcare system, without their traditional sources of community support.</p>
<p>The terminology, diagnosis, treatment options, hospital visits and assessment or therapy appointments can be overwhelming in a new country. Language and cultural barriers may also lead to limited involvement and contribution to decision making leading to helplessness and sometimes lack of trust in health professionals. Remember, you are not alone and can find the support you need.</p>
<p>To help navigate this situation in a new country and manage the family’s well-being, here are a few strategies that can be helpful.</p>
<p>1. Register for Early Intervention Services: Canada offers a lot of services to children with disabilities and supports for the families. Programs offered by Early Intervention Services in your region can help in providing necessary support and services.</p>
<p>2. Research and collect information: Educating oneself and reading books or articles written by professionals and other parents can help you learn and manage the everyday challenges you experience with your child. Talk to a specialist with an interpreter if you have language barriers or need support during the meeting. Asking questions and understanding the condition will help you support your child effectively at home.</p>
<p>3. Contact settlement services for newcomers: Sharing the diagnosis with a settlement worker can help you connect and develop a family settlement plan by assessing your family’s needs, strengths, resources and supports. Newcomer child care programs can support a kid with special needs while you are enrolled in language classes or undergoing any trainings.</p>
<p>4. Enroll in parenting skills classes: Enhance your parenting skills and learn how to manage difficult situations that you may encounter while caring for a child with special needs. You can also learn how to keep your child safe both at home and also outside. Many nonprofits and government agencies offer these programs.</p>
<p>5. Register for respite care services: Caring for a child with special needs can be stressful and exhausting. If you qualify for Respite Care (keep in mind, some providers have age requirements), you may get short term, temporary relief. Respite Care workers may visit you at home or take a child to a park and give you the much-needed break and support you need.</p>
<p>6. Share your emotions: Caring for a child with special needs can be physically and emotionally draining. Do not bottle up your emotions. Share with a parent or friend in your home country, join a support group or you could even seek support from a mental health professional.</p>
<p>7. Accept help when it is offered: If your spouse or a neighbour offers to help with cooking, cleaning, chores or taking turns playing with the child, be open to considering the help offered as it may give you time to do something different.</p>
<p>8. Support your marital relationship: Caregiving responsibilities may not always be equally shared, especially if one partner has to work to provide for the family and the other partner is home to take care of your child with special needs. In this situation, it is important that partners listen and support one another to strengthen the marital relationship. Settlement stress coupled with caregiving responsibilities can contribute to relationship breakdown in newcomer families.</p>
<p>9. Avail disability benefits: Both federal and provincial governments offer disability benefits for caring for a child with special needs and provide financial support. You can find information on the government’s website or you can ask a professional or a tax consultant for more details.</p>
<p>10. Connect with yourself: If you are religious or spiritual, prayers may help cope with the situation. For others, it could be taking a walk, meditation, painting or listening to music.</p>
<p>Research indicates that even if two children have the same diagnosis or disability profile, there will be individual differences in the symptoms, in their progress and also in health outcomes. Similarly, each family has its own unique strengths, resources and skills in managing a child with special needs. Maintaining realistic expectations, accessing support and being open to learning are beneficial in raising a child with special needs.</p>
<p>Be a strong advocate for your child and support them to develop skills, become independent and participate fully in society.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/wellness/caring-for-a-child-with-special-needs-strategies-for-newcomer-families">Caring for a child with special needs: Strategies for newcomer families</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CanadianImmigrant.ca: Sitemap</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/uncategorized/canadianimmigrant-ca-sitemap</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Staff Writer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 20:06:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60342</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>HOME Canadian Immigrant is a national multimedia platform to help immigrants succeed in Canada. Find the information, inspiration &#38; connections you need. TOP 25 CANADIAN IMMIGRANT AWARDS Welcome to the Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards! These coveted national awards recognize the achievements and accomplishments of Canadian immigrants. IMMIGRANT WOMEN OF INSPIRATION In honour of International [&#8230;]</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/uncategorized/canadianimmigrant-ca-sitemap">CanadianImmigrant.ca: Sitemap</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p><a href="https://www.canadianimmigrant.ca/">HOME</a></p>
<p>Canadian Immigrant is a national multimedia platform to help immigrants succeed in Canada. Find the information, inspiration &amp; connections you need.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/canadas-top-25-immigrants">TOP 25 CANADIAN IMMIGRANT AWARDS</a></p>
<p>Welcome to the Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards! These coveted national awards recognize the achievements and accomplishments of Canadian immigrants.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/immigrant-women-of-inspiration">IMMIGRANT WOMEN OF INSPIRATION</a></p>
<p>In honour of International Women’s Day each March, Canadian Immigrant has been recognizing some truly inspirational immigrant women in Canada since 2014.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/careerfair/">CANADIAN IMMIGRANT CAREER FAIR</a></p>
<p>Canada’s ultimate career fair and speakers’ series for skilled immigrants, newcomers, temporary workers, international students and other new Canadians.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/web-conference">CANADIAN IMMIGRANT WEB CONFERENCE SERIES</a></p>
<p>This new Canadian Immigrant Web Conference Series is a free, live webinar series assisting newcomers with information and inspiration.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/category/immigrate">IMMIGRATE</a></p>
<p>News and developments of immigration in Canada. Read latest updates and announcements about immigration in Canada.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/category/immigrate/pre-landing">PREPARING FOR LANDING IN CANADA</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Here’s what you need to know for preparing to move to Canada. Read about pre-arrival services, including resources for finding your first Canadian job.</p>
<ul>
<li><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/category/immigrate/how-to-immigrate">HOW TO IMMIGRATE</a></li>
</ul>
<p>Prepare to live in Canada – everything from filling out documentation to learning about sponsorship programs and discovering information about Canada’s ten provinces.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/category/international-students">INTERNATIONAL STUDENTS</a></p>
<p>Information that is helpful to international students to adjust to Canada and have a successful school year. Read our resources to help you succeed.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/category/careers-and-education">CAREERS AND EDUCATION</a></p>
<p>Information about starting a career and getting education in Canada for immigrants. Start your journey to success with our helpful articles.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/category/settlement">SETTLEMENT</a></p>
<p>Tips and advice to help you in your adjustment to day to day life in Canada and get settled. Find articles to support your journey.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/category/living">LIVING</a></p>
<p>Helpful information about living in Canada as an immigrant. Tips and advice to help you in your adjustment to day to day life in Canada.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/category/people">PEOPLE</a></p>
<p>Stories of immigrants who have made an impact in Canada. Read the latest stories of success and accomplishments making Canada a better place.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/category/money-and-business">MONEY AND BUSINESS</a></p>
<p>Helpful information about money management, business success, and more. Helpful information to help you find success as an immigrant to Canada.</p>
<p><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/find-a-job-home">FIND A JOB AND HOME</a></p>
<p>Looking to launch your career or looking for a home? View our resources to help you get started.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/uncategorized/canadianimmigrant-ca-sitemap">CanadianImmigrant.ca: Sitemap</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Award-winning Canadian LGBTQ+ South Asian documentary now available online</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/community/award-winning-canadian-lgbtq-south-asian-documentary-now-available-online</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ramya Ramanathan]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 16:04:16 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Community]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Living]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60325</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A new award-winning documentary, Emergence: Out of the Shadows', looks at the lonely and terrifying experiences of three South Asians - Kayden, Jag and Amar, and their struggle to express their sexuality within their conservative families.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/community/award-winning-canadian-lgbtq-south-asian-documentary-now-available-online">Award-winning Canadian LGBTQ+ South Asian documentary now available online</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A new award-winning documentary, <em>Emergence: Out of the Shadows</em>&#8216;, looks at the lonely and terrifying experiences of three South Asians &#8211; Kayden, Jag and Amar, and their struggle to express their sexuality within their conservative families.</p>
<p><iframe loading="lazy" title="EMERGENCE: Out of the Shadows | Official Trailer |  2021 | Sher Films Canada" width="770" height="433" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/VNjT3g1bf_Q?wmode=transparent&amp;rel=0&#038;showinfo=0" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture; web-share" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<p>This inspiring film documents their different journeys, distinct experiences and coming-out paths.  Tender, thoughtful and teary, the documentary asserts a potent and transformative voice in support of marginalized queer youth and their families. You can now watch the 81-minute documentary <a href="https://youtu.be/LxWII2Cztlg" target="_blank" rel="noopener">released on YouTube for free.</a></p>
<p>&#8220;The film focuses on the rights of these individuals to live an open and respectable life despite traditional and often strict family values and socio-cultural pressures,&#8221; says the film’s director and editor Vinay Giridhar.</p>
<p>The film has been screened in Canada and globally, and won a number of awards including the South Asian Film Festival Best Film Award for Championing Change at the UK Asian Film Festival (UKAFF).</p>
<p>“As an emerging BIPOC filmmaker, I am so grateful that my film is being embraced by some of the biggest LGBTQ+ and South Asian film festivals in the world.  I made <i>Emergence: Out of the Shadows</i> to educate the South Asian and broader community to break down barriers so no kids are disowned because of their sexuality.  I want to give hope and spread a message that we must all love one another and be kind,” states Giridhar.</p>
<p><i>“Emergence: Out of the Shadows</i> had a shoestring budget and is really a community project. The film was made by a registered charity, Sher Vancouver, that is pioneering non-profit and charitable film production in Canada.  As a result, we felt we had a social responsibility to make the film available on YouTube for everyone to access for free for maximum global impact,” states producer and cast member <span class="marky9d2afja6" data-markjs="true" data-ogac="" data-ogab="" data-ogsc="" data-ogsb="">Alex</span> <span class="markfyr9fzuhu" data-markjs="true" data-ogac="" data-ogab="" data-ogsc="" data-ogsb="">Sangha</span>.</p>
<p>Sangha is a <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/canadas-top-25-immigrants/canadas-top-25-immigrants-2011/alex-sangha">2011 winner</a> of Canadian Immigrant&#8217;s Top 25 Awards.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/community/award-winning-canadian-lgbtq-south-asian-documentary-now-available-online">Award-winning Canadian LGBTQ+ South Asian documentary now available online</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Canadian entrepreneurs prioritize operational efficiency over growth and debt repayment</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/money-and-business/small-business/canadian-entrepreneurs-prioritize-operational-efficiency-over-growth-and-debt-repayment</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canadian Immigrant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 02:41:04 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Money & Business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Small Business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[BDC]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[entrepreneurs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60320</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Most Canadian small and mid-sized enterprises (SMEs) expect an economic downturn in the coming year and are preparing to face challenges, says BDC’s study on the 2023 outlook for Canadian entrepreneurs.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/money-and-business/small-business/canadian-entrepreneurs-prioritize-operational-efficiency-over-growth-and-debt-repayment">Canadian entrepreneurs prioritize operational efficiency over growth and debt repayment</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Most Canadian small and mid-sized enterprises (SMEs) expect an economic downturn in the coming year,  according to BDC’s study entitled “<a href="https://www.bdc.ca/globalassets/digizuite/38998-bdc-outlook-canadian-entrepreneurs-needs-challenges-2023.pdf">Canadian Entrepreneurs’ Needs and Challenges: 2023 Outlook&#8221;.</a></p>
<p>The study reveals that SMEs are rather pessimistic about the current inflationary environment: most companies (52 per cent) believe that the worst is yet to come. They continue to feel the effects of persistent inflation, supply problems and the war in Ukraine. The slowdown in growth has impacted their planning, and 31 per cent are unprepared for it.</p>
<p><strong>Report highlights</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>More than half (52 per cent ) of business owners believe the economy will deteriorate in 2023.</li>
<li>Most businesses plan to limit investments due to economic uncertainty (26 pre cent), interest rate hikes (22 per cent) and declining sales (18 per cent).</li>
<li>Despite rate increases, 45 per cent of SMEs do not fear for their profitability and estimate their sales will be similar to what they were last year (42 per cent). Three-quarters are comfortable with their current level of debt.</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Important challenges ahead</strong></p>
<p>The next few months will be difficult for entrepreneurs in Canada, who cite rising costs (47 per cent), the economic slowdown (40 per cent) and internal cost control as the main obstacles to their activities. Over the next 12 months, SMEs still plan to invest and prioritize operational efficiency (38 per cent) over growth projects and debt repayment.</p>
<p>“In 2023, investing to be more efficient will be a way for many businesses to limit their decrease in profitability under current economic conditions,” says Pierre Cléroux, Vice President, Research and Chief Economist at BDC.</p>
<p>In 2022, the Bank adopted a renewed strategic vision with an intention to fulfill its role as a development bank even more ambitiously over the next few years, including as a shock absorber during economic downturns. As a result, BDC is creating a series of concrete and innovative measures that will expand the scope of its activities and use its solid financial footing to support more entrepreneurs in their development and growth.</p>
<p>BDC’s study was conducted in November 2022 among 1,500 Canadian small business owners to find out their level of confidence in the economy, their business prospects and their investment plans for the next 12 months.</p>
<p><em>Contributor Jean Philippe Nadeau is a media specialist with <a href="https://www.bdc.ca/en" target="_blank" rel="noopener">BDC</a>.</em></p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/money-and-business/small-business/canadian-entrepreneurs-prioritize-operational-efficiency-over-growth-and-debt-repayment">Canadian entrepreneurs prioritize operational efficiency over growth and debt repayment</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Canada welcomes historic number of newcomers in 2022</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/canada-welcomes-a-historic-number-of-newcomers-in-2022</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canadian Immigrant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 03 Jan 2023 22:38:22 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Immigrate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60313</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The Canadian government has announced meeting its target of 431,645 new permanent residents in 2022. In 2021, the country welcomed over 401,000 permanent residents, the highest number of newcomers in any year in Canadian history, surpassing the previous record from 1913! </p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/canada-welcomes-a-historic-number-of-newcomers-in-2022">Canada welcomes historic number of newcomers in 2022</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Canadian government has announced <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/news/2022/12/canada-welcomes-historic-number-of-newcomers-in-2022.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">meeting its target</a> of 431,645 new permanent residents in 2022. In 2021, Canada welcomed over 401,000 permanent residents, the highest number of newcomers in any year in Canadian history, surpassing the previous record from 1913!</p>
<p>In 2022, IRCC processed approximately 5.2 million applications for permanent residence, temporary residence and citizenship — double the number of applications processed in 2021.</p>
<p>Immigration minister Sean Fraser calls this an &#8220;important milestone&#8221; for the country. &#8220;Newcomers play an essential role in filling labour shortages, bringing new perspectives and talents to our communities, and enriching our society as a whole. I am excited to see what the future holds and look forward to another historic year in 2023 as we continue to welcome newcomers.”</p>
<p>As Canada focuses on addressing the acute labour market shortages and building a strong economy, one thing remains certain: immigration is a key part of the solution. To ensure efficient processing of applications, IRCC has added resources, embraced new technology, streamlined processing, and brought more processes online.</p>
<p>Roughly 75 percent of Canada’s population growth comes from immigration, mostly in the economic category. By 2036, immigrants are expected to represent up to 30 per cent of Canada’s population, a 10 per cent increase from 2011.</p>
<p>Immigrants account for 36 per cent of physicians, 33 per cent business owners with paid staff, and 41 per cent of engineers in the country.</p>
<p>In November 2022, Sean Fraser, Canada’s Minister of Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada, tabled Canada’s 2022 Annual Report to Parliament on Immigration along with their plans for 2023-2025.  November&#8217;s report generated considerable <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/immigrate/immigration-law/canada-boosts-immigration-targets-immigration-levels-plan-2023-2025" target="_blank" rel="noopener">media attention</a> because the government announced that its target for 2025 was to admit 500,000 new permanent residents.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/canada-welcomes-a-historic-number-of-newcomers-in-2022">Canada welcomes historic number of newcomers in 2022</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
