<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Canadian Immigrant</title>
	<atom:link href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/feed" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca</link>
	<description>Arrive. Succeed. Inspire.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 19:36:54 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>
	<item>
		<title>Windmill Microlending announces 5.95% fixed interest rate for new loans</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/windmill-microlending-announces-5-45-fixed-interest-rate-for-new-loans</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canadian Immigrant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 27 Jan 2023 19:36:08 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Financial Future In Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Money & Business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Settlement]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[interest rate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[micro loans]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[windmill microlending]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60439</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Windmill Microlending, a Canadian charity offering affordable loans to skilled immigrants and refugees, has announced that all new loans will be capped at a fixed interest rate of 5.95 per cent for the entire loan duration.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/windmill-microlending-announces-5-45-fixed-interest-rate-for-new-loans">Windmill Microlending announces 5.95% fixed interest rate for new loans</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>As a newcomer to Canada, one of the best ways to achieve success is to get a grasp of the financial landscape and plan for the future. And this is not easy given the tough economic climate we face as we enter 2023.</p>
<p>Rising inflation levels, a hike in interest rates and an increased cost of living have all created apprehension and anxiety for many skilled immigrants and refugees.  The impact of higher interest rates just as you are establishing a new life in Canada — building your career, finding housing, and growing your family, can be very frustrating.</p>
<p>In response to these uncertain times, Windmill Microlending, a Canadian charity offering affordable loans to skilled immigrants and refugees, has announced that all new loans will be capped at a <a href="https://windmillmicrolending.org/windmill-microlending-fixed-interest-rate/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">fixed interest rate</a> of 5.95 per cent for the entire loan duration. Capping this loan at this unprecedented below-prime rate, fixed interest rate is to ensure that the loans are accessible and affordable for newcomers.</p>
<p>By setting a fixed interest rate over the loan period, the organization seeks to ensure payment stability, providing newcomers with greater peace of mind when managing finances. The microloans help pay for the costs of  accreditation, training and career development.  In addition, the goal is to provide clients with the opportunity and build their confidence to secure roles that align with their skills and experience.</p>
<p>The organization hopes that this temporary measure will alleviate financial suffering for skilled immigrants and refugees as they utilize their full potential, in addition to contributing towards easing Canada’s labour shortage.</p>
<p>You can learn more <a href="https://windmillmicrolending.org/about/our-impact/">on the Windmill Microlending website here</a>.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/windmill-microlending-announces-5-45-fixed-interest-rate-for-new-loans">Windmill Microlending announces 5.95% fixed interest rate for new loans</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Nominations are now open for the 15th annual Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/nominations-are-now-open-for-the-15th-annual-top-25-canadian-immigrant-awards</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canadian Immigrant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 14:44:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2023 Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[nomination]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[tips on top 25 nomination]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60520</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The first and only national awards program celebrating immigrant success in Canada turns 15 this year. With the support of presenting sponsor Western Union, we are proud to open the call for nominations for the 2023 annual Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/nominations-are-now-open-for-the-15th-annual-top-25-canadian-immigrant-awards">Nominations are now open for the 15th annual Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The first and only national awards program celebrating immigrant success in Canada turns 15 this year! With the support of presenting sponsor <a href="https://smart.link/cem8akinkonlw" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Western Union</a>, we are proud to open the call for nominations for the 2023 annual Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards.</p>
<p>The Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards is the leader in sharing inspiring stories of immigrants and recognizing their contributions to their adopted country. Today, with rising immigration numbers, it’s as important as ever to combat negative stereotypes and spotlight how immigrants overcome systemic barriers to achieve personal success, give back to Canada and serve as role models for newcomers.  This year’s program is also supported by <a href="http://www.costi.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">COSTI Immigrant Services,</a> and <a href="https://windmillmicrolending.org/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Windmill Microlending</a>.</p>
<p>Immigrants who have been honoured with this prestigious national award in past years include national men’s soccer head coach, John Herdman; chief statistician of Canada, Anil Arora; celebrity restaurateur, Vikran Vij; prima ballerina, Chan Hon Goh; as well as many unsung heroes who have demonstrated incredible contributions in their communities and for the country.</p>
<p>“Fifteen years ago, we at <em>Canadian Immigrant</em> launched the Top 25 awards to shine a spotlight on the stories of immigrants who have come to Canada, achieved great things and made the country a better place,” says Sanjay Agnihotri, publisher of <em>Canadian Immigrant</em>. “Every year, we are so inspired by the people who are nominated and make it to the Top 25 and know — even a decade and a half later — that there are so many other success stories to tell.”</p>
<p>“We are honoured once again to sponsor and recognize these awards for the second year, as well as the hard work and sacrifices made by the new members of our community that are creating stronger bonds with citizens throughout the world, while contributing to the overall economic growth and well-being here at home,” says Ari Hagnas, Western Union general manager for Canada.</p>
<p><strong>Eligibility criteria and nomination process </strong></p>
<p>A nominee can be anyone who has immigrated to Canada and has since contributed to the success and uplifting of this country and/or its people. Achievements can be either professional or personal. Nominees must be aged 15 or older, hold permanent resident or citizen status in Canada, and reside in Canada.</p>
<p>Nominations can be made until March 10, 2023, 11:59 p.m. EST. A distinguished panel of judges made up of past winners will review all nominees and present a list of 75 finalists who will be announced in April, after which all Canadians can vote for their favourite nominees.</p>
<p>The 25 winners will be announced in August 2023 in <em>Canadian Immigrant</em> and online at canadianimmigrant.ca. Two of the winners will<br />
be selected for the Entrepreneur Award and Youth Award.</p>
<p><strong>So, do you know someone who deserves to be recognized among the top immigrants in Canada? Go to <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/canadas-top-25-immigrants/">www.canadianimmigrant.ca/top25</a> to nominate an immigrant or refugee who has an inspirational success story to share. </strong></p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/nominations-are-now-open-for-the-15th-annual-top-25-canadian-immigrant-awards">Nominations are now open for the 15th annual Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Winning advice for 2023!</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/featured/winning-advice-for-2023</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canadian Immigrant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 01:16:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Featured]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[People]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Top 25 Canadian Immigrants]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Winning advice]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60505</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>A few of our Top 25 Canadian Immigrants from 2022 share their thoughts, perspectives and some inspirational advice as we take on 2023!</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/featured/winning-advice-for-2023">Winning advice for 2023!</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3>A few of our Top 25 Canadian Immigrants from 2022 share their thoughts, perspectives and some inspirational advice as we take on 2023!</h3>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignleft wp-image-60513 " src="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Karla-1-150x150.jpg" alt="" width="262" height="262" srcset="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Karla-1-150x150.jpg 150w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Karla-1.jpg 300w" sizes="(max-width: 262px) 100vw, 262px" /><strong>Karla Briones</strong><br />
Entrepreneur and business strategist</p>
<p>“Purpose” is such a small word but carries a heavy meaning. Looking at everything I do through that lens has allowed me to guide how I live my life as a woman, an entrepreneur and a human being. Asking: Am I doing this with purpose? Am I moving with purpose? Am I eating with purpose? Am I living with purpose? If I’m not &#8211; then I course-correct. If I am, then I do more of that. Taking time to slow down to ask these question can be transformative.</p>
<p><em>City: Ottawa, Ontario</em><br />
<em>Country of origin: Mexico </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-60512 " src="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Rita-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="264" height="264" srcset="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Rita-1.jpg 300w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Rita-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 264px) 100vw, 264px" /><strong>Rita Chahal</strong><br />
Executive director, Mood Disorders Association of Winnipeg</p>
<p>The last few years have made us all realize how precious each moment is in our lives. If the pandemic has taught us anything it is to start having the candid conversations about our physical and, more importantly, our emotional wellbeing. While we all &#8220;pivoted&#8221; during the pandemic I believe it&#8217;s now time to &#8220;pirouette”. Don&#8217;t be afraid to ask for help if you need it – our vulnerability is often our greatest strength, and there is no shame in that!</p>
<p><em>City: Winnipeg, Manitoba</em><br />
<em>Country of origin: India</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-60515" src="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Diana-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="264" height="264" srcset="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Diana-1.jpg 300w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Diana-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 264px) 100vw, 264px" /><strong>Diana Alli D’Souza</strong><br />
President, Access Empowerment Council</p>
<p>Stay pragmatic and positive! I am 72 years young, and proudly can attest that I have never wasted a day brooding. Of course we grieve on losses of jobs, relations, family, friends and even friendships. A vision and mission have always been my foundation base since I was a young girl. I have chosen humanitarianism, even in my work, as my compass, using a framework of serving the most vulnerable populations in Canada and beyond.</p>
<p><em>City: Toronto, Ontario</em><br />
<em>Country of origin: India </em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-60510" src="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Tracy-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="265" height="265" srcset="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Tracy-1.jpg 300w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Tracy-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 265px) 100vw, 265px" /><strong>Tracy Folorunsho-Barry</strong><br />
Founder and CEO, GROW Women Leaders</p>
<p>Setting the bar high is important for GROW, so that we can support and encourage women, particularly immigrants, in order to reach their highest potential in their careers. It is important for me to forward this initiative because I know that immigrant women face immense isolation and struggles while trying to discover and establish themselves and career in a new country. The only way to quickly bridge the gap of inequalities is a well-calculated measure to get women working and creating a one-stop supported space with resources.<br />
<em>City: Edmonton, Alberta<br />
</em><em>Country of origin: Nigeria</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-60516" src="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Chef-Raquel-Fox-Headshot-2022-scaled-300x300-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="263" height="263" srcset="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Chef-Raquel-Fox-Headshot-2022-scaled-300x300-1.jpg 300w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Chef-Raquel-Fox-Headshot-2022-scaled-300x300-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 263px) 100vw, 263px" /><strong>Raquel Fox</strong><br />
Chef</p>
<p>A simple act of kindness goes a long way. Every award, accolade and career goals that I’ve achieved stemmed from the root of helping and supporting others. I’m a believer in: “Whatever you send into the universe comes back.” My advice to newcomers, is to ask yourself, “how can I contribute my skills or talent to Canada’s landscape?” Begin within your community by contributing with an attitude of gratitude, networking and being prepared whenever opportunities come your way.</p>
<p><em>City: Toronto, Ontario</em><br />
<em>Country of origin: Bahamas</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-60514" src="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Dr.-Sivakumar-Gulasingam-300x300-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="263" height="263" srcset="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Dr.-Sivakumar-Gulasingam-300x300-1.jpg 300w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Dr.-Sivakumar-Gulasingam-300x300-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 263px) 100vw, 263px" /><strong>Dr. Sivakumar Gulasingam</strong><br />
Physician and assistant professor at University of Toronto</p>
<p>As a newcomer, always remember that you are unique. Make use of every opportunity to integrate yourself into the Canadian culture; that will open up many doors personally and professionally. Self-confidence and perseverance are key to success. Don’t let others write your story. Trust yourself and continue to “better your best” in your new home.</p>
<p><em>City: Toronto, Ontario</em><br />
<em>Country of origin: Sri Lanka</em></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignleft wp-image-60511" src="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Ruairi-1-300x300.jpg" alt="" width="263" height="263" srcset="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Ruairi-1.jpg 300w, https://canadianimmigrant.ca/wp-content/uploads/Ruairi-1-150x150.jpg 150w" sizes="(max-width: 263px) 100vw, 263px" /> <strong>Ruairi Spillane</strong><br />
Managing director, Moving2Canada.com/Outpost Recruitment</p>
<p>Embrace the fact that a global recession, or slowdown, is happening in 2023. Having worked through the global financial crisis in 2008 as a newcomer to Canada, I know firsthand how stressful navigating a new country in a volatile market can be. What I’ve learned is that when the employment market is more competitive, it’s a good time to focus on communicating your value to employers. Spending your energy on what you can control is key to making the most of your Canadian journey.</p>
<p><em>City: Vancouver, British Columbia</em><br />
<em>Country of origin: Ireland</em></p>
<p>Know an inspiring immigrant in your life? Nominate them for the Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards of 2023 <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/top25">here</a>!</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/featured/winning-advice-for-2023">Winning advice for 2023!</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Recycling tips: Teach your children to take small steps for a better future</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/parenting/recycling-tips-teach-your-children-to-take-small-steps-for-a-better-future</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Cheryl Song]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 21:51:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Living]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Parenting]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60497</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>There is no time like today to start recycling, to help improve the environment for future generations. Recycling can reduce pollution and landfill waste, and help with protecting our natural resources, ecosystem and wildlife.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/parenting/recycling-tips-teach-your-children-to-take-small-steps-for-a-better-future">Recycling tips: Teach your children to take small steps for a better future</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>There is no time like today to start recycling, to help improve the environment for future generations. Recycling can reduce pollution and landfill waste, and help with protecting our natural resources, ecosystem and wildlife. Here are some recycling tips.</p>
<p><strong>Learn about the 3Rs – Recycle, Reduce, Reuse</strong></p>
<p>Teach children the importance of reducing waste. Get your children involved so that they will grow up to be environmentally conscious. With careful planning and organizing, everyone in family can play an important role in recycling. Designate a recycling area with clear labels and containers at your home. Based on the age of children, assign them different recycling tasks, such as sorting the recyclables or putting the recyclables to the curb.</p>
<p><strong>Abide by your city’s regulations</strong></p>
<p>Know your city and housing recycling and garbage disposal bylaws. Failure to abide by bylaws may result in fines. Check out your local recycling and waste management websites and apps that can provide residents with the schedule, service alerts and reminders. Some websites even have apps and programs for young children to learn about recycling.</p>
<p><strong>Care for the environment</strong></p>
<p>Consider putting a composter and rain barrel in your backyard to help with your gardening. Donate healthy plants and harvest from your garden with others. When out in nature, teach your children to put garbage in the designated garbage or recycle bins. If there is no place to discard garbage or recyclable materials, take them with you to dispose later, to avoid littering in nature.</p>
<p><strong>Give items a second life</strong></p>
<p>Consider selling or donating usable household materials to local consignment stores, thrift stores or give them to friends and families. Find ways to fix or reuse items, such as upcycling and repurposing things or reusing items for craft projects or donating extra craft and supplies to local schools and charities. Check websites where you can give away or sell items online.</p>
<p><strong>Cut down on disposables</strong></p>
<p>When shopping, make conscious decisions to buy products made with recycled materials, and/or less packaging. To reduce your carbon footprint, make an extra effort to buy local and buy less. Use reusable containers instead of use disposable bags or juice bottles for children’s lunch. Bring your own reusable shopping bags when shopping and your own containers for food takeout.</p>
<p>Recycling as a family does require extra time and effort to start, but the impact and benefits are well worth the effort. Commit to making recycling part of your family routine, and teach your children to make the planet a greener and better place for future generations to come.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/parenting/recycling-tips-teach-your-children-to-take-small-steps-for-a-better-future">Recycling tips: Teach your children to take small steps for a better future</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Nominations are now open for the 15th annual  Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Award, presented by Western Union</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/nominations-are-now-open-for-the-15th-annual-top-25-canadian-immigrant-award-presented-by-western-union</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Staff Writer]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 24 Jan 2023 12:06:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[2023 Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top 25 canadian immigrant awards]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[top25]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60553</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>15 years of celebrating immigrant success in Canada! TORONTO, January 25, 2023 – Fifteen years ago, Canadian Immigrant magazine launched the first and only national awards program celebrating immigrant success. Today, with the support of presenting sponsor Western Union, we are proud to open the call for nominations for the 15th annual Top 25 Canadian [&#8230;]</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/nominations-are-now-open-for-the-15th-annual-top-25-canadian-immigrant-award-presented-by-western-union">Nominations are now open for the 15th annual  Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Award, presented by Western Union</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h3><strong><em>15 years of celebrating immigrant success in Canada!</em></strong></h3>
<p><strong>TORONTO, January 25, 2023 –</strong> Fifteen years ago, <em>Canadian Immigrant</em> magazine launched the first and only national awards program celebrating immigrant success. Today, with the support of presenting sponsor Western Union, we are proud to open the call for nominations for the 15th annual Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards of 2023.</p>
<p>The Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Awards is the leader in sharing inspiring stories of immigrants and recognizing their contributions to their adopted country. Today, with rising immigration numbers, it’s as important as ever to combat negative stereotypes and spotlight how immigrants overcome systemic barriers to achieve personal success, give back to Canada and serve as role models for newcomers.  This year’s program is also supported by <a href="http://www.costi.org/">COSTI Immigrant Services</a>, and <a href="https://windmillmicrolending.org/">Windmill Microlending</a>.</p>
<p>Do you know someone who deserves to be recognized among the top immigrants in Canada? <em>Canadian Immigrant</em> and presenting sponsor <a href="https://smart.link/eqamqamplilhe">Western Union</a> are now calling on Canadians to nominate an immigrant or refugee who has an inspirational success story to share at <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/canadas-top-25-immigrants">canadianimmigrant.ca/top25</a>.</p>
<p>Immigrants who have been honoured with this prestigious national award in past years include National Men’s Soccer Head Coach John Herdman, Chief Statistician of Canada Anil Arora, celebrity restaurateur Vikram Vij, prima ballerina Chan Hon Goh, as well as many unsung heroes who have demonstrated incredible contributions in their communities and for the country.</p>
<p>“Fifteen years ago, we at <em>Canadian Immigrant </em>launched the Top 25 awards to shine a spotlight on the stories of immigrants who have come to Canada, achieved great things and made the country a better place,” said Sanjay Agnihotri, Publisher of <em>Canadian Immigrant</em>, a national multimedia platform and producer of the awards. “Every year, we are so inspired by the people who are nominated and make it to the Top 25 and know — even a decade and a half later — that there are so many other success stories to tell.”</p>
<p><em>“The impacts made by migrants are not only felt here in Canada, but all over the world, said Ari Hagnas, Western Union General Manager for Canada. “While their contributions are recognized here domestically, migrants are also sending money back home, helping improve the lives of friends and families and strengthen the local economies of their originating countries.”</em></p>
<p><em>“We are honored once again to sponsor and recognize these awards for the second year, as well as the hard work and sacrifices made by the new members of our community that are creating stronger bonds with citizens throughout the world, while contributing to the overall economic growth and well-being here at home, he added.”</em></p>
<p><strong>Eligibility Criteria</strong></p>
<p>A nominee can be anyone who has immigrated to Canada and has since contributed to the success and uplifting of this country and/or its people. Achievements can be either professional or personal. Nominees must be aged 15 or older, hold landed immigrant (permanent resident) or citizen status in Canada, and reside in Canada.</p>
<p><strong>Entrepreneur Award</strong></p>
<p>This will be the ninth consecutive year that one of the Top 25 winners will also be selected for the additional Entrepreneur Award, honouring one of the Top 25 who has demonstrated entrepreneurial excellence in business. No additional application is required to apply for this award.</p>
<p><strong>Youth Award</strong></p>
<p>For the seventh consecutive year, one of the Top 25 will be awarded the additional Youth Award, which recognizes young immigrants between the ages of 15 and 30 who are making a difference through achievement and/or service, and who exhibit great potential as long-term contributors to Canada. No additional application is required to apply for this award.</p>
<p><strong>Nomination Process</strong></p>
<p>Nominations can be made at www.canadianimmigrant.ca/top25 until March 10, 2023, 11:59 p.m. EST. A distinguished panel of judges made up of past winners will review all nominees and present a list of 75 finalists who will be announced in April, after which all Canadians can vote for their favourite nominees. The 25 winners will be announced in August 2023 in <em>Canadian Immigrant </em>and online at <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">CanadianImmigrant.ca</a>.</p>
<p><strong>About Canadian Immigrant</strong></p>
<p>Attracting more than 400,000 readers each month and over 100,000 visitors a month online, Canadian Immigrant is a national multimedia platform to help immigrants succeed in Canada, with content, resources and events on careers, education and settlement. Canadian Immigrant is the producer of the cross-country Canadian Immigrant Fairs. Canadian Immigrant is a division of Metroland Media Group, a dynamic media company with more than 100 community and daily newspapers in print and online, as well as innovative websites including wheels.ca, goldbook.ca, save.ca and localwork.ca. Learn more at <a href="http://www.canadianimmigrant.ca">canadianimmigrant.ca</a>.<strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>About Western Union</strong></p>
<p>Western Union is a global leader in cross-border, cross-currency money movement and payments. Western Union’s platform provides seamless cross-border flows and its leading global financial network bridges more than 200 countries and territories and over 130 currencies. We connect businesses, financial institutions, governments, and consumers through one of the world’s widest reaching networks, accessing billions of bank accounts, millions of digital wallets and cards, and approximately 600,000 retail locations. Western Union connects the world to bring boundless possibilities within reach.</p>
<p><strong>For more information, contact:</strong></p>
<p><strong>Canadian Immigrant</strong></p>
<p>Laura Jackman: <u><a href="mailto:ljackman@metroland.com">ljackman@metroland.com</a></u><strong> </strong></p>
<p><strong>Western Union</strong></p>
<p>Brad Jones: Bradley.Jones@wu.com</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/news/nominations-are-now-open-for-the-15th-annual-top-25-canadian-immigrant-award-presented-by-western-union">Nominations are now open for the 15th annual  Top 25 Canadian Immigrant Award, presented by Western Union</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Significant Benefit Work Permits: Understanding the LMIA exemption</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/immigrate/immigration-law/significant-benefit-work-permits-understanding-the-lmia-exemption</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven Meurrens]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 23 Jan 2023 23:13:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Immigrate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Immigration Law]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[#ImmigrationMatters]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Labour Market Impact Assessment (LMIA)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[labour market needs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60490</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>On December 15, 2022, Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (IRCC) updated its Labour Market Impact Assessment (LMIA) exemption codes. An LMIA is an opinion from Service Canada that the entry of a foreign worker will have a positive or neutral impact on the Canadian labour market.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/immigrate/immigration-law/significant-benefit-work-permits-understanding-the-lmia-exemption">Significant Benefit Work Permits: Understanding the LMIA exemption</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On December 15, 2022, Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (IRCC) updated its Labour Market Impact Assessment (LMIA) exemption codes. An LMIA is an opinion from Service Canada that the entry of a foreign worker will have a positive or neutral impact on the Canadian labour market. To obtain a positive LMIA, employers must generally recruit for four weeks on prescribed websites, invite potentially qualified Canadians to apply, pay prevailing wage, and demonstrate other labour market benefits. The process is often difficult.</p>
<p>Because of this, and other reasons, Canadian immigration legislation allows IRCC to issue work permits in certain circumstances without employers needing to obtain LMIAs. These are known as LMIA exemptions.</p>
<p>For the most part, the December 15, 2022, changes involve renumbering some of the LMIA exemptions and splitting previous exemptions into several categories. Future changes are expected. There were, however, important changes to the LMIA exemptions for provincial nominees in business programs and other entrepreneurs. These changes involve the introduction of “significant benefit” tests.</p>
<p><strong>Significant Benefit exemption</strong></p>
<p>IRCC has always had an LMIA exemption for individuals whose work in Canada would generate significant economic, social or cultural benefits.</p>
<p>Generally, economic benefits are benefits that would contribute to a company’s growth, expansion or continuation that have fiscal benefits and allow for the competitive advantage of Canada’s business community. Social benefits are where someone’s work will provide significant external benefits to other third parties not directly involved in business transactions. Culture is defined as creative artistic activities and the goods and services produced by it.</p>
<p>Significant includes, but is not limited to, an assessment of how the work of a foreign national will provide general economic support for Canada, advancement of Canadian industry, increased health and well-being or increased tolerance or opportunities to come together with others of similar culture.</p>
<p>The IRCC website provides examples of all of the above. It cautions that visa officers should be reluctant to issue work permits under the category, but also notes that where an LMIA is not available, and the balance of practical considerations indicates that the work of a foreign national would be of significant benefit to Canada, economically, socially, or culturally, then a work permit can be issued without the LMIA.</p>
<p><strong>Provincial Nominee Program for entrepreneurs</strong></p>
<p>Prior to December 15, 2022, prospective provincial nominees who were issued work permit support letters by a provincial government to be entrepreneurs in a province did not need to also demonstrate that their work in Canada would generate a significant economic, social or cultural benefit.</p>
<p>This is no longer the case. Now, under a new LMIA Exemption Code C-60, entrepreneurs applying for work permits under provincial nominee programs will generally need to demonstrate that their proposed work will provide general economic stimulus or the advancement of Canadian industry. They will also need to provide business plans which show that they have the experience to manage the business, the language abilities needed to operate the business and that their work will be of significant benefit. Provincial letters of support may be indicative, but IRCC will now it seems essentially be reassessing provincial nomination applications.</p>
<p>The consequence of this change is significant and could potentially reduce the attractiveness and predictability of provincial nominee entrepreneur programs. The change is recent and has not been widely publicized. Those considering applying to provincial entrepreneur programs, as well as those who may represent them, need to understand the new LMIA Exemption Code C-60.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/immigrate/immigration-law/significant-benefit-work-permits-understanding-the-lmia-exemption">Significant Benefit Work Permits: Understanding the LMIA exemption</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The top financial terms worth knowing</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/financial-future-in-canada/the-top-financial-terms-worth-knowing</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Guest Author]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 18:25:17 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Financial Future In Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[CPP]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[financial planning]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[saving]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60446</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Planning for the future is never easy, and sometimes sorting through all the terminology you see in the business section can be daunting. To help, CPP Investments, along with Canadian Immigrant magazine offer this glossary of terms used by investors, advisors, and other people who deal with money and planning on a daily basis. Active [&#8230;]</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/financial-future-in-canada/the-top-financial-terms-worth-knowing">The top financial terms worth knowing</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Planning for the future is never easy, and sometimes sorting through all the terminology you see in the business section can be daunting. To help, CPP Investments, along with <em>Canadian Immigrant</em> magazine offer this glossary of terms used by investors, advisors, and other people who deal with money and planning on a daily basis.</p>
<p><strong>Active Management</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A strategy that tries to capture price gains by buying investments that a manager believes have more underlying worth than their current price. This approach requires careful timing of when investments are bought and sold.</p>
<p><strong>Annuity</strong><strong><br />
</strong>An income stream paid out by a life insurance company. Payments happen over set time periods, or until the policyholder dies. The word also describes a type of insurance policy that pays out this income stream. An <strong>Annuitant </strong>holds the annuity and receives the income stream.</p>
<p><strong>Asset(s)</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Anything that has value. For an investment company, this can be shares in a company, or bonds, or the physical assets a company owns. Personal property, such as a house or condominium, also is called an asset by financial advisors and planners.</p>
<p><strong>Asset Allocation</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A combination of assets in an investor’s portfolio. Financial advisors will often refer to this in percentage terms — for example, saying that you hold 50% of your assets in stocks, 40% in bonds and 10% in cash.</p>
<p><strong>Average Return</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A number you get when you add up how much more an investment is worth when compared with the price you first paid, and then divide the difference by the number of years you held that investment.</p>
<p><strong>Balanced Mutual Fund</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Fund that spreads out an investor’s risk by combining bonds, cash, stocks and other investments from a variety of economic sectors and geographic regions.</p>
<p><strong>Bear Market</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A period during which investments, like stocks or bonds, lose value.</p>
<p><strong>Benchmark Index</strong><strong><br />
</strong>The Dow Jones Industrial Average is one example of an index used to measure the performance of investment markets. Others include the TSX/S&amp;P and the Nasdaq Composite.</p>
<p><strong>Beneficiary</strong><strong><br />
</strong>The person who receives the funds from an insurance policy or other investment.</p>
<p><strong>Bond</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Debt issued by governments or companies. Bonds are typically issued at fixed interest rates and require the issuer to repay investors after a set period of time. A <strong>Bond Fund</strong> is comprised exclusively of bonds and is sometimes called a <strong>Fixed-Income Fund</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Budget</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A calculation of how much you spend each month, compared against how much money you bring home.</p>
<p><strong>Bull Market</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A period during which the value of investments, like stocks or bonds, goes up.</p>
<p><strong>CPP</strong><strong><br />
</strong>The <a href="https://www.cppinvestments.com/commitments/retirement-starts-here/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Canada Pension Plan</a> is available to all employed or self-employed Canadians in provinces outside Quebec. Quebec has its own plan called the <strong>QPP</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Capital</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Cash or other assets that can be used to buy stocks, bonds, real estate or other things of value.</p>
<p><strong>Capital Gain</strong><strong><br />
</strong>The return, some of which is taxed, that is earned when selling an investment that has increased in value. When investors lose money, that’s called a <strong>Capital Loss</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Common Stock</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Shares of ownership in a company that’s traded on a stock exchange. Prices of common stock shares change constantly based on what people are willing to pay. By contrast, <strong>Preferred Stock</strong> shares have a base value that the company is required to refund to shareholders if the company ceases operations or liquidates.</p>
<p><strong>Compounding</strong><strong><br />
</strong>The interest you earn on an investment or within a bank account when you reinvest, rather than spend. That money is said to compound because the interest builds faster.</p>
<p><strong>CPI</strong><strong><br />
</strong>The Consumer Price Index averages the cost of a variety of services and goods people buy.</p>
<p><strong>Contribution Room</strong><strong><br />
</strong>How much money you can put into an <strong>RRSP</strong> or <strong>TFSA</strong> each year. Contribution room can be carried to the next year if you don’t use all of it.</p>
<p><strong>Correlation</strong><strong><br />
</strong>How the returns from one investment are tied to those of a different investment. Different economic sectors, such as agriculture and manufacturing, may be correlated to one another.</p>
<p><strong>Coupon Rate</strong><strong><br />
</strong>The interest rate on a bond. When a government or company issues a bond, it agrees to pay an agreed-upon interest rate to the buyer. At one time, a paper tab called a coupon showing the interest rate was attached to the bottom of the bond certificate, and the name stuck.</p>
<p><strong>Death Benefit</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Money paid to people named as beneficiaries of an insurance policy, or in the case of an investment, to a named person or the estate of the deceased.</p>
<p><strong>Defined Benefit Plan</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Usually an employer-sponsored pension plan that lets you determine how much monthly income you are entitled to receive after retiring. A <strong>Defined Contribution Plan</strong> bases that monthly sum on how much you contribute while working.</p>
<p><strong>Diversification</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A process that spreads investments out by type (stocks, bonds, etc.), economic sector (technology, consumer goods, etc.) and the region where investments are made (within Canada, globally, etc.) to reduce the risk that poor economic performance in one region or sector may cause harm to the entire portfolio.</p>
<p><strong>Dividends</strong><strong><br />
</strong>When you own shares of stock (either <strong>Preferred</strong> or <strong>Common</strong>), you may get income in the form of dividends. They are paid to the shareholder.</p>
<p><strong>Economic Indicators</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Government statistics showing how a country’s economy is performing.</p>
<p><strong>Equities</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Stocks or other shares of ownership in a company.</p>
<p><strong>ETFs</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Exchange-Traded Funds are investment products that mimic many popular stock indexes like the TSX/S&amp;P.</p>
<p><strong>Financial Planner</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Sometimes called an <strong>Investment Advisor</strong>, these professionals help people select investments that are suitable for their financial circumstances and the length of time before they plan to retire.</p>
<p><strong>Fiscal Year</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A 365-day period that a corporation or business uses for its internal accounting. Often tied to the day and month when a company began doing business, it may or may not match up with the calendar year.</p>
<p><strong>Fixed Income</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Investments, and sometimes funds, made up of bonds and other financial instruments that earn returns at a predetermined rate.</p>
<p><strong>GICs</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Guaranteed Investment Certificates are primarily sold by banks and pay a set rate of interest for a specific time period (six months, one year, two years, etc.). Interest rates are generally a bit higher than what a bank offers for its standard savings accounts. Cashing in a GIC early can result in a penalty.</p>
<p><strong>Income</strong><strong><br />
</strong>How much you earn from an employer or, for the self-employed, from a business you own and run. Financial advisors may refer to money that’s left over after you’ve paid your bills as <strong>Discretionary Income</strong>. Income also can be earned from your investments. <strong>Interest Income </strong>is earned from bonds, bond funds, fixed-income funds or GICs.</p>
<p><strong>Inflation</strong><strong><br />
</strong>When prices for food, shelter, housing and other things increase over a period of time. The opposite is deflation – which rarely happens.</p>
<p><strong>IPO</strong><strong><br />
</strong>An Initial Public Offering is when shares of a company go up for sale to the public on the open market for the first time.</p>
<p><strong>Institutional Investor</strong><strong><br />
</strong>An organization that invests money in the interests of a larger group – like a pension fund.</p>
<p><strong>Investment Dealer</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A stockbroker or other securities firm.</p>
<p><strong>Investment Horizon</strong><strong><br />
</strong>The time between now and when you will need the money from your investments. For most people, their Investment Horizon extends to when they retire. Also called a <strong>Time Horizon</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>Investment Portfolio</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Combination of stocks, bonds or other securities designed to earn money for investors. A <strong>Portfolio Manager</strong> selects and oversees the investments that go into the investment portfolio.</p>
<p><strong>Life Annuity</strong><strong><br />
</strong>An insurance product that pays the owner a specific amount of income (usually monthly) for as long as he or she lives.</p>
<p><strong>Life Insurance</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A financial instrument that pays your heirs a set sum of money upon your death.</p>
<p><strong>Liquidity</strong><strong><br />
</strong>How easy it is to sell an investment at the current market price.</p>
<p><strong>MER</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A Management Expense Ratio is a number calculated based on costs (called <strong>Management Fees</strong>) to operate a mutual fund, including fees paid to the fund’s managers.</p>
<p><strong>Maturity Date</strong><strong><br />
</strong>When a bond must be paid to its owner at full value.</p>
<p><strong>Money Market</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A fund that invests in low-risk financial instruments, such as government bonds.</p>
<p><strong>Mutual Fund</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A portfolio of investments that’s divided into units, giving buyers access to all of the fund’s holdings. Mutual funds have managers who buy and sell the investments it holds.</p>
<p><strong>OAS</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Old Age Security is monthly income paid to those over age 67 who are living in Canada.</p>
<p><strong>RESP</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A Registered Education Saving Plan lets parents or grandparents defer tax when saving for a child’s education. The government also kicks in 20% of what you pay into the account (up to defined limits) each year through a program called the <strong>Canada Education Savings Grant</strong>.</p>
<p><strong>RPP</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Some employers set up Registered Pension Plans to help their workers retire. Contributions are tax deductible and employers generally contribute a portion of the funds that go into the plan. Upon retirement, an RPP is converted to a <strong>LIF</strong> (Life Income Fund).</p>
<p><strong>RRSP</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A Registered Retirement Savings Plan lets Canadians invest part of their annual income and not pay tax on the returns until they retire. Annual contribution limits are set by Ottawa. After retirement, an RRSP is converted to a <strong>RRIF</strong> (Registered Retirement Income Fund).</p>
<p><strong>Return</strong><strong><br />
</strong>What you receive back from an investment as interest or dividends. Also called <strong>ROI</strong> (Return on Investment).</p>
<p><strong>Risk Tolerance</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Your ability to cope with upward and downward movement in the prices of your investments.</p>
<p><strong>Savings</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Funds set aside for future needs. You can use savings for short-term needs, like a new roof or car, or for longer-term goals, like educating children or for your retirement.</p>
<p><strong>Securities</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Usually stocks and bonds, but sometimes shares in other investments of value.</p>
<p><strong>Segregated Fund</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A specialized mutual fund that’s linked to an annuity or other insurance policy. A <strong>Variable Annuity</strong>, which pays an income to the holder based on the value of the fund investment, is a type of Segregated Fund.</p>
<p><strong>Shareholder</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Someone who owns stock shares issued by a corporation.</p>
<p><strong>Stock</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Share in the ownership of a corporation.</p>
<p><strong>Stock Exchange</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Place where stocks and bonds, and sometimes other investments, are bought and sold. They ensure the prices of investments reflect the supply and the public demand – or lack thereof.</p>
<p><strong>TFSA</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A Tax-Free Savings Account is offered by a financial institution (a bank or other investment dealer) and lets the owner invest $5,500 each year, while sheltering proceeds from those investments from tax. Unlike an RRSP, it’s easier to withdraw from a TFSA before retirement.</p>
<p><strong>Trading Costs</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Fees and commissions that brokers charge to buy and sell stocks, bonds and other investments.</p>
<p><strong>Volatility</strong><strong><br />
</strong>A period when the value of investments moves up or down rapidly, and sometimes unexpectedly.</p>
<p><strong>Yield</strong><strong><br />
</strong>Investment returns over time.</p>
<p><strong>Want to learn more about CPP Investments and your financial future as a new Canadian? Check back <u><a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/financial-future-in-canada">here</a></u>  for new content every month, or read more articles, access resources and watch videos at </strong><a href="http://www.cppinvestments.com/commitment-to-canadians" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><strong>www.cppinvestments.com/commitment-to-canadians</strong></a><strong>.</strong></p>
<p><em>This content is provided for information purposes only. CPP Investments is not a financial advisor, and the content on this site does not provide financial advice. Every person’s financial planning needs are different. For advice on how you should prepare financially for retirement, please consult a credentialed professional financial advisor.</em></p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/financial-future-in-canada/the-top-financial-terms-worth-knowing">The top financial terms worth knowing</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sicilian-born chef Roberto Marotta brings flavours of his homeland to Toronto</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/entrepreneur-immigrants/sicilian-born-chef-roberto-marotta-brings-flavours-of-his-homeland-to-toronto</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Lisa Evans]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 15:19:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Entrepreneurs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[People]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[entrepreneur]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Italian-Canadian]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[restaurateur]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60411</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>For Chef Roberto Marotta, it was love at first sight. His now wife and business partner Jacqueline Nicosia was visiting family in Sicily when they met, and he decided to follow his heart and move to Toronto, bringing his culinary expertise.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/entrepreneur-immigrants/sicilian-born-chef-roberto-marotta-brings-flavours-of-his-homeland-to-toronto">Sicilian-born chef Roberto Marotta brings flavours of his homeland to Toronto</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>For Chef Roberto Marotta, it was love at first sight. His now wife and business partner Jacqueline Nicosia was visiting family in Sicily when she met Marotta. “She was supposed to be there two weeks and she stayed over a year,” he says.</p>
<p>For Chef Roberto Marotta, it was love at first sight. His now wife and business partner Jacqueline Nicosia was visiting family in Sicily when they met, and he decided to follow his heart, and dive into a new culture.</p>
<p>But Nicosia was from Toronto and decided she wanted to move back to where she grew up and invited her Sicilian fiancé to return home with her. Marotta had never thought of immigrating to Canada, but was willing to dive into a new culture and a new life.</p>
<p>&#8220;I’ve always been very adventurous in my career. You never know in life until you try and I was in love, so it made it easy,” he says.</p>
<p>He was met with 9 cm of snow on the ground and -10 C weather. “It was interesting,” says Marotta. “I got the feeling it would be a challenge to adjust.”</p>
<p>Back home in Italy, Marotta ran a successful restaurant on the water in Milazzo in Sicily called &#8216;Mood&#8217; that specialized in the region&#8217;s cuisine. He wanted to continue to share his love for his country’s food and culture in his new home, Toronto. But he was now starting from scratch, and was going to have to learn everything about the produce, meats and seafood available here. Knowing he had to get some boots on the ground to figure out how the restaurant scene worked, Marotta began working for a few restaurants.</p>
<p>The most interesting to Marotta was the very different and very short seasons in Toronto. For fresh fruits and vegetables, the season goes from beginning of June to the end of September, a much more concentrated growing season than what Marotta was used to in Italy.</p>
<p>Aside from the seasonality of fresh foods here, Marotta was struck by how different the restaurant supply chain is from what he was used to in Italy. While running his restaurant in Sicily, Marotta knew local fisherman personally and would meet them at the boat daily. “The fisherman, the farmer, they became your friend.” In Toronto, the supply chain requires a lot more logistics management to ensure high quality ingredients. You cannot simply walk down to the dock to get fresh fish. Instead, seafood is flown overnight from all over the world. This global way of supplying the restaurant was new to Marotta, who was used to having direct personal contact with product suppliers.</p>
<p>Marotta took on a few partnership ventures that ultimately failed. “Some people promised me a partnership, developing the concept, designing the menu. Three times it (failed) before I finally decided I can’t do this for other people,” says Marotta. His wife quit her job and the two decided to open their own restaurant, one that would allow Marotta to showcase the flavours of his homeland, Sicily.</p>
<p>“My son was three years old. We’d just bought a house. It was a risky time but I think it was the right thing to do,” he says.</p>
<p>Ardo, named after Marotta’s son, Leonardo, who couldn’t quite pronounce his full name as a toddler and called himself “Ardo”, opened in 2016. The restaurant is located in the King Street area of Toronto, close to the St. Lawrence Market.</p>
<p>When Marotta struggled to find some of the quality ingredients he was used to using back home, he and his wife launched Vivi Imports, named after their daughter Vivienne, to bring fine ingredients from Sicily to Canada. These authentic Sicilian products, such as olive oils, sauces and chocolates, are not only used in their restaurants, but are sold in fine foods stores across the GTA.</p>
<p>Marotta has even found a way to recreate the structure of relationships he had with suppliers back home. “I now have direct contact with a fisherman in Newfoundland. He has three or four boats. He’ll call me and say this is what we caught. It will be in Toronto in the next 48 hours.” Marotta also has a Portuguese supplier who he sources seafood from. “It flies overnight,” he says.</p>
<p>The public response to Ardo’s opening has been positive since day one. “A lot of my customers have travelled a couple of times a year to Italy. They have a sense of what elevated Italian cuisine can be.”</p>
<p>Marotta says he is often greeted by customers who are delighted to return to Toronto and seeing something that has the level of quality of what they had in Italy. Ardo was even named one of Toronto Life’s favourite Italian restaurants.</p>
<p>After the success of Ardo, Marotta decided to open a second restaurant, called Dova. Located in Cabbagetown, Toronto, the restaurant opened in August 2020.</p>
<p>Although Marotta has been no stranger to road blocks including COVID delaying his second restaurant’s opening, failed partnership ventures and navigating a new work culture, he attributes his success to his perseverance.</p>
<p>&#8220;When you immigrate, when you move from another place, it’s going to be a challenge. Everything is going to be new and different. You have to have an open mind,” he says.</p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/entrepreneur-immigrants/sicilian-born-chef-roberto-marotta-brings-flavours-of-his-homeland-to-toronto">Sicilian-born chef Roberto Marotta brings flavours of his homeland to Toronto</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Earn your black belt in money management</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/money-and-business/earn-your-black-belt-in-money-management</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canadian Immigrant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 15:13:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Banking]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Investing]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Money & Business]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[manage your finances]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[money management]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60427</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>As a life time martial arts student, who is also a financial planner and an immigrant, Alireza Fadai has come up with a "black belt money management" system to help people take proper steps in the right direction.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/money-and-business/earn-your-black-belt-in-money-management">Earn your black belt in money management</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Imagine you want to get a black belt in a martial arts. You start from the basics — the white belt, and as you get to the black belt level you put together what you have learned. As a life time martial arts student, who is also a financial planner and an immigrant, I have come up with a system to help people take proper steps in the right direction.</p>
<p>Below are some quick tips that I have covered extensively in my book and online course called, <em>Black Belt Money Management: A practical guide to personal finance for Canadians</em>.</p>
<p><strong>White belt</strong>: This is where you need to learn the fundamentals, know where you are standing financially and where you like to go. What are your financial goals and concerns? Not everyone will have the same workout and diet plan. You will train differently for martial arts, compared to someone who works out for fun. Same goes for personal finances; there is no cookie cutter plan for everyone. General advice such as saving certain percentages or for retirement is pretty much useless.</p>
<p><strong>Yellow belt</strong>: This is where you need to organize your income and expenses. Even the most sophisticated financial plan will fail if you don’t know where the money goes. You need to track expenses and allocate a budget for your discretionary expenses. Your spending habits need to match your income. Think of it as cardiovascular ability. Even if you have all the skills as a martial artist, if you lack stamina and endurance, you will not win your match.</p>
<p><strong>Orange belt</strong>: There are different types of debt, and it is difficult to avoid some of them, including mortgage, specially if you live in one of the major cities with high real estate prices. This is why it is important to go step by step, just like you can’t skip a belt in martial arts. If you take control of your cash flow and expenses as a yellow belt, you will not occur consumer debt in the first place. Even mortgage, although obtained as an asset, can be harmful in some cases.</p>
<p><strong>Blue belt</strong>: An important but often neglected area in financial planning is risk management. I compare it with defense in martial arts. Most people like to learn flashy techniques and spectacular kicks but not many focus on defense. You need a back-up plan if you get ill, become disabled or if your spouse passes away prematurely Get familiar with different types of life, disability and critical illness insurance.</p>
<p><strong>Green belt</strong>: This is probably the most exciting part of a financial plan. Who does not like to know how to grow their investment! This is what people signed up for when they enrolled in the martial arts class. This is where people talk about all the flashy kicks and jumping and flying techniques. Investment is a very broad term and not only are some investments unsuitable but are also harmful for some people. Your time horizon and risk tolerance determine the type of investment suitable for you. Don’t fall into traps. If it is too good to be true, it probably is.</p>
<p><strong>Brown belt</strong>: You have heard about how romantic and peaceful retirement is in Canada right? After all you want to retire like a grandmaster! Nobody can work forever, and we are all living longer. I hate to burst your bubble but if you don’t plan ahead, the supposed golden years will be spent in hardship. People overstate what they will receive as government pensions and, unfortunately, sometimes they figure it out when it is too late. It is essential to know what you will get from different sources as pension and have a plan to fill the gap.</p>
<p><strong>Black belt</strong>: Black belt is the white belt who never quit. It is now time to create a financial plan to put all you have learned together. You need a simple and practical plan with details of how much to save for retirement, when you will be debt free and what coverage you need for a back-up plan. I can’t emphasize enough that there is no cookie cutter plan. Your current financial situation, your life, priorities and personality are different from others. Your financial plan should be different too.</p>
<p>Keep in mind that sticking to a budget and financial plan is like sticking to a diet and exercise regimen. Everybody keeps motivated and maintains discipline in a different way. Consistency is the key to success; however, there could be setbacks and that is okay. Just don’t let the old negative patterns become the new norm again.</p>
<p>Go to work warriors, and never hesitate to ask for help!</p>
<p><em>For more about author <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/people/master-the-art-of-finance-with-alireza-fadaie" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Alireza Fadai, click here</a>. </em></p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/money-and-business/earn-your-black-belt-in-money-management">Earn your black belt in money management</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Taking fitness outside: 9 tips for becoming more active through the Canadian winter</title>
		<link>https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/wellness/taking-fitness-outside-9-tips-for-becoming-more-active-through-the-canadian-winter</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Canadian Immigrant]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 17 Jan 2023 22:13:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Living]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[canada winter activities]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[health and wellness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[winter activities]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://canadianimmigrant.ca/?p=60420</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>If you made a New Year’s resolution about physical activity, you are not alone. Many Canadians make resolutions, and most focus on moving more.</p>
The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/wellness/taking-fitness-outside-9-tips-for-becoming-more-active-through-the-canadian-winter">Taking fitness outside: 9 tips for becoming more active through the Canadian winter</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you made a New Year’s resolution about physical activity, you are not alone. Many Canadians make resolutions, and most focus on moving more. Despite best intentions, it can be difficult for people to maintain New Year’s goals; in fact, nearly half fail to achieve their resolution. There are many reasons for this, and one is that physical activity goals are hard to achieve, regardless of the time of year.</p>
<p>As researchers in the fields of behavioural medicine, physical activity and outdoor recreation, we have some ideas about how to make those resolutions stick.</p>
<p>Try to change up your physical activity and make it fun and enjoyable. Research shows that adherence to physical activity is improved when you mix things up and choose an activity that fills your cup.</p>
<p>One way to increase variety and enjoyment might be choosing outdoor physical activities. And it seems Canadians (with and without chronic conditions) desire outdoor activity, especially since the <a href="https://ccpr.parkpeople.ca/2021/overview/lessons">COVID-19 pandemic</a>.</p>
<h2>Outdoor benefits</h2>
<p>Taking your physical activity outside comes with some added benefits. We have found that a single trail walk can reduce participants’ reported levels of anxiety, and that after eight weeks of trail walking two times per week, stress is decreased. We also know that people who engage in physical activity outdoors stick to it better and longer, and may work harder than when exercising indoors.</p>
<p>This may be explained in part by the shift in focus outwards, to the environment, rather than on inner bodily sensations, making the exercise feel easier.</p>
<p>In a recent study currently under peer review, we (Thomson and Lesser) found that individuals with both low and high functional capacity (a measure of aerobic fitness) were able to complete hikes of varied difficulty. Those who were less fit simply slowed down to be able to complete the same hike at the same level of effort as their fit counterparts.</p>
<p>This suggests that outdoor physical activity, such as hiking, is feasible from a fitness perspective and is perceived as easier.</p>
<h2>The great outdoors in winter</h2>
<p>If you live in a four-season climate, you may be wondering how to take physical activity outside during a Canadian winter.</p>
<p>First and foremost, if you are just getting started, determine your readiness to move more. You can try an online assessment like the <a href="https://csep.ca/wp-content/uploads/2021/05/GETACTIVEQUESTIONNAIRE_ENG.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Get Active Questionnaire</a> to see if you need to talk to your doctor first.</p>
<p>Next, try some of these tips and considerations:</p>
<h2>1. Find a support system</h2>
<p>Research has shown that <a href="https://doi.org/10.1080/1750984X.2016.1183222" target="_blank" rel="noopener">social support can promote sustained physical activity behaviour</a>, and may take on even greater importance when activity moves outdoors.</p>
<h2>2. Dress in layers</h2>
<p>Overdressing is always better than underdressing, and <a href="https://adventure.howstuffworks.com/outdoor-activities/hiking/wool-when-wet.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">wool is your best bet</a> to reduce moisture and keep in heat. Make sure you are covered from head to toe — that means wearing a scarf to help warm the incoming air when the temperatures plummet.</p>
<h2>3. Have a plan B</h2>
<p>Unfortunately, depending on where you live, it might be too cold or icy to be outdoors. In this case, take a break and move it inside for a bit. That way, you can continue your active lifestyle and build up some excitement about getting back outside when the weather improves.</p>
<h2>4. Safety First</h2>
<figure class="align-center zoomable">
<div style="width: 610px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><a href="https://images.theconversation.com/files/503767/original/file-20230110-14-99arna.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=1000&amp;fit=clip"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/503767/original/file-20230110-14-99arna.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" sizes="(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px" srcset="https://images.theconversation.com/files/503767/original/file-20230110-14-99arna.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503767/original/file-20230110-14-99arna.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503767/original/file-20230110-14-99arna.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=400&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503767/original/file-20230110-14-99arna.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503767/original/file-20230110-14-99arna.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503767/original/file-20230110-14-99arna.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=503&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 2262w" alt="Image of the bottoms of a pair of shoes with orange soles, displaying two types of external ice cleats" width="600" height="400" /></a><p class="wp-caption-text">Two kinds of exterior cleats attached to running shoes. (AP Photo/Dan Joling)</p></div><figcaption></figcaption>When it gets slippery outside, ensure that you have proper footwear. We love snow cleats that can be put over your shoes to enhance your grip. You can also consider using walking poles to improve your balance and reduce the risk of falls.</figure>
<h2>5. Hydrate</h2>
<p>Even though you might not feel as warm and sweaty as you would in warmer months, you are still losing water and you need to stay hydrated.</p>
<h2>6. Make it part of your day</h2>
<p>Find different ways to incorporate the outdoors into your daily activities! Did you know that <a href="https://theconversation.com/snow-shovelling-healthy-exercise-or-deadly-activity-129183">shovelling snow</a> counts as intense physical activity? Be the neighbourly snow shoveller — just ensure that you are warmed up and don’t go too hard. If you love biking to work, try fat tires on your bike. They increase your traction on snow and ice.</p>
<p>If these sound a bit too strenuous, you can always park farther away at work, school or the grocery store to add some steps to your day, or consider taking a brief walk outside on your lunch break.</p>
<h2>7. Light it up</h2>
<p>With the days ending so early, it can be a challenge to fit in physical activity before the sun sets. A head lamp will allow you to be out early or past dark. Just ensure that you are in a safe location (and maybe bring someone from your support system along).</p>
<h2>8. Try something new</h2>
<figure class="align-center ">
<div style="width: 610px" class="wp-caption alignnone"><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" src="https://images.theconversation.com/files/503762/original/file-20230110-12-k3nhwk.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;fit=clip" sizes="(min-width: 1466px) 754px, (max-width: 599px) 100vw, (min-width: 600px) 600px, 237px" srcset="https://images.theconversation.com/files/503762/original/file-20230110-12-k3nhwk.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=416&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 600w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503762/original/file-20230110-12-k3nhwk.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=416&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1200w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503762/original/file-20230110-12-k3nhwk.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=600&amp;h=416&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 1800w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503762/original/file-20230110-12-k3nhwk.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=45&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=523&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=1 754w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503762/original/file-20230110-12-k3nhwk.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=30&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=523&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=2 1508w, https://images.theconversation.com/files/503762/original/file-20230110-12-k3nhwk.jpg?ixlib=rb-1.1.0&amp;q=15&amp;auto=format&amp;w=754&amp;h=523&amp;fit=crop&amp;dpr=3 2262w" alt="A blue sign picturing a snowshoer on a tree trunk with snow in the background" width="600" height="416" /><p class="wp-caption-text">If you’re interested in trying snowshoeing, winter hiking or cross-country skiing, consider borrowing equipment from a friend, renting from your local recreation facility or purchasing used equipment from a sports trader. THE CANADIAN PRESS/Graham Hughes</p></div><figcaption></figcaption></figure>
<p>This is a perfect time to break out of your routine. Ever tried snowshoeing, winter hiking or cross-country skiing? Now could be the time. Don’t have equipment? Consider borrowing from a friend, renting from your local recreation facility or purchasing used equipment from a sports trader.</p>
<h2>9. Enjoy the tranquillity</h2>
<p>Outdoor experiences in winter tend to be quieter and include more expansive terrain with different sounds, wildlife and colour experiences. Try taking advantage of it and notice how you feel.</p>
<p>We hope you will try taking it outside to reap the benefits of our beautiful Canadian winters. Who knows, maybe you will even increase the likelihood of sticking to those hard-to-meet New Year’s resolutions in the process!<!-- Below is The Conversation's page counter tag. Please DO NOT REMOVE. --><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" style="border: none !important; box-shadow: none !important; margin: 0 !important; max-height: 1px !important; max-width: 1px !important; min-height: 1px !important; min-width: 1px !important; opacity: 0 !important; outline: none !important; padding: 0 !important;" src="https://counter.theconversation.com/content/197190/count.gif?distributor=republish-lightbox-basic" alt="The Conversation" width="1" height="1" /><!-- End of code. If you don't see any code above, please get new code from the Advanced tab after you click the republish button. The page counter does not collect any personal data. More info: https://theconversation.com/republishing-guidelines --></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><em>Authors: <a href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/iris-lesser-1266009" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Iris Lesser</a>, Assistant professor in kinesiology, University of The Fraser Valley; <a href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/amanda-wurz-1182655" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Amanda Wurz</a>, Assistant Professor, School of Kinesiology, University of The Fraser Valley, and <a href="https://theconversation.com/profiles/cynthia-thomson-1404808" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Cynthia Thomson</a>, Assistant Professor in Kinesiology, University of The Fraser Valley.  </em><em>This article is republished from <a href="https://theconversation.com" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Conversation</a> under a Creative Commons license. Read the <a href="https://theconversation.com/taking-fitness-outside-9-tips-for-becoming-more-active-through-the-canadian-winter-197190" target="_blank" rel="noopener">original article</a>.</em></p>The post <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca/living/wellness/taking-fitness-outside-9-tips-for-becoming-more-active-through-the-canadian-winter">Taking fitness outside: 9 tips for becoming more active through the Canadian winter</a> first appeared on <a href="https://canadianimmigrant.ca">Canadian Immigrant</a>.]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
