<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	 xmlns:media="http://search.yahoo.com/mrss/" >

<channel>
	<title>Immigroup</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.immigroup.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.immigroup.com</link>
	<description>Document &#38; Immigration Support</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 30 Nov 2022 14:02:37 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	
	<item>
		<title>How to get a refugee travel document in Canada.</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-get-a-refugee-travel-document-in-canada/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-get-a-refugee-travel-document-in-canada/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Allard John Keeley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 01:14:20 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Do-it-yourself courses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Documents in Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Certificate of Identity]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Refugee Travel Document]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=9059</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This step-by-step guide will help you get your Canadian Refugee Travel Document or Certificate of Identity. We have taken the government instructions and simplified them for you! Application for Refugee Travel Document &#8211; Let&#8217;s start&#8230; First step: click the link below and download the application and follow our steps.  Adult Travel Document Application – PPTC...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h4 style="text-align: center;">This step-by-step guide will help you get your Canadian Refugee Travel Document or Certificate of Identity. We have taken the government instructions and simplified them for you!</h4>
<h2><strong>Application for Refugee Travel Document &#8211; Let&#8217;s start&#8230;</strong></h2>
<h4><span style="color: #ff0000;">First step:</span> click the link below and <strong>download the application and follow our steps. </strong></h4>
<p><a href="http://www.immigroup.com/pdf/pptc190.pdf">Adult Travel Document Application – PPTC 190 for 16 years and older</a></p>
<p><a href="http://www.immigroup.com/pdf/pptc192.pdf">Child Travel Document Application – PPTC 192 for 16 years and younger</a></p>
<h3><strong>Additional documents you may need:</strong></h3>
<p><a href="http://www.immigroup.com/pdf/pptc203-eng.pdf">Lost, stolen or damaged Travel Document – PPTC 203</a></p>
<p>Complete the Statutory Declaration in Lieu of Guarantor – Pick up in person at the nearest Passport Canada office</p>
<p><a href="http://www.immigroup.com/pdf/imm-562e.pdf">IMM 5562</a> – Must use if applying for the first Travel Document and your home country’s passport has been taken away by Immigration Canada or CBSA.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Did you know Immigroup offers a paid service for Travel Document Applications? We can do the following:</span></h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Fill out the application<br />Make sure everything is perfectly in order &amp; not rejected<br />Troubleshoot and answer all your questions</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">To learn more, <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/service/canadian-refugee-travel-document/" rel="nofollow">click here</a>.</h4>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Section 1:</span> Refugee travel document personal information &#8211; PPTC 190 or 192</h2>
<p>Most things in this section are straightforward, but two issues that people get stuck on are:</p>
<h3><strong>What is a UCI? </strong></h3>
<p>You can find this on your immigration documents (for example: Record of Landing paper). It will be 8 to 10 digits with one or two hyphens (-) in the middle of the number. UCI (Unique Client Identifier) is just your client identification number: the number that IRCC uses to identify you in your dealings with them.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-9063 size-full" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-1-explained-what-is-UCI-number-and-travel-date-pptc-190.jpg" alt="PPTC190, 1 Personal informaiotn" width="1148" height="529" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-1-explained-what-is-UCI-number-and-travel-date-pptc-190.jpg 1148w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-1-explained-what-is-UCI-number-and-travel-date-pptc-190-500x230.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-1-explained-what-is-UCI-number-and-travel-date-pptc-190-768x354.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1148px) 100vw, 1148px" /></p>
<h3><strong>Anticipated date of Travel: How can I get a Refugee Travel Document Urgently? </strong></h3>
<p>To get a travel document expedited, you will need to show proof of urgency. Not all urgencies are treated the same by IRCC. Here are the best to worst urgent reasons.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Note:</span> IRCC states in their instructions in section A, ‘We recommend that you not finalize your travel plans until you receive the requested travel document.’ This may seem like good advice, but if you are thinking of simply requesting urgency or typing up a letter, this will, in most cases, <strong>not work</strong>.  You must show proof to increase your odds of success. As you’ll see below, any letter has to come from somewhere like a hospital or an employer and be on their official letterhead, written (and preferably signed) by an official of that organization. You’ll often need additional proof as you’ll see in the following table.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>

<figure class="wp-block-table">
<table class="has-black-color has-text-color">
<tbody>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center"><strong>Rating Urgency</strong></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center"><strong>Reson of Urgency</strong></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center"><strong>Proof</strong></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center"><strong>Documets you need</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">High</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Death in the family</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Death certificate, a letter from Hospital or a funeral invitation.</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Remember you can’t return to your home country if you claimed refugee protection.<br /> <br />Your letter must be on official hospital letterhead.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">High</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Medical Treatment</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Letter from Hospital</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Letterhead<br />Date you are expected<br />Treatment<br />Cost of treatment, including invoice.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">High</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Loss of employment – for example, your new job requires you to travel. </td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Letter from employer</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Letterhead<br /> <br />The date you started the job.<br /> <br />Your job description (must include the fact that travel is required)<br /> <br />Employers’ contact info<br /> </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Medium to low</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Business</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Letter from an employer, or letter from a business client you are visiting, or an invoice or booking confirmation of a convention you are attending. </td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Letterhead<br /> <br />Date and Times you are expected.<br /> <br />Contact info of the employer or business client.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Medium to low</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Visiting elderly family members</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Letter from a doctor stating the poor health of the family members</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Letterhead<br /> <br />Medical conditions of the family member<br /> <br />Contact info of the doctor </td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Low</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Vacation</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Invoice or booking confirmation</td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">invoice or booking</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
</figure>



<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Note:</span> All documents not in English or French will need to be translated by a certified translator. </p>



<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Section 2:</span> Declaration of Guarantor &#8211; PPTC 190 or 192</h2>
<p>It’s hard enough to find a guarantor that will give you the time, so make sure you have everything ready for them. (See the example below).</p>
<p>Your guarantor will need to sign the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Fill out section 2 of the application form. Remember, they must have known you for at least 6 months.</li>
<li>On the back of <strong><em>one</em></strong> of your passport photos, they must write, <strong>I certify this to be a true likeness of </strong>(your name).”</li>
<li>They must <strong>sign</strong> their name on <strong>all</strong> supporting documents,<strong> front and back. </strong></li>
</ul>
<p>For more information about this subject, or If you can’t find a guarantor, read below:   </p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-9078" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-2-declaration-of-guarantor-pptc-19.jpg" alt="Refugee Travel Document - 2 Declaration of guarantor" width="1148" height="476" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-2-declaration-of-guarantor-pptc-19.jpg 1148w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-2-declaration-of-guarantor-pptc-19-500x207.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-2-declaration-of-guarantor-pptc-19-768x318.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1148px) 100vw, 1148px" /></p>
<h3><strong>What are the guarantor requirements </strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Lives in Canada,</li>
<li>is a citizen or permanent resident of Canada</li>
<li>and has known you for at least <strong>6 months </strong>or more.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>Must be one of the following occupations <strong>and</strong> still work or be licensed in their field.</p>
<p>pharmacist</p>
<p>nurse practitioner</p>
<p>dentist, medical doctor or chiropractor</p>
<p>principal of a primary or secondary school</p>
<p>senior administrator or teacher in a university</p>
<p>professional accountant</p>
<p>minister of religion authorized under provincial or territorial law to perform marriages</p>
<p>mayor</p>
<p>postmaster</p>
<p>optometrist</p>
<p>veterinarian</p>
<p>notary public</p>
<p>professional engineer (P. Eng. or Ing. in Quebec)</p>
<p>senior administrator in a community college (in Quebec, a CEGEP)</p>
<p>judge, magistrate, or police officer</p>
<p>lawyer or notary in Quebec</p>
<h3><strong>If you don’t have a guarantor, what to do? </strong></h3>
<p>This option does not require the person to have known you.</p>
<ul>
<li>Complete the Statutory Declaration in Lieu of Guarantor form. The form is not available online and must be:
<ul>
<li>In Canada: Pick up at the nearest Passport Service Location, or you can <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/services/canadian-passports/contact-passport-program.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">contact Passport Canada at this link</a> to request they send a copy to you.</li>
<li>In the US: Pick up at the nearest Canadian embassy or consulate, or you can contact Passport Canada at the same link.</li>
<li>Outside Canada and the US: contact your nearest Canadian embassy or consulate.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Must be filled out by:</li>
<li>Notary Public</li>
<li>Justice of the Peace</li>
<li>Commissioner for oaths</li>
<li>(Outside of Canada) Canadian or British diplomat. A local member of parliament or civil servant (government official) is also suggested. Check with the Canadian embassy or consulate if a local notary or lawyer is acceptable.</li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Important:</span> The person you used to fill out your Lieu of Guarantor CAN’T be your same reference.</p>
<p>IRCC’s web page states that you can’t use the same references on the Statutory Declaration in Lieu of Guarantor form that you included on your passport or travel document application. In other words, if you have already used a guarantor for your passport application, you’ll have to find another guarantor for your Statutory Declaration in Lieu of Guarantor form.</p>
<p>The government statement does not really make sense for your travel document, seeing that if you have a guarantor for your travel document you don’t need a Statutory Declaration. </p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Section 3:</span> Proof of Immigration Status in Canada &#8211; PPTC 190 or 192</h2>
<p>Here is an excellent example from the IRCC website. If you need help finding your immigration status document number, <a href="https://www.cic.gc.ca/english/helpcentre/answer.asp?qnum=1446" target="_blank" rel="noopener">click here</a>.</p>
<p>Here are the steps:</p>
<ol>
<li>Fill out the section below</li>
<li>Make copies of your immigration documents. Remember, your guarantor will need to sign the front and the back of the documents. You can send the original, and no signature is required, but this is not recommended.</li>
</ol>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-9081 size-full" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-3-proof-of-immigration-status-documents-pptc-190.jpg" alt="Section 3, immigration status in Canada section for the Canadian Refugee Travel Document application" width="1520" height="242" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-3-proof-of-immigration-status-documents-pptc-190.jpg 1520w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-3-proof-of-immigration-status-documents-pptc-190-500x80.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-3-proof-of-immigration-status-documents-pptc-190-768x122.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1520px) 100vw, 1520px" /></p>
<h3><strong>Required Identity documents </strong></h3>
<p><em>An official translator/translation company must professionally translate any documents that are not in English or French. Look for a stamp or seal with a membership number of a professional translation association in Canada or abroad. If the seal or stamp is not in English or French, it must also be translated.  </em></p>
<ul>
<li>A copy of an original document signed by your guarantor</li>
<li><strong>If you have:</strong> a valid passport or travel document issued in your name</li>
<li>2 Passport photos (Go to a professional passport photo location) *</li>
<li>On the back of one of the photos, your guarantor needs to write the following statement, “<strong>I certify this to be a true likeness of </strong>(your name).”</li>
<li>The photographer will need to indicate the company address and date on the back of the photos (this usually is done by the photographer&#8217;s business stamp).</li>
<li>Phot size will be 50 mm wide by 70 mm high (2 inches wide by 2¾ inches high).</li>
<li><em>Please note: A small number of photos do get refused</em>.</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Additional Documents you may need. </strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Change of name document</li>
<li>Replacing a lost, stolen, or damaged travel document &#8211; PPTC 203</li>
<li>Change of sex application – This is a provincial jurisdiction, and the relevant application for your province can be found online.</li>
</ul>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Note: </span>If you are filing a refugee claim and your home country’s passport is taken away from you at your port of entry by Immigration Canada or CBSA, the official will fill out form BSF 698 if the document seized is a Travel Document or Identity Document, or form IMM 5265 for other documents. The official is then required to provide you with a copy of the form they have filled out. Your passport will be scanned and digitally uploaded to the government’s Global Case Management System (GCMS).</p>
<ul>
<li>This is done when there are concerns about the legitimacy of your refugee claim.</li>
</ul>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Section 4:</span> Previous Canadian Travel Document &#8211; PPTC 190 or 192</h2>
<p>You will have to return your old travel document.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Note:</span> if you have a valid visa, you can request that your old travel document be returned. You will have to indicate this request in a letter.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-9083" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-4-previous-travel-dcument-or-passportpptc-190.jpg" alt="section 4 of PPTC 190 Previous Canadiain Travel Document" width="1515" height="320" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-4-previous-travel-dcument-or-passportpptc-190.jpg 1515w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-4-previous-travel-dcument-or-passportpptc-190-500x106.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-4-previous-travel-dcument-or-passportpptc-190-768x162.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1515px) 100vw, 1515px" /></p>
<h3><strong>FAQ – Section 4</strong></h3>
<h3><strong>I am renewing my Refugee Travel Document; will I get the old one back? </strong></h3>
<p>You need to make a formal request to have your Travel Document returned. For most people, this request is made because your old Travel Document or Certificate of Identity still has a valid visa in it.</p>
<h3><strong>When should I renew my Travel Document or Certificate of Identity?</strong></h3>
<p>We recommend applying 6 to 9 months before expiration, but you can apply 12 months before.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Tip:</span> If you still have a valid visa in your current travel document, you can request to have the old document returned.</p>
<h3><strong>I have an expired Travel document or Certificate of Identity; do I still need to return it? </strong></h3>
<p>All documents must be returned unless they have expired over 5 years.</p>
<h3><strong>I have lost my old, expired travel document; what do I do?<br /></strong></h3>
<p>You must fill out a lost passport application <a href="https://www.canada.ca/content/dam/ircc/migration/ircc/english/passport/forms/pdf/pptc203-eng.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">PPTC 203</a></p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Section 5:</span> Citizenship and Travel Documentation &#8211; PPTC 190 or 192</h2>
<h3><strong>Do you have valid travel documents or passports?</strong></h3>
<p>The reason they are asking you this is because Refugee Travel Documents are for people that can’t use their home country’s passport. If you are still in possession of a valid passport, you will need to give it up and mail it in with this application.</p>
<h3><strong>Have you visited another country since you entered Canada?</strong></h3>
<p>If you have travelled, list all dates. if you need more room to put all dates, <a href="http://www.immigroup.com/doc/Travel%20Document%20or%20Certificate%20of%20Identity%20Travel%20Dates.docx" target="_blank" rel="noopener"><span style="color: #000000;">click to download the document here and attach this to your application.</span></a></p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-9084" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-5-citienship-and-other-travel-documentation-pptc-190.jpg" alt="Section 5 Citizenship and Travel Documentation" width="1330" height="835" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-5-citienship-and-other-travel-documentation-pptc-190.jpg 1330w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-5-citienship-and-other-travel-documentation-pptc-190-500x314.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-5-citienship-and-other-travel-documentation-pptc-190-768x482.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1330px) 100vw, 1330px" /></p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Section 6:</span> Documents to Support Identity &#8211; PPTC 190 or 192</h2>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-9085" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-6-documents-support-identity-pptc-190.jpg" alt="Section 6 of the Application PPTC 190 Documents to Support Identity" width="1517" height="339" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-6-documents-support-identity-pptc-190.jpg 1517w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-6-documents-support-identity-pptc-190-500x112.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-6-documents-support-identity-pptc-190-768x172.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1517px) 100vw, 1517px" /></p>
<h3>You need to have an ID that:</h3>
<p>1) has a photo,</p>
<p>2) has your signature, and</p>
<p>3) is valid (Date hasn’t expired).</p>
<ul>
<li>It can be a Provincial or Federal ID.</li>
<li>It’s recommended that the ID is issued in Canada, but you can use IDs from other countries (for example, a driver’s license from your home country)</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Here are the steps: </strong></h3>
<ol>
<li>You will need one ID. This ID must have a <strong>photo</strong> of you, and your <strong>signature</strong> and <strong>not be expired</strong>. The best document to use is a <strong>provincial Driver&#8217;s License</strong> (for alternative solutions, read below).</li>
<li>Make a colour copy of this document <strong>front</strong> and <strong>back</strong>.</li>
<li>Your guarantor will have to sign and date the front and back of each copy of your ID. Note: Your guarantor will have to verify the original ID with the copies, so bring everything with you.</li>
</ol>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Note:</span> You can send original documents, but we don’t recommend this option.</p>
<h3><strong>What if you don’t have an ID with a photo? </strong></h3>
<p>If you don’t have any ID that meets the above requirements, you can apply for a Provincial ID card. Most provinces in Canada have one. See our list below.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>

</p>
<figure class="wp-block-table">
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><strong>Province</strong></td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><strong>Name of the Card &amp; URL</strong></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center"><strong>Cost*</strong></td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left">Alberta</td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><a href="https://www.alberta.ca/get-id-card.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">ID Card</a></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">$49</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left">British Columbia</td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><a href="https://www2.gov.bc.ca/gov/content/governments/government-id/bc-services-card/your-card/get-a-card" target="_blank" rel="noopener">B.C. identification Card (BCID)</a></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">$35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left">Manitoba</td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><a href="https://www.mpi.mb.ca/Pages/apply-for-id-card.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Manitoba Identification Card</a></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">$20</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left">New Brunswick</td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><a href="https://www2.gnb.ca/content/gnb/en/services/services_renderer.12535.Photo_ID_Card.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Photo ID Card</a></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">$48</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left">Newfoundland &amp; Labrador</td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><a href="https://www.gov.nl.ca/motorregistration/new-drivers/photo-identification-card/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Photo ID Card</a></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">$25</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left">Nova Scotia</td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><a href="https://novascotia.ca/sns/paal/rmv/paal275.asp" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Nova Scotia Photo ID card</a></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">$17.70</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left">Ontario</td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><a href="https://www.ontario.ca/page/ontario-photo-card" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Ontario Photo Card</a></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">$35</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left">Prince Edward Island</td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><a href="https://www.princeedwardisland.ca/en/information/transportation-and-infrastructure/photographic-identification-card-voluntary-id" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Voluntary ID</a></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">$50</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left">Saskatchewan</td>
<td class="has-text-align-left" data-align="left"><a href="https://www.sgi.sk.ca/photo-id" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Photo ID Card</a></td>
<td class="has-text-align-center" data-align="center">Free</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p>*Some provinces may waive the fee for refugees.</p>
</figure>
<p>Last resort, you can send in a combination of a few documents, but you will need to check with the IRCC call center to ensure these documents will be excepted. </p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Section 7:</span> Additional Personal Information &#8211; PPTC 190 or 192</h2>
<p>Here you just need to give your address and work history for the last two years.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-9090" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-7-additional-personal-info-pptc-19.jpg" alt="Section 7 pf PPTC 190 application. Additional Personal Information" width="1327" height="694" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-7-additional-personal-info-pptc-19.jpg 1327w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-7-additional-personal-info-pptc-19-500x261.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-7-additional-personal-info-pptc-19-768x402.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1327px) 100vw, 1327px" /></p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Section 8:</span> Refernces &#8211; PPTC 190 or 192</h2>
<p>You will now need to find two people who have known you for at least 6 months, or more.  </p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Tip:</span> Find two people that will <strong>always pick up their phones during the daytime</strong>. The Passport Program call center will call a few times but if your references don’t answer the phone then at some point, they will simply give up and your application can be put on hold or returned to you.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Note:</span> Ask your references to let you know when the call came in, because at this stage of the application process, this usually means you are close to getting your Travel Document.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter size-full wp-image-9091" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-8-referencs-pptc-190.jpg" alt="Section 8 of PPCT 190 application. References" width="1323" height="496" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-8-referencs-pptc-190.jpg 1323w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-8-referencs-pptc-190-500x187.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/section-8-referencs-pptc-190-768x288.jpg 768w" sizes="(max-width: 1323px) 100vw, 1323px" /></p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Section 9:</span> Emergency Contac &#8211; PPTC 190 or 192</h2>
<p>This is in case you have an emergency while traveling. Always a good idea to have someone close to you listed here. If you don’t have anyone in Canada, you can put family or friends from outside of Canada.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Last Step:</span> Review and Send to the government </h2>
<ul>
<li style="text-align: left;">Two Passport Photos</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">Colour copy of proof of immigration status in Canada – signed and dated by guarantor</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">Copies of ID, front and back – signed and dated by guarantor</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">Original Travel Document – if applicable</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">Proof of urgency – If applicable</li>
<li style="text-align: left;">Canada Post Xpresspost package (keep tracking info)</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Centralized Network – Certificate of Identity Section</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Place du Centre,</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Commercial Level 2</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">200 Promenade du Portage</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Gatineau QC</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">J8X 4B7</h4>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Tip:</span> if you are applying for <strong>urgent</strong> reason, then on the outside of the envelope write in big letters “<strong>URGENT</strong>”.</p>
<h3><strong>How to Track and communicate about your application?</strong></h3>
<p>This question usually gives most people the most <strong>frustration</strong>. Getting through, getting a non-templated answer from the government is not easy. What seems to work is persistence, so keep reaching out through the different channels we have listed below. </p>
<p><strong>You have 2 options in tracking or contacting: <br /><br /></strong></p>
<ol>
<li>Webfrom <a href="https://secure.cic.gc.ca/enquiries-renseignements/canada-case-cas-eng.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">click here</a> (Recommended)</li>
<li>Calling IRCC&#8217;s call center at 1-888-242-2100 (difficult getting through) </li>
</ol>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Note:</span> Calling Passport Canada 1-800-567-6868, will not work. </p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Did you know Immigroup offers a paid service for Travel Document Applications? We can do the following:</span></h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Fill out the application<br />Make sure everything is perfectly in order &amp; not rejected<br />Troubleshoot and answer all your questions</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">To learn more, <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/service/canadian-refugee-travel-document/" rel="nofollow">click here</a>.</h4>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">FAQ</h2>
<h3><strong>What is a Refugee Travel Document?</strong></h3>
<p>This document is issued to Protected Persons in Canada (Refugees) or persons in need of protection.</p>
<h3><br /><strong>What is a Certificate of Identity?</strong></h3>
<p>This document is issued to Permanent Residents of Canada that meet one of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>Not Protected Persons</li>
<li>Are Stateless</li>
<li>Can’t get a passport or travel document for their home country</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>What is the definition</strong> of “Persons in need of protection”: According to the IRPA a protected person is someone who is given the protections afforded a convention refugee but not may not fit the Geneva Convention’s legal definition of a convention refugee.</p>
<p><strong><em>Protected person</em></strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><em>(2)</em></strong><em> A protected person is a person on whom refugee protection is conferred under </em><em>subsection (1), and whose claim or application has not subsequently been deemed to be rejected </em><em>under subsection 108(3), 109(3) or 114(4).</em></p>
<h3><strong>Will I get a Travel Document or Certificate of Identity? </strong> </h3>
<p>If you are a refugee and are now a protected person in Canada, you will get a Refugee Travel Document. If you are stateless or not a protected person, you will get a Certificate of Identity.</p>
<h3><strong>Which Document allows me to travel more? </strong></h3>
<p>A travel document is better because more countries give the holder visa-free travel.</p>
<h3><strong>What are the limitations of these documents? </strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>It can’t be used to travel back to your country of citizenship (The country you claimed you needed protection from).</li>
<li>Visa may be required. Once you get your document, you will need to contact each country you wish to travel to.</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>People that are eligible for Travel Documents or a Certificate of Identity</strong></h3>
<p>What are Convention Refugees:</p>
<p>What are Protected Persons: </p>
<p>What are Stateless Persons: </p>
<p>What are Permanent Residents of Canada in Special Circumstances:</p>
<h3><strong>Who issues Canadian Travel Documents?  </strong></h3>
<p>All documents are created in Gatineau, Quebec, by Passport Canada. The location where they make the passport is 210 Rue Champlain, Gatineau, QC J8X 3R5. It is officially called the Gatineau-Hull Service Canada Centre and Passport Services. IRCC is responsible for the processing, and Passport Canada creates the document.</p>
<h3><strong>How long is a Travel Document or Certificate of Identity valid? </strong></h3>
<p>Travel Document or Certificate of Identity: Typically, for 5 years but they can sometimes be valid for only 1 year.</p>
<p>Certificate of Identity issued in Canada: Typically, it’s issued for 1 year or more. </p>
[ays_poll id=7]
<h3><strong>Can I get a Travel Document outside of Canada? </strong></h3>
<p>Travel Documents are issued inside of Canada. In case of an emergency outside of Canada, you will need to contact a Canadian Diplomatic Mission (Embassy or Consulate) outside of Canada. Click here for the <a href="https://travel.gc.ca/assistance/embassies-consulates" target="_blank" rel="noopener">entire directory</a>.</p>
<h3><strong>What age do I have to be to apply for a Travel Document?</strong></h3>
<p><strong>You can be of any age</strong>. There are applications for <strong>adults</strong> (16 years and older) and <strong>children</strong> (15 years or younger).</p>
<h3><strong>Travel Document or Certificate of Identity for children. </strong></h3>
<p>Any parent can apply. You will need one of the following documents to prove you are the parent:</p>
<ul>
<li>The child’s Long Form Birth Certificate (this certificate will have the child’s information and parents on it. This is not the short form birth certificate).</li>
<li>The child’s Adoption Order showing the name of both the child and the adoptive parent.</li>
<li>The parent’s passport as long as the child is listed on the parent’s passport.</li>
</ul>
<p>If Separated or Divorced:</p>
<ul>
<li>Divorce papers showing custody of the child or other legal document detailing any custody arrangements for the child.</li>
</ul>
<p>Child’s legal guardian:</p>
<ul>
<li>Proof of legal guardianship</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3><strong>What is the immigration status document number? </strong></h3>
<p>Most immigration documents will have a document number usually located in the upper right-hand corner of the document. It helps the issuing authority keep track of the documents they issue.</p>
<h3><strong>Where do I find the Date of issue and date of expiry? </strong></h3>
<p>It depends on the document.</p>
<ul>
<li>On your Refugee Travel Document – if it’s in the form of a card it will be on the front near your photo. If it’s in the form of a passport (the Blue Passport) you will find that information on the inside near the beginning.</li>
<li>On your Permanent Resident card, they don’t have a Date of Issue, but they do have a Date of Expiry located on front of the card in the lower middle section.</li>
<li>On your Temporary Resident Permit, your date of issue and expiry date are located below your name on the upper right-hand side.</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>What countries can I travel to with my Refugee Travel Document or Certificate of Identity? </strong></h3>
<p>Most countries will require a vis. Refugee Travel Documents is <strong>not</strong> a Canadian passport and will come with limitations.</p>
<p>In most cases, after you have gotten your Travel Document will need to apply for a visa to the country you are planning to travel to.</p>
<p>Here are the steps to take:</p>
<p><em>*see below for visa-free countries </em></p>
<p>Contact the Embassy of the countries you plan to travel to. <a href="https://travel.gc.ca/assistance/embassies-consulates" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Here is the complete list of all Diplomatic Missions in Canada</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>You must ask if a Canadian Travel Document holder is <strong>visa-free</strong> or <strong>requires a visa</strong>.</li>
<li>If visa-free, what are the rules or limitations (for example, 90 days visa-free)</li>
<li>If the visa is required:</li>
<li>What application needs to be filled out – and where to find it?</li>
<li>Processing timelines and costs</li>
<li>Documents they will need from you (for example, banking information, Hotel addresses or booking confirmation).</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Visa-free countries for a Canadian Refugee Travel Document or Certificate of Identity. </strong></h3>
<p>The Geneva Convention of 1951 established the status of refugees and the protections that should be given to them. Some, but not most, of the countries that signed the convention allow visa-free travel for refugees with a travel document.</p>
<ul>
<li>Armenia</li>
<li>Belgium</li>
<li>Cyprus</li>
<li>Czech Republic</li>
<li>Denmark</li>
<li>Finland</li>
<li>France</li>
<li>Germany</li>
<li>Hungary</li>
<li>Iceland</li>
<li>Ireland</li>
<li>Italy</li>
<li>Liechtenstein</li>
<li>Luxembourg</li>
<li>Malta</li>
<li>Montenegro</li>
<li>Netherlands</li>
<li>Norway</li>
<li>Poland</li>
<li>Portugal</li>
<li>Romania</li>
<li>Slovakia</li>
<li>South Africa</li>
<li>South Korea</li>
<li>Spain</li>
<li>Sweden</li>
<li>Switzerland</li>
<li>United Kingdom</li>
<li>Vatican City</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Can I use the eTA program with my Travel Document? </strong></h3>
<p>It depends.</p>
<ul>
<li>If you’re travelling <strong>to</strong> Canada on a<em> refugee travel document issued abroad</em>, you cannot apply for an eTA. Instead, you will need a Visitor Visa.</li>
<li>If you have a <em>Canadian refugee travel document</em>, you are exempt from both visa and eTA travel requirements when travelling to Canada. However, other countries may still require a visa.</li>
<li>If you are a refugee with lawful permanent resident status in the US, but without a passport, you can still travel to Canada visa-free if you have your I-571 (US Refugee Travel Document) and proof of your lawful permanent resident status. </li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Do Canadian Refugee travel document holders need a visa if travelling to the United States? </strong></h3>
<p>Yes, you must apply for a visa to visit the US.</p>
<h3><strong>I am eligible to apply for Canadian citizenship. Should I still apply for a Travel Document? </strong></h3>
<p>You should apply for both. Your Canadian citizenship will take time, but once you get it, you can apply for a Canadian Passport and return your Travel Document. </p>
<h3><strong>What is the fee for a Canadian Travel Document?<br /></strong></h3>
<p>The fee for a Canadian Travel Document is CDN$120. If you are replacing a lost or stolen document, an additional $45 will apply. Most of the above fees are non-refundable ($25 is refundable).</p>
<h3><strong>What is the fee for a Certificate of Identity?</strong></h3>
<p>The fee for a Certificate of Identity is CDN$260. If you are replacing a lost or stolen document, an additional $45 will apply. Most of the above fees are non-refundable ($25 is refundable).</p>
<h3><strong>How do you pay the government fee? </strong></h3>
<ul>
<li>Use a major credit card – section D of the application</li>
<li>Certified cheque, money order (Canada Post or Bank). Payments for Travel Documents or Certificate of Intensity must be made to <strong>Receiver General for Canada</strong>.</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>What is the mailing address? </strong></h3>
<p><br /><strong>Courier with tracking:</strong> Recommended (Keep tracking information – Use Canada Post or any major courier company)</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Centralized Network – Certificate of Identity Section</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Place du Centre,</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Commercial Level 2</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">200 Promenade du Portage</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">Gatineau QC </p>
<p style="text-align: center;">J8X 4B7  </p>
<p style="text-align: center;"> </p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Regular Mailing: </strong></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"> </p>
<p style="text-align: center;">OSC PPT-COI</p>
<p style="text-align: center;">PO BOX 9783 STN T CSC <br />OTTAWA ON <br />K1G 5G8</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"> </p>
<h3><strong>How to Contact Passport Program for additional questions? </strong></h3>
<ol>
<li>Walk into a Passport Canada Service Center (Go to Google maps, type ‘Passport Canada near me’ or <a href="https://ircc.canada.ca/english/passport/map/map.asp#table1caption" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Click here</a>).</li>
<li>To use the webform <a href="https://secure.cic.gc.ca/enquiries-renseignements/canada-case-cas-eng.aspx" target="_blank" rel="noopener">click here</a></li>
<li>You will need to contact IRCC for tracking and general information at 1-888-242-2100</li>
</ol>
<p>Calling Passport Canada will not work: Toll-free call 1-800-567-6868 – from 8:00 a.m. to 4:00 p.m., Monday to Friday, Easter Standard Time.</p>
<p>If you do call Passport Canada, this will be the message, “Certificate of Identity and Refugee Travel Documents should now be directed to IRCC Client Support Center.”</p>
<!--[if lt IE 9]><script>document.createElement('audio');</script><![endif]-->
<audio class="wp-audio-shortcode" id="audio-9059-1" preload="none" style="width: 100%;" controls="controls"><source type="audio/mpeg" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/Passport-Canada-message-for-Travel-Document-Questions.mp3?_=1" /><a href="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/Passport-Canada-message-for-Travel-Document-Questions.mp3">https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/Passport-Canada-message-for-Travel-Document-Questions.mp3</a></audio>
<h3><strong>I sent my application, but I changed my address; what should I do?</strong></h3>
<p>Contact the IRCC call center. See the section, ‘How to track and communicate about your application?’ on this web page located just above the FAQ section.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><span style="color: #ff0000;">Did you know Immigroup offers a paid service for Travel Document Applications? We can do the following:</span></h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">Fill out the application<br />Make sure everything is perfectly in order &amp; not rejected<br />Troubleshoot and answer all your questions</h4>
<h4 style="text-align: center;">To learn more, <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/service/canadian-refugee-travel-document/" rel="nofollow">click here</a>.</h4>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full" id="wpforms-3069"><form id="wpforms-form-3069" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3069" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="e3c6881b53bf701fc131d3fe933d94ab"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3069-field_0-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="0"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_0">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_0" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][0]" placeholder="Name" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_1">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3069-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" placeholder="Email" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_4-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-number" data-field-id="4"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3069-field_4">Phone number</label><input type="number" pattern="\d*" id="wpforms-3069-field_4" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][4]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_2-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="2"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_2">Questions <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><textarea id="wpforms-3069-field_2" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][2]" placeholder="Questions" required></textarea></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-captcha" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_3">Captcha <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label>			<div class="wpforms-captcha-math">
				<span class="wpforms-captcha-equation">
											<span class="n1"></span>
						<span class="cal"></span>
						<span class="n2"></span>
											<span class="e">=</span>
				</span>
				<input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_3" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required a" data-rule-wpf-captcha="math" name="wpforms[fields][3][a]" required>				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][cal]" class="cal">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n2]" class="n2">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n1]" class="n1">
			</div>
			</div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3069"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="15"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3069" class="wpforms-submit button button-round button-bg-red" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container -->
<p></p>]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-get-a-refugee-travel-document-in-canada/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		<enclosure url="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/Passport-Canada-message-for-Travel-Document-Questions.mp3" length="3097121" type="audio/mpeg" />

			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Truck Driver with Criminal Record</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Allard John Keeley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 17:27:42 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=8975</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[If you have any sort of a criminal record, you&#8217;re going to have to take some steps to help ensure you can work as a truck driver, including being able to cross the border on a job. They generally involve going back to the legal system to clean up your record. How effective these measures...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>If you have any sort of a criminal record, you&#8217;re going to have to take some steps to help ensure you can work as a truck driver, including being able to cross the border on a job. They generally involve going back to the legal system to clean up your record. How effective these measures will be depends on the nature of your criminal record, but if you&#8217;re serious about driving a truck, you&#8217;ll need to try these steps in order to give yourself a reasonable chance to work as a truck operator. Read through our answers to the questions below to get an idea of what&#8217;s involved in cleaning up your criminal record.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>I have a criminal record; can I still get a job as a Truck Driver?</h2>
<p>Yes, it is possible, but it’s highly recommended you do two things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Get a <em>Record of Suspension</em> (essentially a pardon) which takes time and involves the Canadian Parole Board and can take up to 10 years from the time your offence was committed.</li>
<li>Get an <em>Entry Waiver</em> in order to be able to cross the border and drive your truck in the USA.</li>
<li>As well, these will help avoid failing a background check that some driving schools and trucking companies will demand.</li>
</ul>
<p>However, you need to understand that some transportation companies will still not hire you because of the higher insurance rates a serious offence like a DUI will bring. Your Driver Abstract is basically a record of your driving history, and any offence will show up there. Even a Record of Suspension only actually seals and sets aside your DUI but does not erase it. That means if you’re ever convicted of another DUI, you will be charged as a repeat offender, even if you have a Record of Suspension.</p>
<h2>Truck driver with DUI</h2>
<p>In December of 2018, driving under the influence (DUI) in Canada became a serious crime carrying a maximum of 10 years prison time. This complicated matters for temporary visitors and permanent residents in Canada and made DUI a more incriminating offense for someone looking to work as a truck driver. That means anyone with a DUI should think seriously about getting both a Record of Suspension and an Entry Waiver if you’re truly interested in driving a truck for a living.</p>
<h2>Less serious charges</h2>
<p>Yes, you can work as a truck driver if you have a couple of speeding tickets. However, if you want to apply for a FAST Card, you should think about getting a Record of Suspension in Canada, or a Pardon in the US, as any criminal record could make you ineligible. See our FAQ below on FAST Cards.</p>
<h2>More serious charges</h2>
<p>Depending on how serious the charge is, you may have a hard time obtaining work driving a truck. You would likely have to hire a good defense lawyer to get you some sort of a pardon or record of suspension and even then, you wouldn’t be guaranteed a successful outcome.</p>
<h2>Can I get into the US if I have a DUI as a truck driver?</h2>
<p>Only if you get what is called an Entry Waiver, and even then, you may encounter problems when trying to cross the border. DUI is now a serious matter and will make your voyage towards becoming a truck driver much more difficult.</p>
<h2>Can I get into Canada if I have a DUI as a truck driver?</h2>
<p>Yes you can but you&#8217;ll need to do one of 2 things:</p>
<ul>
<li>Apply for a Temporary Residence Permit from Canadian immigration authorities (IRCC) which involves providing proof you have to cross the border for work purposes. The proof can be a letter from your employer or a delivery contract, for example. This is a short-term solution that has to done every time you want to enter Canada for a job.</li>
<li>Apply for Criminal Rehabilitation which usually means your sentence and probation must have finished at least 5 years ago. This takes around a year to do, but is a permanent solution.</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>I&#8217;m a foreigner with a criminal record &#8211; will I get a job as a trucker?</h2>
<p>The first question is whether you&#8217;ll be admissible to Canada as an immigrant, and that will depend on the specifics of your criminal record. If your crime committed overseas qualifies as a federal crime in Canada, it will be tougher for you to get into Canada, never mind get work. You have 2 options as mentioned directly above: apply for a Temporary Residence Permit, or apply for Criminal Rehabilitation. Because you want to work as a trucker in Canada, you need permanent resident status, so applying for Criminal Rehabilitation would be the better choice.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>Can I get a FAST Card with a criminal record?</h2>
<p>A criminal record of almost any kind is generally grounds for ineligibility when it comes to the FAST Card program. However, if you can get a Record of Suspension in Canada, or a Pardon in the US, you can then apply for a FAST Card. Keep in mind, however, that the odds of being rejected will still be fairly high. The burden of proof is on you to convince both the CBSA in Canada and USCBP that you have completely reformed and are no longer a risk.</p>
<p>Just to make this clear, here is the <a href="https://www.cbp.gov/travel/trusted-traveler-programs/fast/eligibility" target="_blank" rel="noopener">USCBP&#8217;s official page</a> on FAST Card eligibility:</p>
<p><em>You may not be eligible for participation in the FAST program if you:</em></p>
<ul>
<li><em>Provide false or incomplete information on the application;</em></li>
<li><em>Have been convicted of any criminal offense or have pending criminal charges or outstanding warrants (to include driving under the influence);</em></li>
<li><em>Have a criminal conviction for which you received a pardon from any country;</em></li>
<li><em>Have been found in violation of any customs, immigration or agriculture regulations or laws in any country;</em></li>
<li><em>Are subjects of an ongoing investigation by any federal, state or local law enforcement agency;</em></li>
<li><em>Have been denied for the purchase of a firearm;</em></li>
<li><em>Are inadmissible to the United States under immigration regulation, including applicants with approved waivers of inadmissibility or parole documentation; or</em></li>
<li><em>Fail to meet other requirements of the FAST Commercial Driver Program.</em></li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>My FAST Card doesn&#8217;t work at the border lane &#8211; what do I do?</h2>
<p>You&#8217;ll have to contact your nearest FAST Enrollment Center to report that your card isn&#8217;t working. They should replace your FAST Card with a new one at no cost.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2>What to do when your FAST Card is taken away at the border?</h2>
<p>You&#8217;ll have to contact the FAST enrollment center nearest to the border crossing where your card was confiscated. There you&#8217;ll have to ask if your FAST membership was suspended or revoked. If it was suspended ask whether you can get your card back what steps you should take. If it was revoked, ask what steps you have to take to get your membership back again.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><b>Truck Drivers in Canada &#8211; Table of Contents</b></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/">How to become a truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/">How to become a truck driver in Canada for <span style="color: #ff0000;">foreigners</span>?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/">How to find a good truck driving school in Canada?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/">Truck drivers pay in Canada</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/">Urban vs. Rural jobs</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/">Owner-operator truck drivers&#8217; salary and bonuses</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/">How to move to USA as a Canadian truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><em>Need help? Contact us today.. </em></h3>
<p><div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full" id="wpforms-3069"><form id="wpforms-form-3069" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3069" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="e3c6881b53bf701fc131d3fe933d94ab"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3069-field_0-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="0"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_0">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_0" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][0]" placeholder="Name" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_1">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3069-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" placeholder="Email" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_4-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-number" data-field-id="4"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3069-field_4">Phone number</label><input type="number" pattern="\d*" id="wpforms-3069-field_4" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][4]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_2-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="2"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_2">Questions <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><textarea id="wpforms-3069-field_2" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][2]" placeholder="Questions" required></textarea></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-captcha" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_3">Captcha <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label>			<div class="wpforms-captcha-math">
				<span class="wpforms-captcha-equation">
											<span class="n1"></span>
						<span class="cal"></span>
						<span class="n2"></span>
											<span class="e">=</span>
				</span>
				<input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_3" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required a" data-rule-wpf-captcha="math" name="wpforms[fields][3][a]" required>				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][cal]" class="cal">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n2]" class="n2">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n1]" class="n1">
			</div>
			</div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3069"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="15"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3069" class="wpforms-submit button button-round button-bg-red" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container --></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Truck driving schools in Canada</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Allard John Keeley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 22 Nov 2022 15:18:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=8958</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The choice is between community colleges with trucking courses and private schools that may sometimes work with trucking companies (as do many local college programs). Some private schools don’t seem to have the best reputation, so opinion seems to slightly favor colleges. Most programs are around 3 months and require over 100 hours of training...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The choice is between community colleges with trucking courses and private schools that may sometimes work with trucking companies (as do many local college programs). Some private schools don’t seem to have the best reputation, so opinion seems to slightly favor colleges. Most programs are around 3 months and require over 100 hours of training and may include additional training for airbrakes, for example, or include the MELT program (Mandatory Entry Level Training). With this in mind, let’s survey some of the offerings out there.</p>
<h2>How to find a good truck driving school?</h2>
<p>You’ll easily find them searching online. Here’s some suggestions to prime your pump:</p>
<ul>
<li>In the Vancouver area and elsewhere in BC try:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://www.goldstarprofessional.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gold Star Professional Driving School</a> in Burnaby BC</li>
<li><a href="https://www.burnabypro.ca/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Burnaby Professional Driving School</a> also, oddly enough, in Burnaby</li>
<li><a href="https://www.roadtitansdrivingschool.ca/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Road Titans Driving School</a> in Surrey BC</li>
<li><a href="https://cotr.bc.ca/truck-driver/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">College of the Rockies</a> in Golden BC</li>
<li><a href="https://www.tru.ca/trades/continuing-studies/professional-driver-training.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Thompson Rivers University – Truck Driver Training</a> in Kamloops BC</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In the Calgary area and elsewhere in Alberta, try:
<ul>
<li><a href="http://www.wtsafety.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> T. Safety Truck Driving School</a> in Calgary, Alberta</li>
<li><a href="https://www.ccatruckdrivertraining.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CCA Truck Driver Training</a> in Calgary</li>
<li><a href="https://www.capilanotrucktraining.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Capilano Truck Driver Training Institute</a> in Edmonton, Alberta</li>
<li><a href="http://wheelson.ca/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Wheels On</a> school in Red Deer, Alberta</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In the GTA and the rest of Ontario try:
<ul>
<li><a href="https://humber.ca/education-training-solutions/transportation-training.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Humber College Transportation Training Centre</a> – in Mississauga Ontario (just west of Toronto)</li>
<li><a href="https://durhamcollege.ca/programs-and-courses/better-jobs-ontario/better-jobs-ontario-options/truck-drivingtechnical-training" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Durham College – Truck Driver/Technical Training</a> – in Whitby/Oshawa Ontario (just east of Toronto)</li>
<li><a href="https://canadiantrucktraining.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Canadian Truck Training Centre</a> – Mississauga Ontario</li>
<li><a href="https://www.confederationcollege.ca/program/az-truck-driver-melt-mandatory-entry-level-training" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Confederation College AZ Truck Driver MELT</a> (Mandatory Entry Level Training) in Thunder Bay Ontario</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-8937 size-medium" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/trucking-ads-on-Immigroup-500x272.jpg" alt="ad" width="500" height="272" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/trucking-ads-on-Immigroup-500x272.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/trucking-ads-on-Immigroup.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></p>
<h2>What are the expected costs?</h2>
<p>Most truck driving training programs and courses will cost you anywhere from $5,000 to up to $15,000. Yes, that’s expensive for a course that might last a month or two, but it’s mandatory training. However, you can look for funding, especially from an employer who is willing to offer you a truck driving job and will pay for at least a part of your tuition. Here are some funding options available in Canada:</p>
<ul>
<li>Canada-Ontario Job Grant (COJG): This provides financial support to employers who want to deliver short-term training for their existing and new employees. If you can get a transportation company in Ontario to offer you a job, this program helps the company pay the costs of your truck driving course.</li>
<li>Second Career: this provides living expenses and helps with tuition for unemployed and laid-off workers in Ontario.</li>
<li>Ontario Works: also helps with the cost of training programs for recipients of this program.</li>
<li>Work BC – B.C. Employer Training Grant – this provides up to $10,000 per employee to the employer to cover up to 80% of the cost of training. This is done to help their employees upgrade their skills.</li>
<li>Canada-Alberta Job Grant (CAJG): this is similar to COJG and involves the employer applying on behalf of current and future employees to obtain funding for their training costs. Funding is provided by the government through the Workforce Development Agreement. The government funds 2/3 of the cost and the employer funds 1/3 of the cost. If the employee is an unemployed Albertan, then the government can fund up to 100% of the cost.</li>
</ul>
<h2>Good school vs. Bad</h2>
<p>The basic standard to judge truck driving schools by is <strong>MELT</strong>,<em> Mandatory Entry Level Training</em>. For the past several years many provinces have switched their training school standards for Class 1/A in Ontario commercial licenses to those mandated by MELT. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>MELT in BC requires you to take 140 hours total time in the classroom and on the road.</li>
<li>MELT in Ontario requires 103.5 hours total classroom and on-road training.</li>
<li>MELT in Saskatchewan requires 121.5 hours total training, including in the classroom and on the road.</li>
<li>MELT in Alberta requires 113 hours total training time.</li>
<li>MELTS in Manitoba requires 121.5 hours total training time.</li>
</ul>
<p>Make sure your school adheres to these standards, depending on the province it’s located in.</p>
<p>Ask yourself if the school is a member of a trade association? For example, Truck Training Schools of Ontario or TTSAO in Ontario.</p>
<p><a href="https://ttsao.com/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://ttsao.com/</a></p>
<p>Ask if the school takes care of the testing as well. Or do they just do the training and send you off elsewhere to be tested?</p>
<p>Some private schools associated with a few transport companies have had the reputation of churning out under-qualified drivers without the necessary training to handle road conditions in Canada. While they may offer you immediate work, make sure you don’t get stuck in a low-paying job with poor training that will put you at a disadvantage going forward. Community college truck training programs tend to take longer but they generally do a better job.</p>
<h2>Resume template for truck drivers in Canada.</h2>
<p>This first section, involving at most a paragraph or two, will be what makes someone decide to contact you or toss your resume aside. Get it right, for your own sake.</p>
<p><strong>NAME </strong></p>
<p><em>Truck driver with – </em>type of license (with endorsements if possible)</p>
<p>One or two easy-to-read sentences that describe your skills and any references you have. Use positive adjectives like <em>quick, reliable, punctual</em>, or phrases like <em>with good knowledge of vehicle maintenance and inspection.</em></p>
<p><strong>CONTACT INFORMATION </strong></p>
<p>Leave at least 2 ways for them to contact you: phone and email, throw in your WhatsApp if you want.</p>
<p>The next sections add details about your Work Experience, your Education, and any Certifications you have. List your latest job first and progress backwards to earlier jobs as you move down the page. The more experience you have the more you’ll know what to put down. Don’t over elaborate. List your responsibilities briefly, focusing on the functions you performed.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="aligncenter wp-image-9002 size-full" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/resume-template-example-for-truck-drivers.jpg" alt="resume template for truck drivers in Canada" width="694" height="596" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/resume-template-example-for-truck-drivers.jpg 694w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/resume-template-example-for-truck-drivers-500x429.jpg 500w" sizes="(max-width: 694px) 100vw, 694px" /></p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">FAQ</h2>
<h3>Truck driving schools overseas (meeting Canadian standards)</h3>
<p>As we mentioned elsewhere, you&#8217;ll need to take a training course and pass the examinations when you move to Canada. An overseas truck driving school might mean you have a little more experience and knowledge than someone starting from scratch. But remember, every country – and every province/territory in Canada – has slightly or sometimes significantly different regulatory requirements. Just assume you’ll have to study for and take practical training in Canada to become a truck driver.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><b>Truck Drivers in Canada &#8211; Table of Contents</b></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/">How to become a truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/">How to become a truck driver in Canada for <span style="color: #ff0000;">foreigners</span>?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/">How to find a good truck driving school in Canada?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/">Truck drivers pay in Canada</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/">Urban vs. Rural jobs</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/">Owner-operator truck drivers&#8217; salary and bonuses</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/">How to move to USA as a Canadian truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/">Truck Driver with Criminal record</a></h3>
<p><div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full" id="wpforms-3069"><form id="wpforms-form-3069" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3069" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="e3c6881b53bf701fc131d3fe933d94ab"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3069-field_0-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="0"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_0">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_0" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][0]" placeholder="Name" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_1">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3069-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" placeholder="Email" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_4-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-number" data-field-id="4"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3069-field_4">Phone number</label><input type="number" pattern="\d*" id="wpforms-3069-field_4" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][4]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_2-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="2"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_2">Questions <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><textarea id="wpforms-3069-field_2" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][2]" placeholder="Questions" required></textarea></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-captcha" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_3">Captcha <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label>			<div class="wpforms-captcha-math">
				<span class="wpforms-captcha-equation">
											<span class="n1"></span>
						<span class="cal"></span>
						<span class="n2"></span>
											<span class="e">=</span>
				</span>
				<input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_3" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required a" data-rule-wpf-captcha="math" name="wpforms[fields][3][a]" required>				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][cal]" class="cal">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n2]" class="n2">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n1]" class="n1">
			</div>
			</div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3069"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="15"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3069" class="wpforms-submit button button-round button-bg-red" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to move to USA as a Canadian truck driver?</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Content Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 19:19:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=8905</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[This article mainly deals with Truck Drivers in Canada. However, let’s instead assume your end goal, once you are working in Canada, is to transfer down to the USA. Let’s explore how your Canadian Trucking experience can be transferred down to the United States. How to get a job for people living in Canada? As...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>This article mainly deals with Truck Drivers in Canada. However, let’s instead assume your end goal, once you are working in Canada, is to transfer down to the USA. Let’s explore how your Canadian Trucking experience can be transferred down to the United States.</p>
<h2>How to get a job for people living in Canada?</h2>
<p>As we mention in our first FAQ below, if you’re going to move to the US, you’re going to have to retake the written and on-road exams to get your commercial driver’s license (CDL) in the US. Remember, each state – like each province/territory in Canada – is in charge of transport licensing, so the rules may vary from state to state in the US. Basically, you’ll have to start from scratch again, but with the advantage of your experience, having taken similar exams in Canada and having worked as a truck driver.</p>
<h3>Here are the steps you’ll need to take:</h3>
<ul>
<li>If you’re still in Canada, you’re going to need a visa to live and work in the US as a commercial truck driver. You can try an <em>H2B non-immigrant visa</em> which some consultants/lawyers suggest, but that’s a temporary work visa and only allows you to work for usually less than a year at a time, although it can sometimes be extended up to 3 years. It’s meant for seasonal or temporary non-agricultural work and for where there’s a shortage of workers (as is the case in trucking nowadays in both the US and Canada).
<ul>
<li>First, get an employer who wants to give you a job in the US to apply for temporary labor certification from the US Department of Labor.</li>
<li>The employer then files form I-129 (Petition for non-immigrant worker) with USCIS showing the work is temporary, and no US workers were available to do the job.</li>
<li>If the employer’s Petition for Nonimmigrant Worker is approved, you’ll be invited to apply for an H2B visa, and you’ll also be interviewed at the nearest US consulate/embassy. However, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/andyjsemotiuk/2021/11/16/could-us-immigration-help-solve-need-to-recruit-1-million-new-truck-drivers-over-next-decade/?sh=21d8eeb66ba6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it has been reported by Forbes magazine</a> that Canadian truck drivers can skip this step and head to the border.</li>
<li>Once your H2B visa stay is over, you’ll have to return to Canada for at least 3 months and repeat the process if you wish to return.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Once you’ve got your visa and moved to the US, you’ll have to:
<ul>
<li>enroll in a truck driver training course;</li>
<li>apply online for a CDL Learners Permit Application;</li>
<li>Take the CDL General Knowledge Test</li>
<li>Do up to 300 hours of classroom training and on-road training</li>
<li>Pass the Final CDL Test (Vehicle Inspection; Basic Controls Test; Road Test; Endorsements for example for airbrakes)</li>
<li>Get your CDL</li>
<li>Get a job or start the job you’ve already been offered.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Frankly, it’s often easier to remain a resident of Canada and try to obtain some more cross-border jobs if they pay well. Otherwise, you have to deal both with getting a visa (you can try obtaining a Green Card which is like a PR Card in Canada, but that’s much less likely to succeed) and with getting your US CDL.</p>
<p>There’s one more option: the EB-3 Employment-Based Permanent Resident Option, but it’s expensive and time-consuming. See just below for more details.</p>
<h2>How to get a job in the US as a foreigners?</h2>
<p>It’s the same as above. You can try an H2B Visa, or you can try to get a Green Card as a truck driver, but it won’t be easy. There is the possibility of applying for what is called an <em>EB-3 Employment-Based Permanent Resident Option</em> for foreign unskilled truck drivers to work in the US. It will take you longer than an H2B visa and will cost you more, <a href="https://www.forbes.com/sites/andyjsemotiuk/2021/11/16/could-us-immigration-help-solve-need-to-recruit-1-million-new-truck-drivers-over-next-decade/?sh=21d8eeb66ba6" target="_blank" rel="noopener">according to Forbes</a>, but you’ll end up with permanent resident status, which is much preferable to the temporary status of an H2B.</p>
<h2>FAQ</h2>
<h3>How to transfer a truck driver’s license between Canada and the US</h3>
<p>Since 1989, the USA and Canada have agreed to mutually recognize Canadian and American commercial driver’s licenses in their jurisdictions. However, if you are prohibited from obtaining a commercial driver’s license in the other country. That means that you’d have to move to the US or to Canada and reside there and apply for a new commercial driver’s license. As the US Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration states:</p>
<p><em>Accordingly, a commercial driver&#8217;s license issued by a Canadian jurisdiction in conformity with the Canadian National Safety Code will be considered to be the single commercial driver&#8217;s license for operation in the United States by Canadian drivers. Also, a Canadian driver holding a commercial driver&#8217;s license issued under the Canadian National Safety Code <strong>will be prohibited</strong> from obtaining any driver&#8217;s license from a State or other licensing jurisdiction of the United States.</em></p>
<p>In other words, if you move to the US from Canada or vice versa, you’ll have to take the written and on-road tests (and any other tests like vehicle inspection) required in order to get a commercial driver0s license for that jurisdiction. If you’re just travelling on a job to the US or vice versa, then your Canadian or American CDL will be accepted – as long as it’s valid for the vehicle and payload you’re carrying.</p>
<p><a href="https://ustr.gov/trade-agreements/free-trade-agreements/united-states-mexico-canada-agreement/agreement-between" target="_blank" rel="noopener">USMCA</a> (US Mexico-Canada Trade Agreement signed in 2020 that replaced NAFTA) does not change this requirement. The only difference is that Canadian and American standards are very similar, so you should have a leg up on someone taking the test for the first time. Still, play it safe and carefully review the material and take a training course to make sure you pass the exams. Some schools will offer a <em>Transfer Training Program</em> tailored to a trucker with experience in one country who is moving to the other country and needs to retake the tests.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><b>Truck Drivers in Canada &#8211; Table of Contents</b></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/">How to become a truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/">How to become a truck driver in Canada for <span style="color: #ff0000;">foreigners</span>?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/">How to find a good truck driving school in Canada?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/">Truck drivers pay in Canada</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/">Urban vs. Rural jobs</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/">Owner-operator truck drivers&#8217; salary and bonuses</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/">Truck Driver with Criminal record</a></h3>
<p><div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full" id="wpforms-3069"><form id="wpforms-form-3069" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3069" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="e3c6881b53bf701fc131d3fe933d94ab"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3069-field_0-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="0"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_0">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_0" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][0]" placeholder="Name" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_1">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3069-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" placeholder="Email" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_4-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-number" data-field-id="4"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3069-field_4">Phone number</label><input type="number" pattern="\d*" id="wpforms-3069-field_4" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][4]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_2-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="2"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_2">Questions <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><textarea id="wpforms-3069-field_2" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][2]" placeholder="Questions" required></textarea></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-captcha" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_3">Captcha <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label>			<div class="wpforms-captcha-math">
				<span class="wpforms-captcha-equation">
											<span class="n1"></span>
						<span class="cal"></span>
						<span class="n2"></span>
											<span class="e">=</span>
				</span>
				<input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_3" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required a" data-rule-wpf-captcha="math" name="wpforms[fields][3][a]" required>				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][cal]" class="cal">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n2]" class="n2">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n1]" class="n1">
			</div>
			</div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3069"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="26"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3069" class="wpforms-submit button button-round button-bg-red" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to become a truck driver in Canada for foreigners?</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Content Team]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 19:10:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=8898</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Even if you’re a foreign truck driver who has experience and credentials from their home country, you generally have to have your credentials recognized by a provincial or territorial authority before you start driving a truck in Canada. We’ll go through the basic steps for someone who wants to move to Canada to become a...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Even if you’re a foreign truck driver who has experience and credentials from their home country, you generally have to have your credentials recognized by a provincial or territorial authority before you start driving a truck in Canada. We’ll go through the basic steps for someone who wants to move to Canada to become a truck driver.</p>
<p>The main difference here is that you have to be accepted through one of Canada’s immigration streams and that often means having a job offer waiting for you in Canada. Most foreigners interested in driving a truck will already have some experience. So, the question becomes whether you can get any of your credentials accepted in Canada.</p>
<h2>Basic requirements for foreigners to drive truck in Canada</h2>
<p>Remember, however, you will have to be accepted by Canadian immigration authorities under whatever stream you choose to apply. In view of this, the best way in is through a provincial nominee program (PNP), if one exists. For example:</p>
<ul>
<li>In BC you can apply through the Entry Level and Semi-Skilled category for work as a long-haul truck driver as a path to permanent residency. To qualify, you must:
<ul>
<li>Have a full-time, permanent job offer</li>
<li>Have been previously working for your employer for at least 9 consecutive months, which means you must already be in Canada on a temporary work permit.</li>
<li>Be licensed or certified to do your job</li>
<li>Earn a wage in line with existing provincial wage rates for that job</li>
<li>Meet language (English proficiency) and education (secondary school completed) requirements</li>
<li>Be able to support your family</li>
<li>Have legal status in Canada</li>
<li>To start, <a href="https://www.pnpapplication.gov.bc.ca/user/sign-in" target="_blank" rel="noopener">go to BCPNP Online</a> to register and start creating your profile.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In Alberta, the Alberta Advantage Immigration Program (AAIP) has several streams for workers. The Opportunity Stream is for foreign workers already living in Alberta, working full-time and with a permanent job offer from a qualified employer. You must also:
<ul>
<li>Have a positive LMIA (Labor Market Impact Assessment) or an LMIA exemption</li>
<li>Not be a refugee claimant</li>
<li>Not be living in another province or territory</li>
<li>Have valid temporary legal status in Canada</li>
<li>Be an eligible occupation in Alberta – truck drivers are eligible. Taxi drivers and limousine drivers are ineligible according to the Alberta government.</li>
<li>You’ll need CLB score of 4 in all English Language (or French) skills. This translates to: IELTS 4.5 for listening, 3.5 for reading, and 4.0 for speaking and writing.</li>
<li>Have completed secondary education that is equivalent to Alberta high school levels along with an educational credential assessment (ECA) from a <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/corporate/partners-service-providers/immigrant-serving-organizations/best-practices/foreign-educational-credential-assessment.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">recognized Educational Credential Assessment Service Provider</a>.</li>
<li>Have a minimum of 12 months of work experience as a truck driver in Alberta in the last 18 months OR have a minimum of 24 months of work experience in Canada or abroad in the last 30 months.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In <a href="https://www.saskatchewan.ca/residents/moving-to-saskatchewan/live-in-saskatchewan/by-immigrating/saskatchewan-immigrant-nominee-program/browse-sinp-programs/applicants-with-saskatchewan-experience/long-haul-truck-driver-project" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Saskatchewan</a>, the province’s Long-Haul Truck Drivers program offers you the possibility of permanent residence just like BC and Alberta but is a little easier on the requirements. You need to have worked as a full-time temporary foreign worker for just 6 months before applying for PR status once your company offers you a permanent full-time job. In addition, you must:
<ul>
<li>Have a 1A Saskatchewan drivers license</li>
<li>Have a permanent full-time job offer from an approved Saskatchewan employer</li>
<li>Have a CLB English test of 4 or higher (See IELTS equivalent scores directly above in the Alberta program)</li>
<li>Have a valid SINP (Saskatchewan Immigrant Nominee Program) Job Approval Letter</li>
<li><a href="https://immigration.saskatchewan.ca/apex/f?p=305:101:16383852508450:::::" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Go here</a> to open an account with SINP Online and start the process.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>In <a href="https://immigratemanitoba.com/employer-services/truck-drivers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Manitoba</a>, <strong><em>employers</em></strong> looking to hire international workers as long-haul truck drivers must now meet some upgraded requirements, including:
<ul>
<li>Obtain a positive LMIA within the last 12 months</li>
<li>Have previously used Canada Job Bank to advertise the position at normal wages</li>
<li>Comply with Mandatory Entry Level Training (MELT) as structured by Manitoba Public Insurance</li>
<li>Hire international truck drivers from countries with standards similar to North America</li>
<li>Comply with Manitoba’s Worker Recruitment and Protection Act (WRAPA)</li>
<li>Prove to Manitoba’s Employer Services that the international truck driver has NOT had to pay to obtain their job at any point in the recruitment process</li>
<li>Show a good record of hiring international truck drivers in the past</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>        Truck drivers themselves in Manitoba must:</h4>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Be between 21 and 50 years old</li>
<li>Have worked a minimum of 3 years in a jurisdiction with similar standards to Manitoba</li>
<li>Provide reference letters and other proof of employment</li>
<li>Have a valid English test (like IELTS) with CLB 5 standards (this is tougher than BC, Alberta, or Saskatchewan)</li>
<li>Be fully vetted in a video-conference video by the employer who wants to hire you</li>
<li>Fully disclose any paid representative helping you at any point in the recruitment and immigration process.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>In other words, Manitoba might not be your best first choice unless you feel you are up to their tougher standards.</p>
<ul>
<li>In Ontario, the In-Demand Skills stream allows foreign workers both in Ontario and abroad to apply for permanent residence. You need a job offer in Ontario and then you have to register with the Ontario Immigrant Nominee Program’s OINP Expression of Interest System, an online portal. You provide your profile at the portal, obtain an Invitation to Apply and then apply for a nomination by the Ontario program. You then are screened by IRCC and hopefully, they approve your application for permanent resident as a truck driver in Ontario. Your job offer must:
<ul>
<li>Full-time and permanent</li>
<li>In an eligible occupation (transport truck drivers are eligible)</li>
<li>Your job is NOT restricted to being outside the GTA (Greater Toronto Area) like some other occupations</li>
<li>You must be paid the median wages level</li>
<li>Your position must be urgently needed by your employer</li>
<li>Your work must be based in Ontario</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<h4>        The truck driver in Ontario must:</h4>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>Have received an ITA from <a href="https://www.ontario.ca/page/ontario-immigrant-nominee-program-oinp" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OINP</a></li>
<li>Be qualified according to Canadian standards</li>
<li>Have 9 months experience within the last 3 years</li>
<li>Have or obtain a valid commercial driver license in Ontario</li>
<li>Have CLB 4 language requirements as proved by a test like IELTS</li>
<li>Have completed secondary school or its equivalent abroad and also provide an ECA (educational credential assessment)</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Quebec and the Maritime provinces have programs with similar requirements aside from the obvious language requirements in Quebec (you must speak French).</p>
<p>*Please note that this research was completed in early 2023, and PNP programs change all the time. Do your own research before moving forward.</p>
<h2>Step 1: Get a job offer in Canada.</h2>
<p>You’ll need to find a company willing to hire you from abroad and ensure you meet their requirements. However, this won’t be quite as difficult as it might seem, given the overwhelming demand for truck drivers that are expected over the next decade as retiring drivers and a growing economy leaves many positions unfilled. Review the job requirements that provincial nominee programs are demanding. As long as you comply with these demands, you should be in good shape as far as any company’s requirements. Also remember to make sure you know what type of driver’s license you need – Generally Class 1 for longer tractor trailers or Semis and Class 3 for smaller straight-body trucks.</p>
<p>If you’ll be driving a truck with airbrakes, you’re going to need an airbrakes endorsement from the provincial regulatory authority. You’ll also need a TDG (Transportation of Dangerous Goods) certificate if you’ll be transporting things like hazardous materials or flammable products. However, these types of jobs usually require several years of experience in Canada, so it’s not likely you’ll start with these types of jobs.</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Tip</span>: Another option is to obtain a temporary work permit for simpler trucking jobs you can start with – like an urban delivery truck or a tow-truck, work for about a year and then try to obtain a full-time permanent job and begin the process of applying to a PNP or directly to Express Entry. Remember if you get a provincial nomination, your odds of getting accepted for permanent residence by IRCC go way up.</p>
<h2>Step 2: Register with and apply through a provincial online portal.</h2>
<p>Remember to take an English test – as you’ll be abroad, we suggest IELTS. See the above for the required scores. You’ll also need to get an ECA or educational credentials assessment for your secondary school. <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/educational-credential-assessment-eca-express-entry/">You’ll find more information on ECAs here</a>.</p>
<h2>Step 3: Apply to IRCC</h2>
<p>With your provincial nomination in hand, you then apply to IRCC for permanent residence. As someone doing an in-demand occupation like truck driving, your odds should be pretty good to obtain your PR card.</p>
<h2>Step 4: Pack your bags</h2>
<p>Once you’re in Canada, you’re going to have to get your commercial driver’s license (Class 1/Class A in Ontario and Class 3/Class D in Ontario) as well as any certification or other licensing required by the province. Then you’ll literally be good to go. See our first FAQ below for more information on driver licenses from abroad.</p>
<h2>Step 5: FAST card</h2>
<p>A FAST (Free and Secure Trade) Card gives commercial drivers quicker access at USMCA borders – Canada/US &amp; US/Mexico. You have to pass a pre-screening process which, once you’re approved, allows for simpler customs and immigration checks at the border.</p>
<p>Remember that there are 2 FAST Card programs – one for the Canada/US border and one for the US/Mexico border. If you’re also going to be driving in Mexico, you’ll need to apply for <em>both</em> cards, assuming you’re eligible to do so.</p>
<h4>Canada/US FAST Card eligibility</h4>
<p>Have Immigroup help you get your Fast Card, <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/service/fast-card-commercial-drivers/">click here</a>.</p>
<ul>
<li>Be a citizen or permanent resident of Canada or the US</li>
<li>Be at least 18 years old</li>
<li>Have a commercial driver’s license</li>
<li>Be admissible to both Canada and the US (not have a criminal record)</li>
<li>Some permanent residents may need a visa to enter Canada or the US – depending on their home country</li>
</ul>
<h4>US/Mexico FAST Card eligibility</h4>
<ul>
<li>Be a citizen or permanent resident of Canada, the US, or Mexico</li>
<li>Be at least 18 years old</li>
<li>Have a commercial driver’s license</li>
<li>Be admissible to the US (no criminal record)</li>
<li>Some permanent residents may need a visa to enter the US or Mexico – depending on their home country</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.immigroup.com/service/fast-card-commercial-drivers/">Go here for our guide on how to apply for a FAST Card</a>.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">FAQ</h2>
<h3>Can I get a truck driving job in Canada, if I am still not licensed?</h3>
<p>Some unethical operators might offer you a job without asking for a license, but this is rare and to be avoided. If anyone did and you accepted, it would be a great way to end up detained and deported should the police stop you for a traffic violation, for example. So, although it’s unlikely that anyone will offer you a job without a license, don’t accept any offer if they don’t ask for your license.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3>Truck driving schools overseas (meeting Canadian standards)</h3>
<p>You will still need to take a training course and pass the examinations when you move to Canada. The only advantage is you might have more experience and knowledge than someone starting from scratch. However, bear in mind that every country – and every province/territory in Canada – has slightly or sometimes significantly different regulatory requirements. Always assume you’ll have to study for and take practical training in Canada to become a truck driver.</p>
<h3>Can I get a visa sponsored as a truck driver in Canada?</h3>
<p>Not exactly, but you can get a provincial nomination if you have a job offer and meet the other requirements. See<em> How to Become a Truck Driver for foreigners </em>above.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><b>Truck Drivers in Canada &#8211; Table of Contents</b></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/">How to become a truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/">How to find a good truck driving school in Canada?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/">Truck drivers pay in Canada</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/">Urban vs. Rural jobs</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/">Owner-operator truck drivers&#8217; salary and bonuses</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/">How to move to USA as a Canadian truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/">Truck Driver with Criminal record</a></h3>
<p><div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full" id="wpforms-3069"><form id="wpforms-form-3069" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3069" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="e3c6881b53bf701fc131d3fe933d94ab"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3069-field_0-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="0"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_0">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_0" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][0]" placeholder="Name" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_1">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3069-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" placeholder="Email" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_4-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-number" data-field-id="4"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3069-field_4">Phone number</label><input type="number" pattern="\d*" id="wpforms-3069-field_4" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][4]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_2-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="2"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_2">Questions <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><textarea id="wpforms-3069-field_2" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][2]" placeholder="Questions" required></textarea></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-captcha" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_3">Captcha <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label>			<div class="wpforms-captcha-math">
				<span class="wpforms-captcha-equation">
											<span class="n1"></span>
						<span class="cal"></span>
						<span class="n2"></span>
											<span class="e">=</span>
				</span>
				<input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_3" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required a" data-rule-wpf-captcha="math" name="wpforms[fields][3][a]" required>				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][cal]" class="cal">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n2]" class="n2">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n1]" class="n1">
			</div>
			</div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3069"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="26"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3069" class="wpforms-submit button button-round button-bg-red" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Owner-operator truck drivers’ salary in Canada</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Allard John Keeley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 18:46:48 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=8891</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Owner-operator truck drivers’ salary and bonuses To start with let’s set out the main differences between working as a driver for a company and being an owner-operator who basically runs their own small business. As a driver working for a company, a lot of things get done for you that you might not even think...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2><strong>Owner-operator truck drivers’ salary and bonuses</strong></h2>
<p>To start with let’s set out the main differences between working as a driver for a company and being an owner-operator who basically runs their own small business. As a driver working for a company, a lot of things get done for you that you might not even think about. You give up control for predictability and stability but often end up with a lower salary.</p>
<p>As an owner-operator, you have the control, which means you’re now responsible for everything from maintenance and insurance to buying new tires, from figuring out how much to spend on a new tractor (it could easily cost you $100K), to doing your taxes and ensuring all licensing requirements and permits are being met. And don’t forget insurance! Plus, you have to look for work. But yes, you can earn a significantly higher income.</p>
<p>In Canada, the average base salary for owner-operators –<a href="https://ca.indeed.com/career/owner-operator-driver/salaries" target="_blank" rel="noopener"> according to indeed.ca</a> &#8211; is just over <strong>$160K per year</strong>. However, don’t forget you have to deduct all those costs and expenses you’ll face for operating your own rig. So, the net take home is often under $100K. Still, if you’re earning, say $85K a year owning and operating your own tractor-trailer, that’s significantly better than most company drivers. And some owner-operators will easily net more than 100K per year.</p>
<p>Remember, you will really have to earn those salaries as an owner-operator. So, here are a few hacks to help you maximize your earnings.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Go to load boards (websites advertising loads that need transporting, usually with a free section and a subscription section with more offers) and keep your truck busy moving as many loads as possible. You’ll need to sort out who the better brokers are, and that’s partly trial and error.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Really dive in and register a <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency/services/tax/businesses/small-businesses-self-employed-income/setting-your-business/sole-proprietorship.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">sole proprietorship</a>. You can even hire yourself as an employee with your benefits as deductible expenses. Register your trade (operating) name, get a tax number from Revenue Canada, and open up a business account in your trade name at your bank. You will need an accountant, by the way.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Get cargo insurance to cover damaged, lost, or stolen goods and any other event that might affect your revenue and incur costs.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Find the regions and cities that pay the best rates. You own your own rig. You can go where the money is, even if that means being away from home for longer.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">How are you getting paid? If it’s a percentage of load revenue, then you want to be moving high-value goods more often than not. If you’re being paid by the kilometer, your earnings are more consistent, but that high-value payload will earn you just the same as any other load you carry. So, your choice will depend on what types of loads you figure you’ll be hauling, and that could depend on what regions you tend to work in, and who you tend to work for and it will also depend on whether you prefer taking on some risk (percentage payments) or whether you value predictability (mileage payments).</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Buy or lease your truck? If you don’t have the cash upfront to outright buy your rig, then you’re basically looking at mortgage payments on a small house, seeing tractors alone can cost around $100K. Do you lease your rig instead and what terms are leasing companies offering you? If you love trucks and think you have the knowledge to sniff out a fair deal on a tractor-trailer, then this part of the game might not be such a huge challenge. However, if you aren’t familiar with the truck market, you might want to accumulate a few years experience driving for a company while you find out as much as you can about trucks and how much they cost to buy and especially how much it costs to keep them running. That will be a huge part of your expenses as an owner-operator and, therefore, a drain on your net income. Never forget that. Always, and that means always, schedule regular maintenance check-ups for your rig and factor that into your expense planning. Or you could end up spending thousands of dollars fixing a problem maintenance would have prevented, all while your truck sits idle in the repair shop. Your choice.</p>
<h3>Planning, what is the most money you can make as a truck driver in Canada?</h3>
<p>A little basic math. Average revenue and maximum revenue. As an owner-operator your income will vary, especially if you usually get paid on a percentage-of-load-revenue basis. What you want are average annual revenues as high as possible, not just a few killer months and then lots of downtime because your truck blew up or you’re too damn tired and need a rest.</p>
<p>Owner operators, and not company drivers, will usually be the top earners, but not every owner operator will be able to maximize their income from their truck driving. It depends on a few factors, similar to what we listed just above:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">How much time are you willing to spend on the road away from home? More time on the road, more revenue.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">How much are you willing to pay and how much time are you willing to take to ensure regular maintenance checks? You’ll really need them if you’re running your rig as much as possible. A major breakdown of your rig will always eat up more operating time than a series of regular maintenance checks. That will require planning your maintenance checks to fit into your load-carrying schedule.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Good tax software. Don’t laugh. Nothing eats into your net earnings more than a surprise <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/revenue-agency.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">tax bill from CRA</a>. And if you can schedule quarterly installment payments on your taxes, do it. It will make your earnings more predictable and help you plan your work.</p>
<p>So, what are some of the highest earnings truck drivers can make? According to indeed.ca an owner operator who carries loads for DSL Express Trucking makes over $360K a year. That would be before expenses, but you’re still looking at around <strong>$250K per year</strong>. That’s a very nice salary.</p>
<h2>FAQ</h2>
<h3>What does it take to own your own truck driver business in Canada?</h3>
<p>If you’re reading this guide, it’s safe to assume you’re more likely interested in starting small and building up your company from a few trucks to something on a larger scale. So, this FAQ will cover how to start a small trucking company in Canada. If you’re seriously interested in starting your own trucking business, ask yourself the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>How much experience in trucking do you have and is it in Canada or the US or abroad?
<ul>
<li>The surest if not the quickest way, is to drive a truck for at least 2 years, then buy your own truck and work as an owner operator for a couple of years to get to know how the transport industry works.</li>
<li>If you don’t have much experience, then you had better do some serious research on the industry. But more than that, your research should guide you to a specific segment of the industry.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What kind of loads will your company be carrying?
<ul>
<li>Dry goods, metal tubing, primary products like lumber … what do you want to focus on?</li>
<li>How many and what type of trucks do you want to start with? A Dry Van, a Flatbed, a Step Deck? It will depend on what you’re carrying and that will depend on what segment you decide to focus on.</li>
<li>Will you do any LTL (Less-Than-Truckload) jobs?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Will you focus on Short-Haul within an urban area or Long-Haul between cities?
<ul>
<li>If it’s Long-Haul, what Lanes will you focus on? Lanes in trucking lingo mean the dedicated routes/highways between cities that your drivers will be mostly using. This in turn depends on where in Canada you’ll focus your activity.</li>
<li>How many trucks do you think you’ll need? How many can your budget pay for? Will you buy using a truck loan, or lease?</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>What do permits and licensing are you going to need?
<ul>
<li>For example, you’ll need a Safety Fitness Certificate from the National Safety Code. If you’ll be operating in more than one province, apply under Federal law. If you’ll be doing business within only one province, then apply under provincial law.</li>
<li>Your drivers and your company will have to comply with Transport Canada’s Canadian Hours of Service rules – rules prohibiting drivers being on the road without rest for periods deemed dangerous. This means transport companies have to install ELDs (Electronic Logging Devices) to monitor their drivers and ensure they’re not on the road for dangerously long periods.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>Canadian Hours of Service Regulations &#8211; here&#8217;s the government page giving the actual legislation for Hours of Service</p>
<p><a href="https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-2005-313/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/regulations/SOR-2005-313/</a></p>
<ul>
<li>You’ll have to apply for your company’s <em>Commercial Vehicle Operators Registration</em> (CVOR) which is not to be confused with a<em> Commerical Vehicle Operators Record </em>which comes with your truck driving license.</li>
<li>If you’re planning on doing routes in the US, you’ll need an MC (Motor Carrier) number and perhaps what’s called a DOT (Department of Transport) number.</li>
<li>What insurance will you need to cover accidents and other events? How can you get a competitive rate so that your insurance costs don’t eat up a significant part of your revenue?</li>
<li>What type of ownership structure do you want? A Sole Proprietorship? A Partnership? A Corporation is really for larger companies earning lots of revenue, but it’s always an option as well.</li>
<li>While there are websites that help you find a load, you better be ready for some effort and disappointments when looking for work for your company always keeping in mind how low you want to go to get those first jobs when you’re just building a reputation in the transport industry.
<ul>
<li>Be careful here, you might end up charging far too little and get caught in a cash-flow trap and be forced to resort to factoring – having a company take care of your invoices and collecting your bills for you. You’ll get cash up front a little quicker which will help your cash flow, but they will charge a percentage of your revenue.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>And perhaps most importantly: do you have the experience to know how to hire the right drivers for your company? If you don’t, find someone who does. In fact, you could even take a Truck Dispatch Training Course to gain a little experience regarding how to handle your drivers.</li>
<li>Finally, don’t forget to register as a business with Canada Revenue Agency (CRA) and get your account number with them.
<ul>
<li>Yes, you’ll have to pay taxes. GST/HST payroll deductions for your employees, Fuel Taxes, etc.</li>
<li>You’ll have to register under IFTA – International Fuel Tax Agreement; an interprovincial and intestate agreement on fuel taxes that allows you to pay your fuel taxes in one chosen jurisdiction. You’ll need your IFTA credentials in every province (but not Yukon, Northwest Territories, or Nunavut) and most states (except Hawaii and District of Columbia)</li>
<li>You’ll also have to register under IRP – International Registration Plan – which like IFTA involves the provinces in Canada and the states in the US. Here the focus is on commercial vehicle registration rather than fuel taxes.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li>One final suggestion: as mentioned at the start, it’s often a good idea to first try a few years as an owner-operator driving, maintaining and paying for your truck all by your lonesome self. There’s no better way to get to know shippers, mechanics, and other drivers and really have a good idea of how the business works. Then start your own company buying or leasing extra trucks and hiring drivers.</li>
</ul>
<p style="text-align: center;"><b>Truck Drivers in Canada &#8211; Table of Contents</b></p>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/">How to become a truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/">How to become a truck driver in Canada for <span style="color: #ff0000;">foreigners</span>?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/">How to find a good truck driving school in Canada?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/">Truck drivers pay in Canada</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/">Urban vs. Rural jobs</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/">How to move to USA as a Canadian truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/">Truck Driver with Criminal record</a></h3>
<p><div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full" id="wpforms-3069"><form id="wpforms-form-3069" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3069" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="e3c6881b53bf701fc131d3fe933d94ab"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3069-field_0-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="0"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_0">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_0" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][0]" placeholder="Name" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_1">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3069-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" placeholder="Email" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_4-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-number" data-field-id="4"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3069-field_4">Phone number</label><input type="number" pattern="\d*" id="wpforms-3069-field_4" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][4]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_2-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="2"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_2">Questions <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><textarea id="wpforms-3069-field_2" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][2]" placeholder="Questions" required></textarea></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-captcha" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_3">Captcha <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label>			<div class="wpforms-captcha-math">
				<span class="wpforms-captcha-equation">
											<span class="n1"></span>
						<span class="cal"></span>
						<span class="n2"></span>
											<span class="e">=</span>
				</span>
				<input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_3" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required a" data-rule-wpf-captcha="math" name="wpforms[fields][3][a]" required>				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][cal]" class="cal">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n2]" class="n2">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n1]" class="n1">
			</div>
			</div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3069"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="15"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3069" class="wpforms-submit button button-round button-bg-red" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Urban versus Rural jobs for Truck Drivers in Canada</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Allard John Keeley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 18:43:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=8886</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Trucking in North America is divided into 3 main categories: OTR, which means Over-the-road and is another way of saying long-haul trucking; Regional; and Local. So, what is OTR, Regional, and Local Trucking? OTR/Long-haul An OTR diver will spend from weeks to several months on the road for any given job. You’ll end up driving...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Trucking in North America is divided into 3 main categories:</p>
<ol>
<li>OTR, which means <strong>Over-the-road</strong> and is another way of saying long-haul trucking;</li>
<li>Regional; and</li>
<li>Local.</li>
</ol>
<p>So, what is OTR, Regional, and Local Trucking?</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>OTR/Long-haul </strong>
<ul>
<li>An <a href="https://www.smart-trucking.com/long-haul-trucker/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">OTR diver</a> will spend from weeks to several months on the road for any given job.</li>
<li>You’ll end up driving through most of Canada, as well as into the US and even occasionally, Mexico</li>
<li>You can operate either on your own, which is called solo or as part of a team of usually 2 drivers.</li>
<li>Basically, you’ll be doing fewer jobs but travelling further for each job.</li>
<li>You will usually require Class 1/A commercial driving licenses because you&#8217;ll be driving large rigs like a tractor trailer.</li>
<li>You’re paid by the kilometre or by a percentage of what’s called the line-haul revenue or a percentage of the total revenue of the load you transport. You tend to earn significantly more than regional and especially local drivers. Average salaries are around $60,000 annually, but you can make a lot more if you’re willing to put in the time and basically live on the road for long stretches.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Regional</strong>
<ul>
<li>A regional driver is out on a job for maybe a week or 2 at a time.</li>
<li>Because distances are somewhat less, you’ll normally work on your own.</li>
<li>You tend to specialize driving certain types of cargo within a region like the West Coast, the Prairies, Central Canada, or the Maritimes.</li>
<li>Compared to OTR/Long-haul drivers, you’ll do more trips over shorter distances.</li>
<li>You may need a Class 1/A license, or in some cases you might be able to get by with Class 3/D but not if you&#8217;ll be driving semis.</li>
<li>You might get paid by the kilometre or a percentage of the load revenue, but your pay will be somewhat less than long-haul drivers. Average annual salaries are $40,000 to $60,000.</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li><strong>Local</strong>
<ul>
<li>If you’re a local driver, you generally get to go home daily.</li>
<li>The norm is for you to operate on your own and not in a 2-driver team.</li>
<li>Some local drivers work what are called dedicated routes where you transport the same cargo to the same place on a daily basis.</li>
<li>Local drivers will also often handle LTL (less-than-truckload) shipments. That may mean getting paid less than for other long-haul or regional jobs. An LTL is less profitable for the company transporting the goods, so it’s something to keep in mind about local routes.</li>
<li>Local drivers usually get paid by the hour and earn significantly less than long-haul/OTR or Regional drivers. Your salary will range between <strong>$30,000</strong> up to around <strong>$40,000</strong>.</li>
<li>You can usually get by with a Class 3/D license with local work as you&#8217;re often driving straight-body trucks and not semitrailers or 18 wheelers.</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p>If you’re doing more rural routes, you’ll tend to be doing OTR/Long-haul or Regional jobs. Urban drivers tend to be local and often will do dedicated routes, running the same cargo to the same locations, as we mentioned above. Additionally, you will often find yourself starting your trucker career doing local work and then moving up to regional, and finally, long-haul/OTR routes. As you move up to long-haul/OTR you&#8217;ll need to graduate to a Class 1/A license. See our chapter on truck driving schools for more information on this.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: left;">FAQ</h2>
<h3>What are the best locations in Canada to drive a truck? (Pay, an abundance of work, low overhead, etc.)</h3>
<p>The key is to live reasonably close to major transportation hubs like Vancouver, Calgary, Toronto, or Montreal but not too close as the cost of living is substantially higher in Canada’s largest cities, especially Vancouver and Toronto.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<ul>
<li>So, locations like Burnaby or Surrey BC, or even further away in mainland BC, or anywhere in Southern Ontario that’s not actually in Metro Toronto work out well.</li>
<li>Montreal is somewhat cheaper so anywhere close to Montreal works out well, but you’re going to have to do at least part of your work in French.</li>
<li>Additionally, provinces like Saskatchewan offer good prospects with much cheaper housing as we explain below in our FAQ: <em>How many truck drivers will be needed in Canada and what does the future look like?</em></li>
<li>Remember that while a place like Yukon has good job prospects, it’s very expensive to live in – given how expensive it is to transport goods up to the Northwest of Canada – so make sure your pay is high enough to make it worth it.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Trucking jobs with Walmart and other retailers</h3>
<p>Walmart is definitely a place to look for <a href="https://careers.walmart.ca/category/drivers-jobs/4853/8269664/1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">truck driving jobs</a>. They tend to hire on a fairly continual basis and just a quick google search will throw up a few Walmart trucker ads from across the country. You can also work for other major retailers but remember you may need a qualification like an airbrake endorsement. Decide if you want long-haul or short-haul routes as well, because you will need to be more qualified (Class 1/A license for example) to do the long-haul routes.</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><b>Truck Drivers in Canada &#8211; Table of Contents</b></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/">How to become a truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/">How to become a truck driver in Canada for <span style="color: #ff0000;">foreigners</span>?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/">How to find a good truck driving school in Canada?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/">Truck drivers pay in Canada</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/">Owner-operator truck drivers&#8217; salary and bonuses</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/">How to move to USA as a Canadian truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/">Truck Driver with Criminal record</a></h3>
<p><div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full" id="wpforms-3069"><form id="wpforms-form-3069" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3069" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="e3c6881b53bf701fc131d3fe933d94ab"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3069-field_0-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="0"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_0">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_0" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][0]" placeholder="Name" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_1">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3069-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" placeholder="Email" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_4-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-number" data-field-id="4"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3069-field_4">Phone number</label><input type="number" pattern="\d*" id="wpforms-3069-field_4" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][4]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_2-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="2"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_2">Questions <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><textarea id="wpforms-3069-field_2" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][2]" placeholder="Questions" required></textarea></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-captcha" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_3">Captcha <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label>			<div class="wpforms-captcha-math">
				<span class="wpforms-captcha-equation">
											<span class="n1"></span>
						<span class="cal"></span>
						<span class="n2"></span>
											<span class="e">=</span>
				</span>
				<input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_3" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required a" data-rule-wpf-captcha="math" name="wpforms[fields][3][a]" required>				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][cal]" class="cal">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n2]" class="n2">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n1]" class="n1">
			</div>
			</div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3069"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="15"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3069" class="wpforms-submit button button-round button-bg-red" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Truck Driver pay in Canada</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Allard John Keeley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 21 Nov 2022 18:20:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Truck Driver pay in Canada]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=8881</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In Canada, time is money, and truck drivers know that more than anyone else. They sometimes get paid by the hour, although companies will also pay by the kilometer. Some companies even pay a combination of hourly rates and payments based on kilometers travelled. In many surveys of trucker salaries in Canada, the amounts are...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In Canada, time is money, and truck drivers know that more than anyone else. They sometimes get paid by the hour, although companies will also pay by the kilometer. Some companies even pay a combination of hourly rates and payments based on kilometers travelled. In many surveys of trucker salaries in Canada, the amounts are usually given on an hourly basis. The average across the country is around CDN$ 25 an hour, but you’ll get a lot of variation depending on where you work, whom you work for, and your experience. As far as the difference between getting paid by the hour or by the kilometer, see our section: <em>Urban versus Rural jobs</em>, as well as our section on Owner-Operators. You’ll find both below our regional breakdown of hourly salaries.</p>
<p>According to the website <a href="https://ca.indeed.com/career/truck-driver/salaries" target="_blank" rel="noopener">indeed.com</a> here are the <strong><em>top 10-paying </em></strong>Trucking/Transport companies in Canada:</p>
<ul>
<li>RWR Trucking Inc. &#8211; Environmental Decontamination &amp; Excavation &#8211; <strong>$40.12</strong> an hour</li>
<li>Triple Eight Transport – Controlled-temp supply chain and cross-border trucking &#8211; <strong>$35.52</strong></li>
<li>Bulldog Energy Group – Western Canada based, operates in the Energy sector &#8211; <strong>$34.60</strong></li>
<li>Pride Group Logistics – Transport &amp; Logistics, based in Mississauga, ON &#8211; <strong>$34.55</strong></li>
<li>Sanjel Energy Services – Energy, Mining &amp; Utilities, based in Calgary &#8211; <strong>$32.95</strong></li>
<li>Parkland Corporation – Energy, Mining &amp; Utilities, also in Calgary &#8211; <strong>$32.59</strong></li>
<li>Armstrong Top Pack Ltd. &#8211; Food &amp; Beverage, based in Ontario &#8211; <strong>$31.57</strong></li>
<li>The Miller Group – Construction in Canada &amp; USA, based in Markham, ON &#8211; <strong>$31.42</strong></li>
<li>Arrow Transportation Systems Inc. &#8211; Transport &amp; Logistics, based in Kamloops, BC &#8211; <strong>$31.36</strong></li>
<li>Caron Transportation Systems – Transport &amp; Logistics, based in Alberta &#8211; <strong>$31.80</strong></li>
</ul>
<h2>Pay for Truck Drivers by Province</h2>
<p><strong>BC:</strong> Annual trucking salaries in the Vancouver area are just under $58,000 a year and range between 40 up to 80 thousand annually. According to <a href="https://www.glassdoor.ca/Salaries/truck-driver-salary-SRCH_KO0,12.htm" target="_blank" rel="noopener">glassdoor</a>, hourly rates vary quite a bit – from under $20 an hour up to close to $40 an hour depending on whom you work for and your experience. However, most companies in the province offer rates from about $25 to around $35.</p>
<p><strong>Alberta:</strong> The hourly rates are very similar to those in BC, ranging from the mid-20-dollar range per hour up to $35 or $36 per hour. For the really juicy payday, you should look into fuel truck drivers who can earn well over $100K annually.</p>
<p><strong>Saskatchewan:</strong> In this prairie province, the average base salary – according to indeed.com &#8211; is just under $28 which is above the national average. Of course, that’s also true of average hourly salaries in BC and Alberta, where you will often see salaries above $30 an hour.</p>
<p><strong>Manitoba: </strong>Surprisingly, given the numbers in Saskatchewan and Alberta, average wages in Manitoba – again, according to indeed.com &#8211; are significantly lower at just under $23 per hour. It seems that the further north in the province you go, the lower the wages. For example, in Brandon which is tucked into the southwest corner of the province near the border with Saskatchewan, average rates are over $26 an hour, while way up north in Thompson, you get under $24 an hour. And in Winnipeg, rates are surprisingly low at just over $22 an hour.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-8937" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/trucking-ads-on-Immigroup-500x272.jpg" alt="ad" width="500" height="272" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/trucking-ads-on-Immigroup-500x272.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/trucking-ads-on-Immigroup.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></p>
<p><strong>Ontario:</strong> In Canada’s largest province, you can expect lots of competition as well as lots of demand for drivers, which tends to keep rates within a fairly narrow band. The average base salary is a little over $24 – according to indeed.com &#8211; and local rates range from under $24 in London, ON, to nearly $26 in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Guelph" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Guelph</a>. That’s not much difference for 2 cities located about an hour’s drive from each other but remember that Guelph is more of an agricultural centre than London, so that might create additional demand for truck drivers.</p>
<p><strong>Quebec: </strong>Truck driving pays less in Quebec than in Ontario or the western provinces. While average rates are similar to Ontario at just over $24, and rates in the city of Montreal come in at over $24 per hour, rates in the greater Montreal area suck, to put it bluntly. In <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dorval" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Dorval</a> (where Montreal’s airport is located, so it’s a transportation hub) you get an average of under $22 an hour and in <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Laval,_Quebec" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Laval</a> (a suburb just to the north of the city) you get paid an average of just under $23 an hour. <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gatineau" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Gatineau</a> – just across the river from Ottawa – is better at $25. But Pointe-Claire at the western edge of the island of Montreal, pays an average of just over $21.50, and heading south and east towards Quebec’s Eastern townships and the border with New York state and Vermont, you have meagre wages of just over $18.50 in Sain-Jean-Sur-Richelieu.</p>
<p><strong>New Brunswick:</strong> We’re now in the Maritimes, so the cost of living – especially housing – is a little lower and salaries tend to reflect that. In New Brunswick, the average rate is just under $22 an hour. In the <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Woodstock,_New_Brunswick" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Woodstock area</a> – a transportation hub near the border with Maine and connections with Interstate 95 in the US and the <a href="https://www.google.ca/search?q=transcanada+highway+map&amp;newwindow=1&amp;sxsrf=ALiCzsZp0VwjJnb72vYW8ZWDQ8_2NCi8ow%3A1669081894484&amp;ei=Jit8Y5CMHZ2dptQP77edsAc&amp;oq=TransCanada+hig&amp;gs_lcp=Cgxnd3Mtd2l6LXNlcnAQARgCMgoIABCABBCHAhAUMgUIABCABDIFCAAQgAQyBQgAEIAEMgUIABCABDIHCAAQgAQQCjIFCAAQgAQyBwgAEIAEEAoyBQgAEIAEMgUIABCABDoECCMQJzoKCC4QxwEQ0QMQQzoKCAAQsQMQgwEQQzoQCC4QsQMQgwEQxwEQ0QMQQzoECAAQQzoRCC4QgAQQsQMQgwEQxwEQ0QM6DgguELEDEIMBEMcBENEDOgQILhBDOgUIABCRAjoLCC4QsQMQgwEQkQI6BwguENQCEEM6CwgAEIAEELEDEIMBOg0ILhCABBCHAhDUAhAUOg0ILhCxAxDHARDRAxBDOhMILhCABBCHAhCxAxDHARDRAxAUOhYILhCABBCHAhCxAxDHARDRAxDUAhAUOhAIABCABBCHAhCxAxCDARAUOggIABCABBCxAzoRCC4QxwEQ1AIQsQMQ0QMQgAQ6CwguEIAEEMcBEK8BOhAILhCABBCHAhDHARCvARAUOg4ILhCABBDHARDRAxDUAkoECEEYAEoECEYYAFAAWMccYOcwaABwAXgAgAHEAYgB1g2SAQM3LjiYAQCgAQHAAQE&amp;sclient=gws-wiz-serp" target="_blank" rel="noopener">TransCanada highway</a> – you have some wages reported at nearly $40 at indeed.com, but those are outliers for drivers with international experience that are eligible to drive in the USA. Most wages are around $22 or even just under $20.</p>
<p><strong>Nova Scotia:</strong> Average wages are a little lower compared to New Brunswick with the average at under $20 and most salaries around $21. For example, in Halifax, Sydney, and <a href="https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Truro,_Nova_Scotia" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Truro</a>, wages are a little under $21.50.</p>
<p><strong>PEI:</strong> Very similar to Nova Scotia, with the average under $22 and some locales paying under $20 per hour.</p>
<p><strong>Newfoundland &amp; Labrador:</strong> Ditto Newfoundland, with hourly wages at around $22 in Saint John’s and around or under $20 in the rest of the province.</p>
<p><strong>Yukon:</strong> Even though the average hourly rate is around $30, remember that living in Yukon (and the NTW, as well as Nunavut) is quite expensive. You have to pay truck drivers to transport goods in 30° to 40° below zero temperatures in winter across long, sparsely populated distances. So your net savings might not be that different from, say, Alberta, but there’s no doubt that there’s a demand for truckers in the far North and Northwest.</p>
<p><strong>Northwest Territories: </strong>Average wages are just under $30, so it’s basically identical to Yukon, but the same observation about working conditions and cost-of-living as in Yukon holds true here as well.</p>
<p><strong>Nunavut:</strong> Can you go further north than Yukon? Yes, you can. Head to Nunavut! Unfortunately, the demand for truckers is slightly less, given the very sparse population in this large, arctic territory, and as a result, the average rate is a little lower at about $27.50. Life is cold and expensive in Nunavut, but it can be a place to gain valuable experience as a long-haul driver. Do you dare?</p>
<h3>By Experience</h3>
<p>Obviously, your salary goes up with experience. But there’s something even more important. You won’t even get offered many types of trucking jobs – especially long-haul and HAZMAT jobs, if you don’t have at least several years of experience as a truck driver. Here’s what <a href="https://www.jobbank.gc.ca/jobsearch/jobsearch?searchstring=Truck+driver&amp;locationstring=&amp;sort=M" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Canada’s Job Bank notes</a>:</p>
<h4 style="text-align: center;"><em>&#8220;Employers in this industry seldom recruit youths under the age of 25 owing to the experience requirements and higher insurance expenses.&#8221;</em></h4>
<p>So, the question is, how do you gain the experience needed to get a decent trucking job? For that answer, see our chapter: <em>How to Become a Truck Driver?</em> Scroll down to the FAQ section there to see about gaining your first experience with some easier-to-get jobs.</p>
<h2>FAQ</h2>
<h3>Truck loans and truck title loans in Canada.</h3>
<ul>
<li>Truck Title Loan: No one wants to face a cash crunch, but it does happen from time to time, especially if you’re an owner-operator who has to find their own jobs. A truck title loan is a short-term (3 months to 3 years to pay back) loan with your truck used as collateral. Think carefully before getting one because you’re taking a mortgage out on your rig, and you need to be very confident that you’ll get enough work to pay the loan off, or the finance company could take ownership of your rig.</li>
<li>Truck loans in general: this can involve anything from a smaller credit to help pay for needed repairs to your vehicle to getting a loan to purchase your truck (which will generally involve a down payment just like a mortgage on a house). It can also involve refinancing an existing loan on your truck, always an option if you can find a better rate from another finance company.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Large vs. small trucking companies in Canada.</h3>
<p>It really depends on what type of driving you’re planning on doing. If you’re focused on driving long-haul jobs, then you probably should consider a larger company that offers you more choices with more routes to choose from. This means you’ll need a Class 1 (Class A in Ontario) license to operate tractor trailer rigs.</p>
<p>If you’re more interested in urban shorter-haul jobs where you go back home every night, then some smaller companies located in your preferred area might work for you. However, remember that transport operators need a lot of equipment and overhead, something smaller companies with only a truck or two can’t always offer you.</p>
<p>If, on the other hand, you’re an owner-operator then you choose what company to work for, depending on their rates and the type of work.</p>
<p>Whatever company – large, mid-sized, or small – you choose, remember to ask:</p>
<ul>
<li>Do they offer Less-than-truckload (LTL)? If you’re getting paid by the percentage, these aren’t the best-paying jobs, but they might be useful when you need to pick up some extra work any given month.</li>
<li>Do they offer LCV (Long Combination Vehicles) jobs? If they do, you’ll definitely need a Class 1/A license and the experience to handle these over-sized rigs. But the pay should be better than average.</li>
<li>Do they run singles and teams? In other words, are you comfortable working in a 2-driver team? Or do you prefer to do the jobs on your own?</li>
<li>Do they run flat-bed trucks, or temperature-controlled trucks? That will be determined by what type of loads they tend to carry. Remember to find out if you’ll need an airbrakes endorsement on your license (usually indicated by a Z).</li>
<li>Do they pay by the mile/kilometer or by the hour or both?</li>
</ul>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<h3 style="text-align: center;"><b>Truck Drivers in Canada &#8211; Table of Contents</b></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/">How to become a truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/">How to become a truck driver in Canada for <span style="color: #ff0000;">foreigners</span>?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/">How to find a good truck driving school in Canada?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/">Urban vs. Rural jobs</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/">Owner-operator truck drivers&#8217; salary and bonuses</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/">How to move to USA as a Canadian truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/">Truck Driver with Criminal record</a></h3>
<p><div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full" id="wpforms-3069"><form id="wpforms-form-3069" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3069" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="e3c6881b53bf701fc131d3fe933d94ab"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3069-field_0-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="0"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_0">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_0" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][0]" placeholder="Name" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_1">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3069-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" placeholder="Email" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_4-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-number" data-field-id="4"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3069-field_4">Phone number</label><input type="number" pattern="\d*" id="wpforms-3069-field_4" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][4]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_2-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="2"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_2">Questions <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><textarea id="wpforms-3069-field_2" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][2]" placeholder="Questions" required></textarea></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-captcha" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_3">Captcha <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label>			<div class="wpforms-captcha-math">
				<span class="wpforms-captcha-equation">
											<span class="n1"></span>
						<span class="cal"></span>
						<span class="n2"></span>
											<span class="e">=</span>
				</span>
				<input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_3" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required a" data-rule-wpf-captcha="math" name="wpforms[fields][3][a]" required>				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][cal]" class="cal">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n2]" class="n2">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n1]" class="n1">
			</div>
			</div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3069"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="15"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3069" class="wpforms-submit button button-round button-bg-red" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>7</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How to become a truck driver in Canada</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/#comments</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Allard John Keeley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sun, 20 Nov 2022 23:05:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Do-it-yourself courses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[General Interest]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Truck Driver jobs]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=8868</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Read our step-by-step guide to getting a job as a truck driver, either as someone already living in Canada or a foreigner thinking of moving here. What you need to keep in mind is that driving a truck is often a full-time-plus job and is done mostly for the money. It’s not usually about the...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Read our <strong>step-by-step guide</strong> to getting a job as a truck driver, either as someone already living in Canada or a foreigner thinking of moving here. What you need to keep in mind is that driving a truck is often a full-time-plus job and is done mostly for the money. It’s not usually about the freedom of the road because you’re tied to a tight schedule and are always trying to make sure you keep up with your deliveries.</p>
<p>It might be your childhood dream job, but the reality is a little different. Do you have what it takes to be a trucker in Canada? Keep reading to get some answers because one thing is certain: Canada is going to need thousands of new truck drivers over the coming years. For example, <a href="https://truckinghr.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/THRC-Labour-Market-Information-Report_English-version.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Road Ahead: Addressing Canada’s Trucking and Logistics Industry Labour Shortages</a>, a report based on research by the Conference Board of Canada, suggests at least 25,000 vacancies that will need to be filled over the next few years.</p>
<p>First off, let&#8217;s look at the Pros vs. Cons of this industry:</p>
<p>Pros</p>
<ul>
<li>Good pay</li>
<li>Get to see most of the country and much of the US</li>
<li>High demand for new drivers over the next decade</li>
<li>Can pick and choose what work you do – although this will take some experience before you can pick and choose your jobs.</li>
</ul>
<p>Cons</p>
<ul>
<li>Long hours</li>
<li>Away from home for up to weeks at a time</li>
<li>Difficult driving conditions</li>
<li>Responsibilities of paying for that big rig you own and covering your expenses – if you’re an owner-operator</li>
</ul>
<h2 style="text-align: center;"><b>Truck Drivers in Canada &#8211; Table of Contents</b></h2>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="#How to become a truck driver in Canada">How to become a truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada-for-foreigners/">How to become a truck driver in Canada for <span style="color: #ff0000;">foreigners</span>?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driving-schools-in-canada/">How to find a good truck driving school in Canada?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-pay-in-canada/">Truck drivers pay in Canada</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/urban-versus-rural-jobs-for-truck-drivers-in-canada/">Urban vs. Rural jobs</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/owner-operator-truck-drivers-salary-in-canada/">Owner-operator truck drivers&#8217; salary and bonuses</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-move-to-usa-as-a-canadian-truck-driver/">How to move to USA as a Canadian truck driver?</a></h3>
<h3>Chapter: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/truck-driver-with-criminal-record/">Truck Driver with Criminal record</a></h3>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Tip</span>: <a href="#definitions">Click here</a> for <strong>definitions</strong> to better understand this guide</p>
<h2 id="How to become a truck driver in Canada">How to become a truck driver in Canada?</h2>
<h3><strong>Basic requirements</strong></h3>
<p>You’ll need to have finished high school in most cases, and the better companies require you to have taken a driver training course at a vocational school or community college. You’ll also need the following commercial driving licenses – depending on what type of truck you’ll be driving:</p>
<ul>
<li>Class 3 License or D License if you’re driving straight-body trucks</li>
<li>Class 1 License or A License if you’re driving tractor trailers.</li>
<li>If you’re going to be transporting hazardous materials or dangerous goods, then you’ll need a TDG (Transportation of Dangerous Goods) certification.</li>
<li>If you’re going to be operating trucks with airbrakes, then you’ll need what is called an Airbrake Endorsement (identified by the code Z)</li>
</ul>
<p>Tip: the more difficult the licensing, the more money you will earn. Truck drivers overlook this. When you can get obscure credentials or experience, you will not only get paid more but also give yourself a significant advantage when it comes to job security.</p>
<h3>Step 1: Go back to school</h3>
<p>A <a href="https://humber.ca/education-training-solutions/transportation-training.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">truck-driving course</a> generally lasts around 3 months and is taught both at private vocational schools and at community colleges. Scroll down to our FAQ section below for more information. Remember, you generally need to take this type of course <em>before</em> applying for your commercial driving license.</p>
<h3>Step 2: Get your commercial license</h3>
<p>Do you have a driver’s license? If you have a general driver’s license – <a href="https://www.fmcsa.dot.gov/sites/fmcsa.dot.gov/files/docs/Canadian%20Driver&#039;s%20Licence%20Reference%20Guide%20Revised%202015.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">for example</a>: Class 5 &amp; 7 in BC or Class G in Ontario – then you’ll need to upgrade to a commercial driver’s license that specifically allows you to drive trucks and especially tractor trailer trucks. Each province handles driver’s licenses and has different classification systems. The higher the level of the license, the longer it will take, including examinations and experience on the road. This is because provincial licensing systems are graduated, with drivers moving up from one level to the next as they become qualified.</p>
<ul>
<li>BC: Class 1 is the highest level which allows you to drive any vehicle except a motorcycle. Class 2 also includes most trucks but not ones with air brakes.</li>
<li>Alberta: Class 1 driver’s licenses are similar to those in BC while Class 3 licenses allow you to drive smaller trucks (no more than 3 axles).</li>
<li>Saskatchewan: Just about identical to Alberta. You’ll need a Class 1 license to drive any kind of truck, while Class 3 lets you drive smaller trucks (not tractor trailers).</li>
<li>Manitoba: Again, like it’s two Prairie neighbours, you’ll want a Class 1 license for the largest semis &#8211; like an 18 wheeler &#8211; and a Class 3 for smaller trucks.</li>
<li>Ontario: Here Class A is equivalent to Class 1 out west, while Class D allows you to drive smaller trucks.</li>
<li>Quebec: Licenses are similar to the Western provinces. Class 1 for any kind of truck and Class 3 for smaller trucks.</li>
<li>New Brunswick: Similar to Quebec and the Western Provinces with Class 1 getting you into any kind of rig while Class 3 allows you to drive smaller trucks.</li>
<li>Nova Scotia: Same as New Brunswick, Quebec, and the West. Class 1 for all trucks, Class 3 for slightly smaller trucks.</li>
<li>Newfoundland &amp; Labrador: Same again, with Class 1 and Class 3, but remember to get endorsements on your license to drive certain types of trucks. This may apply in other provinces as well.</li>
<li>Yukon &amp; NWT? Class 1 and Class 3.</li>
</ul>
<p><img decoding="async" class="alignnone size-medium wp-image-8937" src="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/trucking-ads-on-Immigroup-500x272.jpg" alt="ad" width="500" height="272" srcset="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/trucking-ads-on-Immigroup-500x272.jpg 500w, https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/trucking-ads-on-Immigroup.jpg 750w" sizes="(max-width: 500px) 100vw, 500px" /></p>
<h3>Step 3: Start small</h3>
<p>You need to start gaining experience, so you generally have to start driving smaller delivery trucks or even start by driving a tow truck. It may not be your dream trucking job, but it will start to build your resume towards eventually getting into a full-size rig with a truck trailer attached. Some of these jobs won’t require a Class 1 or A license, but make sure you have the required license before you start your first trucking job. Unfortunately, a few operators may not even ask to see your license before sending you off to work, but this is rare and to be avoided.</p>
<h2 style="text-align: center;">FAQ</h2>
<h3>How to get a job as a truck driver with no experience?</h3>
<p>Start with something like a tow-truck job. They’re hiring right now with no experience necessary. You’ll basically be driving a glorified pickup truck, but you will have to deal with tricky traffic and weather conditions, not to mention vehicles that can be hard to tow. While you’re doing that you should be saving up for your driver training course which you’ll need before you can apply for a commercial driving license (Class 1/A in Ontario or Class 3/D in Ontario). You will need a general driving license before you can get your commercial license. So make sure you have your general driving license. If you&#8217;re from abroad and driving on your foreign license, make sure you get your general driver&#8217;s license before your international permit runs out.</p>
<h3>Expectations as a truck driver in Canada. The reality</h3>
<p>You will likely start your career driving something like a tow truck or small delivery truck and work your way towards a Class 1/A license, gaining the experience you need, one job at a time. As you work your way up towards a Class 1/A commercial license, remember to get the training and endorsements for things like airbrakes and hazardous materials in order to be able to drive specialty loads that pay better.</p>
<p>To earn the big bucks, whether working as a driver for a transport company or as an owner-operator subcontracting jobs, you will have to put in all those days and nights on the road. Your truck will become your second home and you’ll be driving in all sorts of weather conditions – from heat waves in August to freezing rain and icy roads in winter, to 40 below zero hauling loads to places like Whitehorse in the Yukon.</p>
<h3>Automation in the trucking industry, what does the future hold?</h3>
<p>They say it’s all about increasing safety and making your job as a truck driver easier to do. It’s reasonable to ask, however, if there’s also the intent to replace drivers with autonomous vehicles. Let’s start with that question.</p>
<p>To make autonomous (driverless) vehicles a reality, it will require enormous expenditure on advanced wireless technology like 5G cell networks that will need to cover every major highway and road in the country. Additionally, handing over control of a tractor-trailer rig to an algorithm will eventually happen but right now it&#8217;s just too risky. However, big changes are happening and will be coming in the future.</p>
<p>What is happening is that some companies like Uber Freight are developing the idea of using a hub-to-hub network of autonomous semitrailers covering the city-to-city routes, working in a hybrid system with traditional truck drivers handling the so-called first and last mile of the payload’s journey. Whether this plan (and right now it’s just a plan) turns out to be economically feasible, or politically feasible, remains to be seen. It’s also a fair question to ask if it will be technologically feasible as well.</p>
<p>In other words, for at least the next generation or so, lots of truck drivers will definitely be needed.</p>
<p>Remember, automation is not exactly the same as autonomous/driverless vehicles. Cars and trucks have been using increasing amounts of automation over the last couple of decades. So, here’s a useful scale to think about the level of automation in a truck. It’s being used a lot lately and you may have read about it. It goes like this:</p>
<ul>
<li>Level 0: no automation in the truck with a fully human-operated vehicle. However, it can include things like stability control, blind-spot warnings and braking assistance.</li>
<li>Level 1: includes at least 1 driver-support system; either steering assistance or assistance with accelerating and braking, but not both. So, you might get lane-centering assistance but need to be ready to take control at any time.</li>
<li>Level 2: you guessed it, includes both automatic braking, as well as lane changing and self-parking. This is partial automation with these systems taking over at certain times, but drivers must remain alert in order to handle situations at all times.</li>
<li>Level 3: the automation systems make decisions based on conditions on the road. This includes changing lanes and accelerating around other vehicles, leaving the driver to do other activities. However, drivers need to be ready to intervene if necessary.</li>
<li>Level 4: most systems are automated and are only constrained by severe weather or say crossing a border into another country, state, province, or territory where the regulations might change. They normally operate without human interaction.</li>
<li>Level 5: no weather limits nor any geographic limits. The driver inputs the destination and then engages in other activity. The truck drives itself.</li>
</ul>
<p>So, referring back to Uber Freight’s plan for hub-to-hub hybrid networks, the city-to-city routes would have level 4 or 5 automation (the only levels that are truly driverless), while the first and last mile would likely have level 2 or possibly level 3 automation. Time will tell if this is what the future holds for trucking.</p>
<h3>How many truck drivers will be needed in Canada, and what does the future look like</h3>
<p>According to <a href="https://www.jobbank.gc.ca/marketreport/outlook-occupation/10552/ca" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Canada Job Bank’s 2018 report</a>, the average age of a truck operator was around 42 while the average retirement age was estimated at around 66 years old. Their outlook for demand for truck drivers was neutral to positive with the following regional breakdowns:</p>
<ul>
<li>Very good prospects for truck drivers:
<ul>
<li>Manitoba</li>
<li>PEI</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Good prospects for truck drivers:
<ul>
<li>Alberta</li>
<li>Saskatchewan</li>
<li>Ontario</li>
<li>Maritimes – except Newfoundland &amp; Labrador and PEI</li>
<li>Yukon &amp; Northwest Territories</li>
</ul>
</li>
<li>Moderate prospects for truck drivers:
<ul>
<li>BC</li>
<li>Quebec</li>
<li>Newfoundland &amp; Labrador</li>
<li>Nunavut</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p><a href="https://www.trucknews.com/transportation/canada-short-25000-truck-drivers-by-2023-report/1003137725/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Trucking HR Canada with research by The Conference Board of Canada</a> has a more optimistic outlook in their 2020 report <a href="https://truckinghr.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/03/THRC-Labour-Market-Information-Report_English-version.pdf" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Road Ahead: Addressing Canada’s Trucking and Logistics Industry Labour Shortages</a>. The report shows over 300,000 drivers currently working in Canada with around 15,000 current vacancies which are expected to rapidly increase to 25,000 vacancies, as an aging workforce of drivers retires in increasing numbers.</p>
<p><a href="https://cantruck.ca/new-statscan-data-highlights-demographic-crisis-underpinning-truck-driver-shortage/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Other estimates</a> call for over 50,000 job vacancies within the next couple of years, but these estimates may be just a little too optimistic.</p>
<h3>Truck driving interview questions you need to have the answer for</h3>
<p>Here are some questions you really should have the answer to if you want to get hired as a truck driver:</p>
<ul>
<li>Know the many types of trucks – Dry Box Van, Dry Bulk, Refridgerated, Flat Bed, Cabover versus Conventional etc. And know which type of truck you’re qualified to drive and have experience with.</li>
<li>When they ask you what endorsements you have, they’re NOT asking you if someone’s sponsoring you but rather if you’re qualified to drive a truck with air brakes, for example.</li>
<li>When they ask you what lanes you’ve driven, DON’T say the fast lane. They’re asking you about dedicated routes on major highways, usually between major urban centers and transport hubs that transport companies use on a regular basis.</li>
<li>Know what paperwork you need to drive in the US – DOT cards for example.</li>
<li>If you’ve had a DUI, you’d better be able to talk about your Record of Suspension and hopefully your Entry Waiver. See our FAQ on DUIs in our chapter: Truck driver with criminal record.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Signs you are dealing with a bad trucking business.</h3>
<ul>
<li>They target new arrivals with little to no experience, including international students.</li>
<li>They demand you pay them an upfront fee, just to work for them.</li>
<li>They’re run from a private home in the suburbs.</li>
<li>They don’t give you any training.</li>
<li>They send out completely inexperienced drivers with heavy loads for which they have no experience handling.</li>
<li>They force international students to work over their 20-hour-a-week limit and don’t pay them the overtime, knowing full well the student won’t want to declare those extra hours to avoid getting in trouble with immigration authorities.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Signs you are dealing with a great trucking business.</h3>
<ul>
<li>They tell you you’re too young and you need to get more experience before you can work for them.</li>
<li>They never ask for an upfront fee to get a job.</li>
<li>They emphasize training for their drivers.</li>
</ul>
<h3>Is the trucking industry in Canada regulated?</h3>
<p>Although there was some deregulation of the industry in the 1980s, it still requires a fair deal of paperwork to set up a trucking company in Canada. The deregulation in the 80s was apprently opposed by major unions like Teamsters Canada. See our next FAQ just below: <em>Does the trucking industry have a union?</em> As well, check out our FAQ titled: <em>What does it take to own your own Truck Driver Business in Canada?</em> You&#8217;ll find it in our chapter on owner operators. It&#8217;ll give you an idea of some of the permits and licenses drivers and owners need in order to do business and to drive commercially in Canada.</p>
<h3>Does the trucking industry have a union?</h3>
<p>There are a few major unions in Canada: Teamsters Canada, for example, who have around 15,000 members. With over 300,000 truck drivers in Canada that means that a significant percentage of truck drivers are not unionized. As well, there’s the industry group the Canadian Trucking Alliance, but this represents transport companies and some owner-operators and is not a union. Back in 2006, Statistics Canada estimated that about 25% of truckers were unionized. Nowadays that’s estimated to have fallen to around 20%. You should also know that Teamsters Canada is generally opposed to bringing in foreign truck drivers and advocates instead for higher salaries and better job security to attract Canadians to the industry.</p>
<h3>What is the best resource for Truck Drivers in Canada? (Magazines, forum communities, free support etc.)</h3>
<p><strong>It depends. Use plenty of resources:</strong></p>
<p>Looking for truck driving jobs</p>
<ul>
<li>Job Bank Canada</li>
<li>Indeed.ca</li>
<li>Major retailers like Walmart</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Develop contacts in your industry</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Shippers</li>
<li>Transport Company officials</li>
<li>Mechanics – don&#8217;t underestimate the importance of a good mechanic for your truck!</li>
<li>Other truck drivers with lots of experience</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Online forums</strong></p>
<ul>
<li>Reddit Truckers at <a href="https://www.reddit.com/r/Truckers/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.reddit.com/r/Truckers/</a></li>
<li>Canada’s trucking forum at Facebook <a href="https://www.facebook.com/canadastruckingforum/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.facebook.com/canadastruckingforum/</a></li>
<li>Canadian Truck Drivers Forum also at Facebook <a href="https://www.facebook.com/CanadianTruckDriversForum/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.facebook.com/CanadianTruckDriversForum/</a></li>
<li>Canadian Truckers Forum at trucker’s report <a href="https://www.thetruckersreport.com/truckingindustryforum/forums/canadian-truckers-forum.329/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.thetruckersreport.com/truckingindustryforum/forums/canadian-truckers-forum.329/</a></li>
<li>Canadian forum at truckdiver.com <a href="https://www.truckdriver.com/trucker-forums/forum/9-canadian/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.truckdriver.com/trucker-forums/forum/9-canadian/</a></li>
<li>For US/Canadian forums try <a href="https://www.roadtrucker.com/forum/forumdisplay.php?55-Canadian-Truckers" target="_blank" rel="noopener">https://www.roadtrucker.com/forum/forumdisplay.php?55-Canadian-Truckers</a></li>
</ul>
<h2 id="definitions">Definitions to help you understand this guide</h2>
<ul>
<li><strong>Hazmat:</strong> Hazardous Material – usually require a certification or endorsement to transport</li>
<li><strong>Long-Haul:</strong> Transporting goods between cities – Also called Over-the-road or OTR</li>
<li><strong>Short-Haul:</strong> Transporting goods within an urban area</li>
<li><strong>Airbrake endorsement</strong>: marked by a Z on your Class 1 license showing you’re qualified to operate a truck equipped with airbrakes</li>
<li><strong>Lane</strong>: a route between cities typically over a highway that transport companies use as a dedicated corridor to move goods back and forth.</li>
<li><strong>Class 1/A in Ontario and the US license</strong>: Qualified to drive any type of truck</li>
<li><strong>Class 3/D in Ontario and the Us license</strong>: Qualified to drive smaller straight-body trucks but not large tractor trailers</li>
<li><strong>LTL</strong>: Less than Truckload – jobs involving smaller loads that don’t fill-up your truck but at least bring in some revenue</li>
<li><strong>Truck Title Loans</strong>: a loan that uses your truck as collateral. Used by owner-operators, but involves the risk of the finance company taking possession of your truck.</li>
<li><strong>Factoring</strong>: companies that collect your bills for you which means you get paid quicker but have to pay a percentage of your revenues to the company that provides factoring services</li>
<li><strong>ELD</strong>: Electronic Logging Device on commercial trucks used to keep HOS – Hours of Service see next definition.</li>
<li><strong>Hours of Service (HOS)</strong>: maximum time a trucker can be on duty without a rest, including driving time.</li>
<li><strong>FMCSA</strong>: Federal Motor Carrier Safety Administration – a US Department of Transport (DOT) agency in charge of safety regulations. Canadian standards generally are very similar to those set by FMCSA and the DOT in the US.</li>
<li><strong>DOT</strong>: Department of Transport – US government agency in charge of supervising and regulating the transportation industry. Canadian standards and regulations generally are quite similar to those issued by DOT and FMCSA.</li>
</ul>
<p><div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full" id="wpforms-3069"><form id="wpforms-form-3069" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3069" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="e3c6881b53bf701fc131d3fe933d94ab"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3069-field_0-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="0"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_0">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_0" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][0]" placeholder="Name" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_1">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3069-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" placeholder="Email" required></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_4-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-number" data-field-id="4"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3069-field_4">Phone number</label><input type="number" pattern="\d*" id="wpforms-3069-field_4" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][4]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_2-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="2"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_2">Questions <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><textarea id="wpforms-3069-field_2" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][2]" placeholder="Questions" required></textarea></div><div id="wpforms-3069-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-captcha" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label wpforms-label-hide" for="wpforms-3069-field_3">Captcha <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label>			<div class="wpforms-captcha-math">
				<span class="wpforms-captcha-equation">
											<span class="n1"></span>
						<span class="cal"></span>
						<span class="n2"></span>
											<span class="e">=</span>
				</span>
				<input type="text" id="wpforms-3069-field_3" class="wpforms-field-medium wpforms-field-required a" data-rule-wpf-captcha="math" name="wpforms[fields][3][a]" required>				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][cal]" class="cal">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n2]" class="n2">
				<input type="hidden" name="wpforms[fields][3][n1]" class="n1">
			</div>
			</div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3069"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="15"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3069" class="wpforms-submit button button-round button-bg-red" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/how-to-become-a-truck-driver-in-canada/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>8</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Free Spousal Sponsorship Course</title>
		<link>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-course/</link>
					<comments>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-course/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Allard John Keeley]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 26 Sep 2022 19:36:36 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Do-it-yourself courses]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Articles]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Sponsorship]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Do-it-yourself and courses]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.immigroup.com/?p=8680</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Get Canadian PR For Your Spouse or Common Law Partner &#8211; Complete Guide Do it yourself course, in-depth tutorial, call it what you want, this step-by-step sponsorship course will be a god-send for most people that are lucky enough to find it on the web. Note: IRCC online application portal information coming soon&#8230; You may...]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h2>Get Canadian PR For Your Spouse or Common Law Partner &#8211; Complete Guide</h2>
<p>Do it yourself course, in-depth tutorial, call it what you want, this step-by-step sponsorship course will be a god-send for most people that are lucky enough to find it on the web.</p>
<p><strong>Note:</strong> IRCC online application portal information coming soon&#8230;</p>
<p>You may be tight on cash, or just up for the challenge. Whatever your reason is, <strong>by taking this course you are vastly improving the odds of an ‘approval’</strong>, speeding up the processing of your application, and saving thousands of dollars in legal fees.</p>
<p>Before you start let’s talk about it:</p>
<p><strong>If you are serious about putting together your spousal sponsorship application on your own, then this tutorial is exactly what you need</strong>. Step by step, in easy-to-digest chapters, we go through just about <strong>everything involved in successfully sponsoring a spouse or partner to come and live with you in Canada</strong>.</p>
<p>Do you have the focus, energy, and commitment to get it done?</p>
<p>Then let’s start!</p>
<p>This tutorial will take you step-by-step through the whole process:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>what kind of office supplies you’ll need </strong></li>
<li><strong>how to fill out each and every one of the multiple forms</strong> you often are required to submit in a sponsorship application</li>
<li><strong>each and every supporting document you may need</strong> – how and where to get them.</li>
</ul>
<p>Every day, we get to help overwhelmed <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/reviews/">clients</a> navigate the complicated immigration process. But for those who like to “do-it-yourself,” we’re happy to provide this free, clear, step-by-step article.</p>
<h2>Before you start &#8211; what you need</h2>
<p>To get an idea of what’s involved, start with a little reading assignment: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/family-sponsorship-application-document-checklist/">Go here to our article on family sponsorship documents to see all the forms and supporting documents you are required to submit for a sponsorship application</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Remember please</strong>, if you’re serious about this then the <strong>volume of documents and forms shouldn’t be seen as a burden but rather as a carefully laid out requirement</strong> that you fulfill one document and form at a time.</p>
<p>And speaking of time, you should calculate that <strong>spending around 2 hours carefully reviewing each step in our tutorial will save you much more time when you actually apply</strong>. If you put together a sponsorship application in a matter of <strong>a few days, then you have almost certainly forgotten key steps</strong> and/or supporting documents.</p>
<p>A successful sponsorship application can take weeks and even a month or two just to put together, depending on the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>How quickly you can gather your documents depends on knowing which documents you’ll need in the first place, and not forgetting key documents when you first apply. Nothing <strong>slows down an application like having to scurry around and get a document several months after you’ve applied</strong>.</li>
<li>How carefully and clearly you’ve filled in the forms – especially ones for family members (of your sponsored spouse/partner) who might not even be considering visiting in Canada. Mistaken or questionable information is seen by immigration officers as <strong>a warning flag which can result in requests for additional documents</strong> to clear up any mistakes you made by not paying attention to providing accurate information your sponsored spouse’s siblings for example.</li>
</ul>
<p>In other words, <strong>our aim is to help save you days and weeks of frustrating delays</strong> that sometimes stretch into <strong>months</strong>.</p>
<p><iframe title="How to do your own Spousal Sponsorship for free ? | Canadian Desi |" width="1200" height="675" src="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TQgVhnvu3DM?start=153&#038;feature=oembed" frameborder="0" allow="accelerometer; autoplay; clipboard-write; encrypted-media; gyroscope; picture-in-picture" allowfullscreen></iframe></p>
<h2>What do I need to submit a spousal sponsorship application?</h2>
<ul>
<li>All spousal sponsorship applications &#8211; You will need to go to IRCC&#8217;s web page &#8211; <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/services/application/application-forms-guides/guide-5289-sponsor-your-spouse-common-law-partner-conjugal-partner-dependent-child-complete-guide.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CLICK HERE </a>(further down on the page)</li>
<li>A colour <strong>printer/scanner</strong> for optimal images</li>
<li>High-quality <strong>paper</strong>, sticky notes, <strong>paper clips</strong> (<strong>do NOT staple items</strong> when preparing your application – <strong>use paper clips</strong>)</li>
<li>Software – <strong>Adobe Acrobat</strong> (latest version); photo-capture software.</li>
</ul>
<p>Remember to:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Make at least 2 copies of everything</strong> – one for you and one for IRCC.</li>
<li><a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/to-do-list/"><strong>Create a Word Document</strong> titled something like <em>Not Sure of This</em></a>. If you can’t find the answer to a question on<em>line after resea</em>rching for over 1 hour, make a note of it in this doc and then as you near the end of the process, you can refer back to this and see how to get help.</li>
</ul>
<p>The important thing is, <strong>don’t let the process get stuck on one item</strong>. Take note of the unresolved question, then leave it for later and move on. We have provided a helpful template for your to keep track of your questions:<br />
<div class="grid-x text-center align-center  grid-padding-x  grid-padding-y "><br />
<div class=" large-6 small-12 cell"><a class="button" href="https://www.immigroup.com/files/sponsorship-to-do-list-things-i-am-still-missing-in-my-sponsorship-application.docx">Sample Sponsorship To Do List (Word doc)</a></div><br />
<div class=" large-6 small-12 cell"><a class="button" href="https://www.immigroup.com/files/sponsorship-to-do-list-things-i-am-still-missing-in-my-sponsorship-application.pdf">Sample Sponsorship To Do List (PDF)</a></div><br />
</div></p>
<p>Once you have downloaded your To Do list, or made one yourself, move on to the next chapter:</p>
<p>We hope you found this content to be helpful.</p>
<p>At Immigroup we provide do-it-yourselfers with clear and accurate information. (For best results, we recommend using the government’s website in conjunction with our ours. <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/forum/index.php">For answers to specific question, please check out our forum</a>. Do these simple things and you’ll be far ahead of the pack!)</p>
<p><span style="color: #ff0000;">Tip:</span> Don&#8217;t close this page when completing this course. You will be jumping around on Immigroup&#8217;s website to different in-depth articles and this page going to be your only guide to what the next step is. If you lose or close this page, don&#8217;t worry just go to the homepage of Immigroup, select Research A Topic and under Sponsorship  category you will find this page.</p>
<h2>Spousal Sponsorship Course Steps &#8211; Table of Contents</h2>
<p>Step 1: Spousal Sponsorship Course – Before we start</p>
<p>Step 2: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/when-do-overseas-vs-inland-spousal-sponsorship-application/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">When to do Overseas vs. Inland Spousal Sponsorship Application</a></p>
<p>Step 3: <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/topics/online-applications-for-permanent-residence-pr/">Online Application vs. Paper Applications</a></p>
<p>Step 4: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-1344-sponsorship-agreement-undertaking/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Form IMM 1344 Application Sponsorship Agreement and Undertaking</a></p>
<p>Step 5: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-5532-relationship-information-sponsorship-evaluation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Form IMM 5532 Relationship Information and Sponsorship Evaluation</a></p>
<p>Step 6: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-0008-general-application/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IMM 0008 Generic Application form for Canada for Sponsored Spouse</a></p>
<p>Step 7: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-5669-schedule-background-declaration/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IMM 5669 Schedule A Background Declaration</a></p>
<p>Step 8: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-5645-imm-5406-family-information-form/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IMM 5645 / IMM 5406 Family Information Form </a></p>
<p>Step 9: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-5409-statutory-declaration-common-law-union/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IMM 5409 Statutory Declaration of Common-Law Union</a></p>
<p>Step 10: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/document-checklist-imm-5533-or-imm-5589-or-imm-5629/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">The Document Checklist IMM 5533 or IMM 5589 or IMM 5629</a></p>
<p>Step 11: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-5481-sponsorship-evaluation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IMM 5481 Sponsorship Evaluation</a></p>
<p>Step 12: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-1283-financial-evaluation/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IMM 1283 Financial Evaluation</a></p>
<p>Step 13: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-0008-general-application-imm-0008dep-additional-dependants-declaration/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">General Application Form IMM 0008 and IMM 0008DEP Additional Dependants Deliration</a></p>
<p>Step 14: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-country-specific-sponsorship-application-forms/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spousal Sponsorship Country Specific Sponsorship Application Forms</a></p>
<p>Step 15: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/imm-5476-use-representative/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">IMM 5476 Use of a Representative</a></p>
<p>Step 16: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/to-do-list/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">To Do List – Things you don’t have answer for</a></p>
<p>Step 17: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/marriage-certificates/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Marriage Certificates</a></p>
<p>Step 18: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/sponsors-support-documents-for-sponsorship/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Sponsor’s Supporting Documents for Sponsorship</a></p>
<p>Step 19: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/primary-applicants-supporting-documents-for-sponsorship/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Primary Applicant’s Supporting Documents for Sponsorship</a></p>
<p>Step 20: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-letter-how-ace-it/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spousal Sponsorship Letter – How to Ace it</a></p>
<p>Step 21: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-proof-communication/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spousal Sponsorship Proof of Communication</a></p>
<p>Step 22: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-proof-relationship-through-gifts-travel-and-support/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spousal Sponsorship Proof of Relationship through Gifts, Travel and Support</a></p>
<p>Step 23: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-photographs-help-prove-your-relationship/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spousal Sponsorship Photographs to help prove your relationship </a></p>
<p>Step 24: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-support-letters-friends-and-family/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spousal Sponsorship Support Letter from Friends and Family</a></p>
<p>Step 25: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/putting-your-sponsorship-application-together/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Putting Your Sponsorship Application Together</a></p>
<p>Step 26: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/summary-letter-example-canadian-immigration/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Summary Letter Example for Canadian Immigration</a></p>
<p>Step 27: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/paying-your-sponsorship-application-fees/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Paying Your Sponsorship Application Fees</a></p>
<p>Step 28: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/mailing-your-canadian-immigration-package/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Mailing in Your Canadian Immigration Package</a></p>
<p>Step 29: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/tracking-status-your-immigration-application/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Tracking the Status of Your Immigration Application</a></p>
<p>Step 30: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/ommunicating-ircc-about-your-immigration-application/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Communicating with IRCC About Your Immigration Application</a></p>
<p>Step 31: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/are-you-ready-your-sponsorship-interview/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Are you Ready for Your Sponsorship Interview?</a></p>
<p>Step 32: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/submitting-biometrics-your-immigration-application/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Submitting Biometrics for Your Immigration Application </a></p>
<p>Step 33: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/medical-examination-for-canadian-immigration/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Medical Examination for Canadian Immigration</a></p>
<p>Step 34: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/canadian-immigration-approved-applications/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Canadian Immigration Approved Application</a></p>
<p>Step 35: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/denied-sponsorship-applications/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Denied Sponsorship Applications</a></p>
<p>Step 36: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/new-to-canada-pr-card-drivers-license-health-card/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">New to Canada – Getting you PR Card/Driver’s License/Heath Card</a></p>
<p>Step 37: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/how-not-to-lose-your-status-in-canada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">How not to Lose Your Status as a Permanent Resident in Canada</a></p>
<p>Step 38: <a href="https://immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-course-you-are-done-wow/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Spousal Sponsorship Course – You are DONE! Wow</a></p>
<p>Most people know our business depends on people hiring us to help them through the maze and red tape that is “immigration.” So why would we share our expertise in free, do-it-yourself articles like this? Because we believe everyone moving to a new culture to work, study, or live deserves clear and accurate information.</p>
<p>Questions to ask in deciding whether to “do it yourself” or “hire the pros” at Immigroup:</p>
<ul>
<li>Do you enjoy reading?</li>
<li>Do you like complex projects?</li>
<li>Do you have a lot of “extra” time?</li>
<li>Are you detailed oriented—and good at catching mistakes?</li>
<li>Can you follow complicated directions?</li>
</ul>
<p>If you answered “yes” to all or most of those questions, then you’re a prime candidate for doing the application process on your own.</p>
<p>If you answered “no” to all or most of those questions . . . if such activities leave you flustered and frustrated and impatient, then you’d be wise to get an expert to at least review your application. <a href="https://www.immigroup.com/contact">Click here to contact us today</a>.</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><a class="button button-bg-red" href="https://www.immigroup.com/service/family-class-sponsorship-canada/">Paid Service from Immigroup</a></p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><div class="wpforms-container wpforms-container-full form-container-1" id="wpforms-3176"><form id="wpforms-form-3176" class="wpforms-validate wpforms-form" data-formid="3176" method="post" enctype="multipart/form-data" action="/feed/" data-token="b3226b88e02bc40919d098e7ca21eef1"><noscript class="wpforms-error-noscript">Please enable JavaScript in your browser to complete this form.</noscript><div class="wpforms-field-container"><div id="wpforms-3176-field_17-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-html" data-field-id="17"><div id="wpforms-3176-field_17"><h4 class="mt-0 mb-20 text-center">Have someone from our team call you back and answer all your questions.</h4></div></div><div id="wpforms-3176-field_1-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-name wpforms-one-half wpforms-first" data-field-id="1"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3176-field_1">Name <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3176-field_1" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][1]" required></div><div id="wpforms-3176-field_18-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-text wpforms-one-half" data-field-id="18"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3176-field_18">Phone number</label><input type="text" id="wpforms-3176-field_18" class="wpforms-field-large" name="wpforms[fields][18]" ></div><div id="wpforms-3176-field_3-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-email" data-field-id="3"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3176-field_3">Email <span class="wpforms-required-label">*</span></label><input type="email" id="wpforms-3176-field_3" class="wpforms-field-large wpforms-field-required" name="wpforms[fields][3]" required></div><div id="wpforms-3176-field_5-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-checkbox" data-field-id="5"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3176-field_5">What do you need?</label><ul id="wpforms-3176-field_5"><li class="choice-1 depth-1"><input type="checkbox" id="wpforms-3176-field_5_1" name="wpforms[fields][5][]" value="I need marriage papers (getting married overseas) "  ><label class="wpforms-field-label-inline" for="wpforms-3176-field_5_1">I need marriage papers (getting married overseas) </label></li><li class="choice-2 depth-1"><input type="checkbox" id="wpforms-3176-field_5_2" name="wpforms[fields][5][]" value="Sponsorship Application (bring my loved one to Canada) "  ><label class="wpforms-field-label-inline" for="wpforms-3176-field_5_2">Sponsorship Application (bring my loved one to Canada) </label></li></ul></div><div id="wpforms-3176-field_6-container" class="wpforms-field wpforms-field-textarea" data-field-id="6"><label class="wpforms-field-label" for="wpforms-3176-field_6">Tell us more about the relationship and what questions you need answered?</label><textarea id="wpforms-3176-field_6" class="wpforms-field-medium" name="wpforms[fields][6]" ></textarea></div></div><div class="wpforms-recaptcha-container wpforms-is-recaptcha"><div class="g-recaptcha" data-sitekey="6LcOq6EcAAAAAIUZpfojnEflSu-KDMSawsbdlUzF" data-size="invisible"></div></div><div class="wpforms-submit-container"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[id]" value="3176"><input type="hidden" name="wpforms[author]" value="15"><button type="submit" name="wpforms[submit]" id="wpforms-submit-3176" class="wpforms-submit" data-alt-text="Sending..." data-submit-text="Submit" aria-live="assertive" value="wpforms-submit">Submit</button></div></form></div>  <!-- .wpforms-container --></p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://www.immigroup.com/topics/spousal-sponsorship-course/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
		<media:content url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TQgVhnvu3DM" medium="video" width="1280" height="720">
			<media:player url="https://www.youtube.com/embed/TQgVhnvu3DM" />
			<media:title type="plain">How to do your own Spousal Sponsorship for free ? | Canadian Desi |</media:title>
			<media:description type="html"><![CDATA[In today&#039;s video, we will discuss about a spousal sponsorship tutorial I came across a couple weeks ago that can help you become an expert for your Spousal S...]]></media:description>
			<media:thumbnail url="https://www.immigroup.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/06/documents-papperwork.jpg" />
			<media:rating scheme="urn:simple">nonadult</media:rating>
		</media:content>
	</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
