<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>Meurrens Law</title>
	<atom:link href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com</link>
	<description>Meurrens Law – Canadian Immigration Law</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Thu, 26 Jan 2023 20:13:44 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-CA</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/03/icon-judicial.png</url>
	<title>Meurrens Law</title>
	<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>LMIA Exemption Code C-60</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/lmia-exemption-code-c-60/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven Meurrens]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 00:00:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=13804</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On December 15, 2022, Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (“IRCC”) updates its Labour Market Impact Assessment (“LMIA”) exemption codes.  An LMIA is an opinion from Service Canada that the entry of a foreign worker will have a positive or neutral impact on the Canadian labour market.  To obtain a positive LMIA employers must generally recruit ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/lmia-exemption-code-c-60/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On December 15, 2022, Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (“IRCC”) updates its Labour Market Impact Assessment (“LMIA”) exemption codes.  An LMIA is an opinion from Service Canada that the entry of a foreign worker will have a positive or neutral impact on the Canadian labour market.  To obtain a positive LMIA employers must generally recruit for four weeks on prescribed websites, invite potentially qualified Canadians to apply, pay prevailing wage, and demonstrate other labour market benefits. The process is often difficult.</p>
<p>Because of this, and other reasons, Canadian immigration legislation permits IRCC to issue work permits in certain circumstances without employers needing to obtain LMIAs. These are known as LMIA exemptions.</p>
<p>For the most part the December 15, 2022 changes involve renumbering some of the LMIA exemptions and splitting previous LMIA exemptions into several categories.  Future changes are expected. There were, however, important changes to the LMIA exemptions for provincial nominees in business programs and other entrepreneurs.  These changes involve the introduction of “significant benefit” tests.</p>
<p><strong>Significant Benefit</strong></p>
<p>IRCC has always had an LMIA exemption for individuals whose work in Canada would generate significant economic, social or cultural benefits.</p>
<p>Generally, economic benefits are benefits that would contribute to a company’s growth, expansion or continuation that have fiscal benefits and allow for the competitive advantage of Canada’s business community. Social benefits are where someone’s work will provide significant external benefits to other third parties not directly involved in business transactions. Culture is defined as creative artistic activities and the goods and services produced by it.</p>
<p>Significant includes, but is not limited to, an assessment of how the work of a foreign national will provide general economic support for Canada, advancement of Canadian industry, increased health and well-being or increased tolerance or opportunities to come together with others of similar culture.</p>
<p>The IRCC website provides examples of all of the above. It cautions that visa officers should be reluctant to issue work permits under the category, but also notes that where an LMIA is not available, and the balance of practical considerations indicates that the work of a foreign national would be of significant benefit to Canada, economically, socially, or culturally, then a work permit can be issued without the LMIA.</p>
<p><strong>Provincial Nominee Entrepreneurs </strong></p>
<p>Prior to December 15, 2022, prospective provincial nominees who were issued work permit support letters by a provincial government to be entrepreneurs in a province did not need to also demonstrate that their work in Canada would generate a significant economic, social or cultural benefit.</p>
<p>This is no longer the case.  Now, under a new LMIA Exemption Code C-60, entrepreneurs applying for work permits under provincial nominee programs will generally need to demonstrate that their proposed work will provide general economic stimulus or the advancement of Canadian industry.  They will also need to provide business plans which show that they have the experience to manage the business, the language abilities needed to operate the business and that their work will be of significant benefit.  Provincial letters of support may be indicative, but IRCC will now it seems essentially be reassessing provincial nomination applications.</p>
<p>The consequence of this change is significant, and could potentially reduce the attractiveness and predictability of provincial nominee entrepreneur programs. The change is recent and has not been widely publicized. Those considering applying to provincial entrepreneur programs, as well as those who may represent them, need to understand the new LMIA Exemption Code C-60.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Deemed Rehabilitation</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/deemed-rehabilitation/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven Meurrens]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 12 Jan 2023 16:31:09 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Inadmissibility]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=13797</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[An individual who is criminally inadmissible to Canada may be deemed rehabilitated depending on the crime that was committed, the amount of time that has passed since the crime was committed, the maximum term of punishment for the crime and whether the person committed one or more crimes. It is not necessary to apply to ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/deemed-rehabilitation/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<div class="mwsbodytext text parbase section">
<p>An individual who is criminally inadmissible to Canada may be deemed rehabilitated depending on the crime that was committed, the amount of time that has passed since the crime was committed, the maximum term of punishment for the crime and whether the person committed one or more crimes.</p>
<p>It is not necessary to apply to be deemed rehabilitated, although it is helpful to avoid being found inadmissible to Canada when one arrives at a port of entry.  People who live in the United States may travel to a Canadian port of entry and ask to be assessed.</p>
<p>The following charts demonstrate the legislative provisions of deemed rehabilitation.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-13798 aligncenter" src="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture-1024x500.png" alt="" width="846" height="413" srcset="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture-1024x500.png 1024w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture-300x146.png 300w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture-768x375.png 768w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture-100x49.png 100w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture-846x413.png 846w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture-1184x578.png 1184w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture-600x293.png 600w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture.png 1536w" sizes="(max-width: 846px) 100vw, 846px" /> <img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-large wp-image-13799 aligncenter" src="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2-1024x540.png" alt="" width="846" height="446" srcset="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2-1024x540.png 1024w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2-300x158.png 300w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2-768x405.png 768w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2-1536x811.png 1536w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2-100x53.png 100w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2-846x447.png 846w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2-1184x625.png 1184w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2-600x317.png 600w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/Capture2.png 1563w" sizes="(max-width: 846px) 100vw, 846px" /></p>
</div>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Self Employment and The Canadian Experience Class</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/self-employment-and-the-canadian-experience-class-2/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven Meurrens]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 10 Jan 2023 01:27:55 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=13789</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The Canadian Experience Class (the &#8220;CEC&#8221;) is an immigration program for skilled workers who have Canadian work experience and want to become permanent residents. Regulation 87.1(3)(b) of the Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations provides that any period of self-employment shall not be included in calculating Canadian work experience under the CEC. The Immigration Refugee and Citizenship Canada ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/self-employment-and-the-canadian-experience-class-2/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>The Canadian Experience Class (the &#8220;CEC&#8221;) is an immigration program for skilled workers who have Canadian work experience and want to become permanent residents.</p>
<p>Regulation 87.1(3)(b) of the <em>Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations </em>provides that any period of self-employment shall not be included in calculating Canadian work experience under the CEC.</p>
<p>The Immigration Refugee and Citizenship Canada (&#8220;<strong>IRCC</strong>&#8220;) guidelines provide the following guidance to officers in assessing whether someone is self-employed:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;"><strong>Determining an applicant’s employment status</strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Applicants under the CEC must satisfy an IRCC officer that they meet all program requirements as per section R87.1. Any period of self-employment shall not be included in calculating the period of qualifying work experience under the CEC [R87.1(3)(b)]. As such, the CEC requires that applicants demonstrate they acquired skilled work experience in Canada through authorized employment by a third party.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Principal applicants are requested to provide documentary evidence of their work experience in Canada through a combination of: a copy of their most recent work permit (unless they are work-permit exempt), copies of their most recent T4 tax information slips and Notice of Assessment (NOA) issued by the Canada Revenue Agency (CRA) or a sufficient combination of other supporting documentation, and employer letters of reference for all periods of qualifying work experience claimed in the application.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Canadian employers are responsible for deducting and remitting Canada Pension Plan (CPP) contributions, Employment Insurance (EI) premiums, and income tax from remuneration or other amounts they pay to their employees to the CRA. They must also provide employees with a record of their remuneration and deductions in the form of a T4 tax information slip. The T4 slip is therefore key documentary evidence for the vast majority of CEC applicants to demonstrate that they were in an employer-employee work relationship during their period of qualifying work experience in Canada.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">However, there is no obligation under the regulations that CEC applicants provide a T4 tax information slip or NOA specifically with their application, and these particular documents cannot be considered conclusive evidence or the only evidence accepted for the purposes of substantiating whether an applicant has qualifying Canadian work experience. As such, in the absence of a T4 tax information slip or NOA, documents which may help substantiate the applicant’s work experience in Canada could include a record or letter of employment from the Canadian employer, work contracts and pay stubs.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">In all cases, the onus is on the applicant to establish that they meet the CEC criteria at the time of their application. All applicants are required to provide satisfactory evidence of their work experience in Canada, including the fact that they were in an employer-employee relationship during their period of qualifying work experience.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;"><strong>Factors to consider – Employee vs. self-employed</strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">In determining whether an applicant under the CEC was an employee or a self-employed individual during their period of qualifying work experience in Canada, IRCC officers should consider factors such as</p>
<ul>
<li style="list-style-type: none;">
<ul>
<li>the degree of the worker’s control or autonomy in terms of how and when work is performed, and the method(s) used to do the work</li>
<li>whether the worker owns or provides tools and equipment to accomplish the work;</li>
<li>the degree to which the worker has to perform the work personally and whether the worker has the option of subcontracting work or hiring others to help and assist with completing the work</li>
<li>the degree of financial risk assumed by the worker, including whether the worker is required to make any investment in order to complete the work or provide the service and whether the worker is free to make business decisions that affect their ability to realize a profit or incur a loss (as opposed to the opportunity to earn commissions or other productivity bonuses)</li>
<li>any other relevant factors, such as written contracts</li>
</ul>
</li>
</ul>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Additional details regarding each of the above factors, and indicators that can be used when determining whether an individual is an employee or self-employed, are available in the Employee or Self-employed? CRA guide.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Determination of the degree of control can be difficult when examining the employment of professionals such as engineers, physicians and information technology consultants. Given their expertise and specialized training, they may need little or no specific direction in their daily activities. When examining the factor of control, it is necessary to focus on both the payer’s control over the worker’s daily activities and the payer’s influence over the worker. There are also certain occupations in which individuals may be either self-employed or in an employer-employee relationship depending on the specific circumstances of their employment. More information on the determination of a worker’s employment status for a number of specific employment categories is available on the CRA website.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Generally speaking, consultants or contractors are considered to be self-employed individuals in a contract for services business relationship. For example, independent contractors in the financial, real estate and business service industries. Similarly, individuals who hold substantial ownership and/or exercise management control of a business for which they are also employed are generally considered to be self-employed.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">If a prospective applicant is not sure of their employment status and does not have the documentation set out above, they may choose to request a ruling from the CRA to have that status determined. Such a ruling will state whether, in the view of the CRA, a worker is an employee or self-employed, and whether or not that worker’s employment is pensionable or insurable. A worker may request a ruling by sending a letter or completed Form CPT1, Request for a Ruling as to the Status of a Worker Under the Canada Pension Plan and/or the Employment Insurance Act to their tax services office. This ruling may thereafter be submitted to IRCC to supplement a CEC application.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Each application under the CEC is to be considered on its own merits, with a final decision based on a review of all the information available to the IRCC officer at the time of decision. While a CRA ruling on an applicant’s employment status will be given due consideration by an IRCC officer, such a ruling will not constitute conclusive evidence. The final decision as to the employment status of the applicant for the purposes of meeting CEC requirements rests with the IRCC officer.</p>
<p><strong>Jurisprudence</strong></p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2017/2017fc16/2017fc16.html?resultIndex=1"><em>Lazar v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2017 FC 16</a>, Justice Gleeson determined that it was reasonable for an officer to decide that an individual who owned 90% of a company, and was President of the company, meant that someone had substantial ownership and management control of the business.  He also addressed an issue that many lawyers have raised, which is that the definition of &#8220;self-employment&#8221; under Canadian immigration law is different from that of corporate law. Justice Gleeson wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">While a corporation is, in law, a separate and distinct legal entity, the assessment of the question of self-employment under the CEC is driven by factors relating to ownership and control of a business. This is evident when one reviews the factors relating to an assessment of self-employment set out in the Operational Manual. The Operational Manual draws no distinction between businesses established as corporations, sole proprietorships or partnerships. Rather, the Operational Manual speaks of businesses generally and focuses on questions of ownership and control, not business structure.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2017/2017fc640/2017fc640.html?resultIndex=1"><em>Byrne v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2017 FC 640</a>, Justice Southcott determined that in the context of a Labour Market Impact Assessment which states that someone is an Owner/Operator and where someone is the principal shareholder of a business, then it is reasonable for an officer to conclude that they are self-employed.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/522741/index.do"><em>Zamani v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2023 FC 19</a>, Madam Justice Furlanetto determined that if an individual has been approved as an Intra-Company Transferee, then this means that a determination has been made that there is a qualifying employer-employee relationship, which, according to the IRCC Guidelines, includes a statement that &#8220;[t]he essential element in determining [the] relationship is the right of the employer to order and control the employee in the performance of their work.” A visa officer under the CEC needs to address the fact that a previous officer has determined that someone met this requirement in their work permit application before determining that they are self-employed under the CEC.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Applying for a Study Permit</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/applying-for-a-study-permit/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meurrens Law]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 09 Jan 2023 11:04:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Study Permits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Obison]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Study Permit]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=9988</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Generally, to be eligible for a study permit, a potential student must: present a letter of acceptance from the educational institution where she intends to study. This school must be a Designated Learning Institution; be able to both pay the tuition fees of the program as well as be able to financially support themselves and any ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/applying-for-a-study-permit/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Generally, to be eligible for a study permit, a potential student must:</p>
<ul>
<li>present a letter of acceptance from the educational institution where she intends to study. This school must be a Designated Learning Institution;</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>be able to both pay the tuition fees of the program as well as be able to financially support themselves and any accompanying financial members. Depending on the person’s country of origin, they may be required to take out a GIC with a designated Canadian bank;</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>be able to cover the cost of transportation to and from Canada;</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>pass any medical examinations;</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>possibly show proof of health insurance;</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>demonstrate that they are a bona fide student and that they will leave Canada at the end of the period authorized by their stay.</li>
</ul>
<p>Not every student needs a study permit. Exempt students include:</p>
<ul>
<li>persons seeking to study for a short-term program (unless they wish to work on campus).</li>
</ul>
<ul>
<li>minor students in Canada.</li>
</ul>
<h3><strong>Approval </strong>Rate Statistics</h3>
<p>The following charts were obtained through <em>Access to Information Act </em>requests.</p>
<p>Here is the Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (&#8220;IRCC&#8221;) approval rate for study permit applications based on certain countries of origin from 2009 – 2013.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/SP-approval-Rates.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">SP-approval-Rates<br/></a>
<p>Here is a breakdown of approvals for India, China, the Philippines, and Vietnam broken down by level of study, gender, age, and whether the person applied online or in person.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/2A-2020-45814-Release-package.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Study Permit Approvals<br/></a>
<p>Here is the monthly 2019-2020 (Oct) approval statistics based on country and proposed program of study.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Study-Permit-Approval-by-Country.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Study Permit Approval by Country<br/></a>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/2A-2020-67507_Release-package-reducedsize.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Approval Rates<br/></a>
<p>Here is the breakdown of approvals for 2016 &#8211; 2020 by country.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Study-Permit-Approval-Rate-by-Age.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Study Permit Approval Rate by Age<br/></a>
<p>Here is the number of students at the post-secondary level based on country of nationality.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Students-at-University.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Students at University<br/></a>
<p>As well, here are two PDFs which show the number of study permit applications received based on school as well as the number of approvals.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Study-Permit-Approval.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Study Permit Approval<br/></a><a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Study-Permit-Receipt.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Study Permit Receipt<br/></a>
<p>Finally, the number of study permits issued based on port of entry, and refused based on visa office.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/A-2020-25204_Release-package.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">A-2020-25204_Release package<br/></a>
<h3><strong>When to Apply</strong></h3>
<p>Most people have to apply for study permits outside of Canada.  There are exceptions to this, however, including those who already hold study permits, those who hold work permits, family members of work permit holders, and temporary residents who has completed a course or program of study that is a prerequisite to their enrolling at a designated learning institution. Pursuant to the Federal Court of Canada decision in <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2018/2018fc1181/2018fc1181.html?resultIndex=1"><em>Virk v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em></a>, it is not necessary that the prerequisite have been completed in Canada.</p>
<h3>Meaningful Engagement with Application</h3>
<p>As with all applications visa officers are required to meaningfully engage with evidence.  In <em>Patel v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2020 FC 77, affirmed in <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/489415/index.do"><em>Obison v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2020 FC 1083</a>, Justice Diner stated:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">…I appreciate that the context of a visa office, with immense pressures to produce a large volume of decisions every day, do not allow for extensive reasons. The brevity of the Decision, however, is not what makes this Decision unreasonable. Rather, it is its lack of responsiveness to the evidence. Vavilov, at paragraphs 127-128, describes the concept of responsiveness as follows:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">The principles of justification and transparency require that an administrative decision maker’s reasons meaningfully account for the central issues and concerns raised by the parties. The principle that the individual or individuals affected by a decision should have the opportunity to present their case fully and fairly underlies the duty of procedural fairness and is rooted in the right to be heard: Baker, at para. 28. The concept of responsive reasons is inherently bound up with this principle, because reasons are the primary mechanism by which decision makers demonstrate that they have actually listened to the parties.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">[…]
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Again, while the reality of visa offices and the context in which its officers work include significant operational pressures and resource constraints created by huge volumes of applications, this cannot exempt their decisions from being responsive to the factual matrix put before them. Failing to ask for basic responsiveness to the evidence would deprive reasonableness review of the robust quality that Vavilov requires at paras 13, 67 and 72. “Reasonableness” is not synonymous with “voluminous reasons”: simple, concise justification will do.</p>
<p>As well, when it comes to common sense country conditions, the Federal Court has noted that officers cannot make summary statements about country conditions without engaging with the evidence. In <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/516998/index.do"><em>Ghasemi v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2021 FC 1296</a>, Justice Favel stated:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The reasons refer to political and economic considerations in Iran but the record does not indicate what those conditions are. While an Officer can rely on common sense and reason, they must also engage with the evidence before them (Motala v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration), 2020 FC 726 at para 13). When an Officer bases their decision on a hunch or speculation, and it is not supported by the record or sufficiently articulated, that decision will be unreasonable (Demyati v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration), 2018 FC 701 at paras 16, 20).</p>
<h3><strong>Bona Fides</strong></h3>
<p>In addition to the reasons why any <a href="http://meurrensonimmigration.com/factors-in-determining-whether-a-temporary-worker-will-voluntarily-leave-canada/">temporary residency application might be refused regarding whether the person will leave Canada by the end of their authorised stay</a>, there are also reasons for refusal that are unique to study permits.  The most significant is whether the individual intends on being a <em>bona fide </em>student.</p>
<p>As Justice Roy noted in <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2018/2018fc701/2018fc701.html?searchUrlHash=AAAAAQA4InNoYWxsIGFjdGl2ZWx5IHB1cnN1ZSB0aGVpciBjb3Vyc2Ugb3IgcHJvZ3JhbSBvZiBzdHVkeSIAAAAAAQ&amp;resultIndex=1"><em>Demyati v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2018 FC 701</a>, arbitrariness is the antithesis of reasonableness, and the prohibition against arbitrariness is one of the principles of fundamental justice which is at the heart of section 7 of the <em>Canadian Charter of Rights and Freedoms</em>.  In setting aside the decision of a visa officer to refuse a study permit application, Justice Roy wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">In the case at bar, it remains unclear why the visa officer concluded that an 18-year-old student, who benefits from a scholarship award from a recognized university, would not be a bona fide student who would stay in this country beyond the expiration of the study permit. Furthermore, there is no reason that is articulated to suggest that this applicant would run afoul of section 220.1 (1) of the Regulations:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px;">Conditions — study permit holder</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px;">220.1 (1) The holder of a study permit in Canada is subject to the following conditions:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px;">(a) they shall enroll at a designated learning institution and remain enrolled at a designated learning institution until they complete their studies; and</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px;">(b) they shall actively pursue their course or program of study.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">I have not found any justification on this record for such a conclusion. If there is a justification, and there may well be, it has to be articulated for the decision to be reasonable.</p>
<p>There are non-arbitary reasons to refuse a study permit application.  Study permit applications are often refused if a visa officer determines that an applicant’s program of study does not reflect a logical educational choice given a person’s educational background. As the Federal Court noted in <a href="https://decisia.lexum.com/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/236749/index.do"><em>Perez v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration) </em>2017 FC 1001</a>, an applicant intending to study in areas totally disconnected from their background and experience typically prompt visa officers to question the true intent behind a study permit application.  However, where an individual is completing a program which complements their background and experience, then an application is much more likely to be approved.</p>
<p>As well, several Federal Court decisions note that it is unreasonable for officers to &#8220;foray into career counselling.&#8221;  In <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/522535/index.do"><em>Nia v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 1648</a>, the Court said:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">[28] Justice Fuhrer relied on Adom in the recent case of Seyedsalehi v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration), 2022 FC 1250 (&#8220;“Seyedsalehi”&#8221;), in which a visa officer refused a study permit application because the applicant’s pursuit of a college level program was illogical given her previous master’s degree at a university (at para 16). Justice Fuhrer found:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">[16] Further, one is left wondering on what basis the Officer finds studying a college level program illogical in the face of a previously studied Masters level program at university. For example, does the Officer correlate the Masters program in Malaysia with a similar Masters level program in Canada? Does the Officer find the illogicality rests in a university (regardless of where located) versus a college program, i.e. is the latter considered to be a lower level or of lesser value? Or is it the Applicant’s change of focus from psychology to early childhood education and care? Nowhere does the Officer provide reasons for the finding of illogicality, especially in the context of the Applicant’s motivation letter or study plan. In my view, the Officer’s finding is tantamount to an unreasonable “foray into career counselling” that lacks intelligibility and transparency: Adom v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration), 2019 FC 26 at para 17.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">[Emphasis added]
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">[29] The same reasoning can be applied in the Applicant’s case. The Officer provides no substantive reason for deciding that the Applicant’s pursued program of study is illogical given her previous education at a higher level, especially in the context of her detailed evidence explaining the purpose of this pursuit. Rather than carry out an intelligible, justified and transparent analysis of this evidence, the Officer’s reasoning exhibits a &#8220;“foray into career counselling”&#8221; that lacks reasonableness (Seyedsalehi at para 16, citing Adom at para 17).</p>
<p>Another issue that study permit applicants face is satisfying visa officers that their proposed program of study is reasonable in light of the costs.  However, as the Federal Court noted in <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/346338/index.do"><em>Cervjakova v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em></a>, an individual&#8217;s decision to study in Canada could well entail financial sacrifices for a study permit applicant and her family but this is often what is required to improve one’s circumstances in life.  The Federal Court recently affirmed this decision in <em>Caianda v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, when it stated that there is nothing wrong with individuals putting a high value on education.</p>
<h3>Leaving Canada at the end of Authorized Stay</h3>
<p>In <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2018/2018fc701/2018fc701.html?searchUrlHash=AAAAAQA4InNoYWxsIGFjdGl2ZWx5IHB1cnN1ZSB0aGVpciBjb3Vyc2Ugb3IgcHJvZ3JhbSBvZiBzdHVkeSIAAAAAAQ&amp;resultIndex=1"><em>Demyati v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em></a>, Justice Shore ruled that in the study permit context the presence of family in Canada could not by itself be seen as a negative factor in a study permit application.  This is in part because it could suggest that the person would have family support.  As well, in <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/522755/index.do"><em>Ahadi v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2023 FC 25</a>, Justice Bell said that refusing an applicant because their dependent would be accompanying them amounts to a fettering of discretion.</p>
<p>As well, in <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/500597/index.do"><em>Rahmati v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2021 FC 778</a>, Madam Justice Walker ruled that if a visa officer determines that an applicant already has a temporary resident visa, then a determination that the individual would not leave Canada at the end of their studies will be unreasonable if the officer does not adequately consider the fact that they already have a temporary resident visa.</p>
<p>As well, the Federal Court has repeatedly cautioned that an applicant&#8217;s lack of a dependent spouse or children, without any further analysis, should not necessarily be considered a negative factor in assessing a study permit application.  In <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/522614/index.do"><em>Gilavan v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 1698</a>, for example, Justice Lafreniere noted that this would disqualify many, if not most, study permit applicants.  As such, statements that an applicant is single, young and mobile without any further explanation can render a refusal unreasonable.</p>
<h3>Credibility of Bank Statements</h3>
<p>An argument that bank statements may have been &#8220;put together for the application&#8221; is  a credibility concern, as the Federal Court determined in <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/512958/index.do"><em>Opakunbi v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2021 FC 943</a>.</p>
<h3>Returning to Work</h3>
<p>Study permit applicants will often provide letters from their employers confirming that they have permission to study in Canada and that they can resume working for the company once the person completes their studies. The exact wording of these letters can be important. In <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/515077/index.do"><em>Bondarenko v. Canada (Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship)</em>, 2021 FC 1106</a> Madam Justice MacDonald wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The Applicant provided a letter from her employer which “strongly encourage[s]” her to take a course in Canada. Given the length of time the Applicant would be gone, it was reasonable for the Officer to weigh the loss of the Applicant’s job as a negative factor. A confirmed intention to consider re-hire is not the same as a promise to re-hire. In the circumstances, it was reasonable for the Officer to weigh this evidence accordingly and conclude that the Applicant had weak financial ties to Russia.</p>
<p><strong>Grades</strong></p>
<p>In <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/522755/index.do"><em>Ahadi v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2023 FC 25</a>, Justice Bell wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The Officer criticizes the Applicant for having failed to provide <q class="decisia-wcag-quote-inline"><span class="CitationCar">“recent education transcripts and diplomas”</span></q> in support of her study permit request. With respect, this requirement imposed by the Officer seems rather unintelligible given the number of years that have passed since the Applicant completed her Bachelor’s program, the fact she offers proof of acceptance into the Master’s program and the fact that she has been awarded a scholarship. I ask rhetorically, <q class="decisia-wcag-quote-inline"><span class="CitationCar">“what difference does knowledge of her marks make to any part of the task being undertaken by the Officer”?</span></q> The answer, in these circumstances, is, in my view, <q class="decisia-wcag-quote-inline"><span class="CitationCar">“none”</span></q>.</p>
<p>However, the Federal Court in <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/522826/index.do"><em>Singh v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 1745,</a> also ruled that an applicant&#8217;s skills and abilities can be taken into account in assessing a study permit application, and that &#8220;Wanting to undertake a course of studies in which one was unlikely to succeed could raise questions about whether an applicant is a bona fide student who will leave Canada by the end of the period authorized for their stay.”</p>
<h3><strong>Procedural Fairness</strong></h3>
<p>The requirements of procedural fairness are relaxed for study permit applications.  The onus is on applicants to prove their case, and a visa officer is not required to provide them with a “running score” of weaknesses or give notice of concerns arising from legislative requirements.  However, there are circumstances where a visa officer will be required to inform an applicant of concerns with an application, even where those concerns arise from the applicant’s own evidence.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2010/2010fc522/2010fc522.html?resultIndex=1"><em>Gu v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2010 FC 522</a>, Justice Mainville set aside a refusal that was based on an IRCC officer&#8217;s determination that the applicant had not previously completed her studies under a different study permit.  He wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">In the CAIPS notes, the officer was concerned that the Applicant did not establish she had completed any studies in Canada under previously issued study permits or worked in Canada under the work permits issued to her. Indeed, if the Applicant was using work or study permits for other purposes, then this could certainly give rise to a valid concern about her commitment to leave Canada by the end of the new study permit she was requesting.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">However, these past permits had been issued and renewed by the Canadian immigration authorities, and there is no evidence of non-compliance with the Act and the Regulations on the part of the Applicant. In circumstances where past compliance issues have never been raised, I agree with the Applicant that if the officer had a concern about her compliance with past permits, the officer should have informed her of the concern and provided her with an opportunity to respond. As noted by Justice Beaudry in Li v. Canada (Minister of Citizenship &amp; Immigration), supra at para. 35:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">There is no statutory right to an interview (Ali v. Canada (Minister of Citizenship and Immigration), (1998) 151 F.T.R. 1, 79 A.C.W.S. (3d) 140 at paragraph 28). However, procedural fairness requires that an Applicant be given the opportunity to respond to an officer&#8217;s concerns under certain circumstances. When no extrinsic evidence is relied on, it is unclear when it is necessary to afford an Applicant an interview or a right to respond. Yet, the jurisprudence suggests that there will be a right to respond under certain circumstances.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">[…]
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">This is not a case where the officer had concerns with the application which was submitted. Rather the concerns related to past permits and past applications. In light of these circumstances, the Applicant was entitled to be provided with an opportunity to answer these concerns which she could not have reasonably foreseen as being of interest to the officer. Since the application will be returned to another Non-Immigrant Officer for redetermination, the Applicant is now well advised that she must address these concerns with this new officer.</p>
<p>Similarly, in<a href="https://decisia.lexum.com/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/308627/index.do"> <em>Popova v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2018 FC 326</a>, Justice Diner set aside a study permit application where in a previous application IRCC only raised concerns about proof of funds. In the subsequent application, IRCC determined that proof of funds was fine, but that this time the reasonableness of the proposed study was the problem. Justice Diner determined that in this case IRCC had to notify the applicant of the new concerns as the applicant had no way of knowing about them based on the refusal reasons for the previous application, stating that &#8221; an interview may be required in student visa applications where the officer has formed an opinion that the applicant would have no way of anticipating.&#8221;</p>
<p>Finally, pursuant to Justice Walker&#8217;s decision in <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/366090/index.do"><em>Al Aridi v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2019 FC 381, </a> where an applicant provides sufficient evidence, but an officer simply does not believe that an applicant will be a <em>bona fide </em>student, then this is a veiled credibility concern, and procedural fairness requires that an officer provide the applicant with an opportunity to respond.  This decision was affirmed by Justice Diner in <em>Patel v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, where Justice Diner in addition to stating that an expression of concern over someone&#8217;s <em>bona fides </em>was a credibility concern, also voiced concerns over the reasonableness of refusing an application over the cost of studying in Canada. Justice Diner wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Returning to the four reasons underlying the conclusion in this case (as listed in paragraph 14 above), first, there are clear potential employment benefits to international study, including in this case, the opportunity to improve English language skills.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">As for the second reason cited by the Officer, lower-cost options for English programs in India does not make enrollment in a Canadian English program unreasonable. Foreign students worldwide often pay substantial fees for the experience of studying abroad, and all the salutary effects that it may have, including receiving advanced education, improving language skills, gaining international perspectives, being immersed in foreign cultures, and improving career prospects.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Regarding the third ground cited in the Decision, Mr. Patel’s academic and employment history is in the field of business. Therefore, I find nothing inherently unreasonable about pursuing further studies in his field.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Finally, on the fourth issue cited, the Officer did not expand whatsoever – or justify in any way – what the “personal circumstances” might be, or why those might render his attendance at the university “unreasonable.”</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Assessing the Genuineness of a Work Permit Offer of Employment</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/assessing-the-genuineness-of-a-work-permit-offer-of-employment/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meurrens Law]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 04 Jan 2023 05:59:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Work Permits]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Genuineness]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Work Permit]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=8957</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Canada&#8217;s Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations (the &#8220;IRPR&#8220;) states that a work permit application must be refused if an officer determines that the offer of employment is not genuine. Section 200(5) of the IRPR states that in order to determine whether an offer of employment is genuine an officer should consider (a) whether the offer is made ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/assessing-the-genuineness-of-a-work-permit-offer-of-employment/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>Canada&#8217;s <em>Immigration and Refugee Protection Regulations </em>(the &#8220;<strong>IRPR</strong>&#8220;) states that a work permit application must be refused if an officer determines that the offer of employment is not genuine.</p>
<p>Section 200(5) of the IRPR states that in order to determine whether an offer of employment is genuine an officer should consider (a) whether the offer is made by an employer that is actively engaged in the business in respect of which the offer is made, (b) whether the offer is consistent with the reasonable needs of the employer, (c) whether the terms of the offer are terms that the employer is reasonably able to fulfill, and (d) the past compliance of the employer with federal or provincial laws that regulate employment.</p>
<p>Immigration, Refugee and Citizenship Canada&#8217;s (&#8220;<strong>IRCC</strong>&#8220;) guidelines contain extensive instructions to <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/corporate/publications-manuals/operational-bulletins-manuals/temporary-residents/foreign-workers/genuineness.html">officers on assessing the genuineness of the offer of employment on a work permit application</a>.</p>
<p><strong>Actively Engaged</strong></p>
<p>In order to demonstrate that an employer is actively engaged in the business an employer must do all of the following:</p>
<ul>
<li>have an operating business;</li>
<li>provide either a good or a service; and</li>
<li>have a physical work location in Canada where the temporary worker will work.</li>
</ul>
<p>The following are some red flags that can trigger an in-depth assessment of whether a company is actively engaged in the business.</p>
<ul>
<li>the business information in the offer of employment raises concerns with respect to the organization’s active engagement in a business (such as being less than 1 year old);</li>
<li>there is negative publicly available information regarding the organization; and</li>
<li>previous work permit applications were refused because officers had concerns about whether an employer was actively engaged in the business.</li>
</ul>
<p>The IRCC website contains the following examples of how officers should assess whether an employer is actively engaged in the business:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Example of an employer actively engaged in the business</strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The owner of a high-end Japanese restaurant in Toronto would like to hire a Japanese sous-chef. His business has been open for 6 years and employs 36 people, including 8 foreign nationals.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">An officer may be satisfied that the organization legally exists and has the ability to provide stable employment for the requested period because it does all of the following:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px;">has been open for several years</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px;">already employs several people</p>
<p style="padding-left: 60px;">provides food and drink in a physical space (that is, the restaurant)</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>Example of employer that may not be actively engaged in the business</strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The owner of a small Japanese “bento-box” delivery restaurant in Toronto would like to hire a Japanese cook. His business has been open for 5 months and employs 2 other people. He cannot provide the officer with T4s (his business is too new), nor can he provide a lease because he operates his business from home. He pays his employees with cash or in food, which they don’t mind because they are family members. He shows the officer order slips for produce bought last month.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Even if an officer is satisfied that this business may be operational, provides a good and has a work location, it has not “demonstrated the ability to provide stable employment for the requested period” because it is too new and does not pay its employees in a consistent and reliable way.</p>
<p><strong>Reasonable Employment Need</strong></p>
<p>In order for an employer to show that the offer of employment is consistent with the reasonable employment needs of the employer, the employer must demonstrate that the  offer of employment is reasonable in relation to the type of business the organization is engaged in.  Specifically, the occupation should be one that is reasonably expected in that organization’s sector, and the employer must be able to meet the terms of employment that they have offered.  In other words, the employer must be able to satisfactorily explain the role of the temporary worker in their operations and how it covers a reasonable employment need, in terms of both occupation and operation.</p>
<p>The IRCC website contains the following examples of when an employer might not be able to demonstrate that there is a reasonable employment need:</p>
<ul>
<li>An insurance company is hiring a full-time actor.</li>
<li>A company has only 10 employees, and this is the sixth supervisor position they have offered in the last year.</li>
<li>A hair salon is hiring a management consultant.</li>
</ul>
<p><b>Ability to Fulfill </b></p>
<p style="text-align: left;">An employer must be able to demonstrate that the terms of employment are ones that they can reasonably fulfill. They must demonstrate that they are capable of providing, for the duration of the work permit, the hours of work, wages and benefits stated in the offer of employment.</p>
<p>Officers may request the following documents to show whether an employer can fulfill the terms of the job offer:</p>
<ul>
<li>T4 Summary of Remuneration Paid</li>
<li>T2 Schedule 100/125</li>
<li>T2125 or equivalent</li>
<li>worker&#8217;s compensation clearance letter</li>
<li>business contracts.</li>
</ul>
<p>The IRCC website contains the following examples of how officers should assess whether an employer is actively engaged in the business:</p>
<h4 style="padding-left: 30px;">Positive example</h4>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>A well-established restaurant chain is hiring a specialty cook. The chain has been in existence for over 10 years and is known for its exemplary food and service.</strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The restaurant chain is able to demonstrate that it is “capable of providing, for the duration of the work permit, work in line with the occupation, wages offered and acceptable employment standards” because they are well established and have several years of income to prove they can afford the new cook.</p>
<h4 style="padding-left: 30px;">Negative example</h4>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>A new home-based business is hiring a person to prepare food for a new gourmet meal delivery service. The owner of the new business declared a profit of only $10,000 the previous year, but they are going to be paying the temporary worker $45,000 a year.</strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The new business is not able to show that they have sufficient funds to pay the wages offered, nor do they have business contracts to show that they would be able to meet the terms of the offer based on monies to be received through the contracts.</p>
<p><strong>Compliance with Federal / Provincial Law</strong></p>
<p>Finally, an officer must be satisfied that the employer will be and has been compliant with federal and provincial or territorial laws regulating employment.</p>
<p>The IRCC website contains the following examples of how officers should assess whether an employer is actively engaged in the business:</p>
<h4 style="padding-left: 30px;">Positive example</h4>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>A British Columbia mining company is hiring a temporary worker. There are several news articles referencing the fact that they have won prestigious safety awards in their industry and that they are a top 50 company to work for.</strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">Unless the officer has any indication to the contrary, they could be satisfied that this company has a common practice of compliance with “federal and/or provincial laws regulating employment and recruitment in the province(s) it is intended that the temporary worker will work” based on having won awards for safety and being one of the top 50 companies in Canada.</p>
<h4 style="padding-left: 30px;">Negative example</h4>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;"><strong>An Alberta mining company has just received a provincial court judgement that they are guilty of involuntary manslaughter because of a lack of safety equipment on their work sites that caused the death of 2 workers.</strong></p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">The Alberta mining company has been found guilty in a provincial court of not complying with provincial and federal laws. Therefore, they do not meet this requirement, and the work permit would be refused.</p>
<p><strong>Sample Questionnaire</strong></p>
<p>In 2020 the Canadian visa office in New Delhi started issuing the following questions to applicants to determine genuineness.</p>
<p><strong><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-12118 aligncenter" src="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/Capture-1.png" alt="" width="844" height="1119" /></strong>The full instructions are here:</p>
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong><a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/2A202003954_Release-package.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">2A202003954_Release package<br/></a></strong></p>
<p><strong>Jurisprudence</strong></p>
<p>The Federal Court has consistently held that positive LMIA is not determinative and that visa officers have the authority to assess the genuineness of job offers.</p>
<p>In determining whether an offer of employment is genuine, visa officers can go beyond the prescribed factors described above.  For example, in <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2016/2016fc509/2016fc509.html?searchUrlHash=AAAAAQBmIkEgZGV0ZXJtaW5hdGlvbiBvZiB3aGV0aGVyIGFuIG9mZmVyIG9mIGVtcGxveW1lbnQgaXMgZ2VudWluZSBzaGFsbCBiZSBiYXNlZCBvbiB0aGUgZm9sbG93aW5nIGZhY3RvcnMiAAAAAAE&amp;resultIndex=4"><em>Singh v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em></a><em>, </em>2016 FC 509, Madam Justice Kane noted that where it appears that an employer is hiring a family member, and that the motivation appears more to help the family member than to fill a vacancy, then the genuineness of a job offer can be doubted.  Madam Justice Kane wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 30px;">I do not accept the applicant’s argument that the factors in subsection 200(5) are the only factors that can be considered to determine the genuineness of a job offer or that they should be interpreted so narrowly that the Officer’s legitimate concerns about the genuineness of a job offer could not be considered. In addition, paragraph 200(5)(a), whether the offer is consistent with the reasonable employment needs of the employer, is a broad question which would include consideration of a range of relevant factors, including: the nature of the business; the nature of the particular employment offered; the size of the business; the volume of sales; and, the number of employees. In my view, it would not be consistent with the reasonable employment needs of an employer in a specialized area, such as a jewellery business, to offer employment to a person who has not provided objective evidence of their qualifications and experience and whose personal connection to the business owner appears to be a higher priority than the objective and legitimate needs of the employer and business owner for a qualified jewellery appraiser.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2022/2022fc1344/2022fc1344.html?autocompleteStr=2022%20FC%201344%20&amp;autocompletePos=1"><em>Dhaliwal v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 1344</a> Madam Justice Pallotta held that visa officers are required to independently assess the genuinness of job offers, including including whether the offer is consistent with the employer’s reasonable employment needs and whether its terms are ones the employer would be able to fulfill.</p>
<p>In <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/522700/index.do"><em>Jandu v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 1787</a>, Justice Diner held that this inquiry is not without limits and nuances, particualarly where a Labour Market Impact Assessment has already been obtained.  First, he noted that it is unreasonable to require prospective employees to provide sensitive business documentation that they could not be expected to possess.  Second, he noted that employers should be able to place some reliance on a positive Labour Market Impact Assessment from ESDC, and that it may be unreasonable for IRCC to not coordinate with ESDC when assessing genuineness factors that ESDC already assessed.  He wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">While there is no question that both departments have a duty to satisfy themselves of job offer genuineness, it is unreasonable to do so without any coordination. The absence of communication is akin to two ships passing in the night, which is particularly concerning where those ships belong to the same government fleet. And just as in this situation, where the second ship plans to chart a different course, one would expect a modicum of communication with the first. This could help to avoid navigational blind spots, on account of the failure to engage with either of the two parties who could have properly answered questions or responded to concerns (i.e. the employer, or ESDC).</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Questions related to the ability of the employer to pay prospective employees, or how its financials computed, how it planned to acquire trucks for the workers, what facilities they operated from, or how they would grow their business, could and should have been put to the employer, Daytona. Rather, IRCC put these questions to the Applicants, who were truck drivers from India, none of whom had ever visited Canada, and who also never consulted or received Daytona’s financial records in the Document Package sent directly to IRCC.</p>
<p>As well, absent further explanation, it would be unreasonable for officers to determine that an offer of employment is not genuine based on the fee that an applicant paid an immigration representative.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Regulations to Protect Foreign Workers</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/new-regulations-to-protect-foreign-workers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven Meurrens]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 19:29:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=13767</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On September 26, 2022, regulatory changes to Canadian immigration law took effect with the goal being to increase protections for temporary foreign workers.  All employers who currently employ, or wish to employ, foreign workers should understand these changes. In order to understand the changes, it is necessary to understand the distinction between the Temporary Foreign ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/new-regulations-to-protect-foreign-workers/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>On September 26, 2022, regulatory changes to Canadian immigration law took effect with the goal being to increase protections for temporary foreign workers.  All employers who currently employ, or wish to employ, foreign workers should understand these changes.</p>
<p>In order to understand the changes, it is necessary to understand the distinction between the Temporary Foreign Worker Program (the &#8220;TFWP&#8221;) and the International Mobility Program (the &#8220;IMP&#8221;).</p>
<p>In brief, the TFWP is a method of hiring foreign workers in which employers need to first obtain Labour Market Impact Assessments to demonstrate that the entry of the foreign workers will have a positive or neutral impact on the Canadian labour market. This is typically done through recruiting on prescribed locations for a four week period prior to applying, although there are recruitment exemptions.</p>
<p>The IMP consists of workers who are exempt from the requirement to obtain a Labour Market Impact Assessment.  Examples include free-trade agreements, International Experience Canada, provincial nominees, charitable and religious workers, and more.   Many more, in fact. Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada has almost one-hundred exemption categories.</p>
<p><strong>Providing Information to Foreign Workers About their Rights</strong></p>
<p>The change which will likely take most employers by surprise is that employers must provide foreign workers with up-to-date information about their rights in Canada.</p>
<p>To meet this requirement, employers will need to provide their employees with specific PDFs (or printed pamphlets) that are made available by the Government of Canada.  The PDF for employers hiring employees under the TFWP can be found <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/employment-social-development/services/foreign-workers/protected-rights.html">here</a>.  The PDF for employers hiring employees under the IMP can be found <a href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/corporate/publications-manuals/know-your-rights-worker-international-mobility-program.html">here</a>.  The information must be provided on or before the employee&#8217;s first day of work.</p>
<p>As well, employers must make the information available to foreign workers in both English and French available to their foreign workers throughout their period of employment.  The requirement that the information be available in both official languages applies regardless of whether employers have employees who speak both languages.</p>
<p><strong>Health and Safety</strong></p>
<p>Employers of foreign workers must now make reasonable efforts to provide access to health care services when a foreign worker is injured or becomes ill at the workplace. Reasonable efforts can include ensuring that there is a phone available to foreign workers to call emergency services or organizing (but not paying for) transportation to a hospital, clinic or doctor.</p>
<p>As well, employers in the TFWP must obtain and pay for private health insurance that covers emergency medical care during the period for which their foreign workers are not covered by their provincial or territorial health systems.</p>
<p><strong>Other Changes</strong></p>
<p>The remaining changes are more straight-forward, and most employers were probably already doing what is now required.</p>
<p>First, employers must have written employment agreements with their foreign workers that are signed by both employers and foreign workers.</p>
<p>Second, employers cannot retaliate against foreign workers who report abuse.</p>
<p>Third, employers are prohibited from charging or recovering fees for the provision of services in relation to Labour Market Impact Assessments, employer compliance fees or fees related to recruitment.</p>
<p><strong>Ensuring Compliance </strong></p>
<p>In order to enhance its ability to monitor compliance, the government will now have the ability to require that third parties, without the consent of the employer or worker, provide documentation relating to employer compliance.  As well, employers and affiliated entities who are not compliant can be banned from hiring employers, with especially stringent rules in the TFWP.</p>
<p>Canada&#8217;s immigration system increasingly relies on prospective immigrants first working in Canada as foreign workers and both the IMP and the TFWP have grown tremendously in recent years (with a brief drop during the COVID-19 pandemic).  This is unlikely to change in the near future, and as such, it is important that all foreign workers understand the September 26 changes now in effect.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Chinook</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/chinook/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Steven Meurrens]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 23:05:14 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=13758</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In addition to automated triaging Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (&#8220;IRCC&#8221;) has also introduced software so that officers can bulk process applications.  The software tool is known as Chinook. According to an affidavit that IRCC filed in Federal Court, Chinook is a standalone tool that streamlines administrative steps.  Applicant information is extracted from their applications ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/chinook/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>In addition to automated triaging Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (&#8220;IRCC&#8221;) has also introduced software so that officers can bulk process applications.  The software tool is known as Chinook.</p>
<p>According to an affidavit that IRCC filed in Federal Court, Chinook is a standalone tool that streamlines administrative steps.  Applicant information is extracted from their applications and presented in a spreadsheet. Visa officers are assigned a workload of applications through Chinook. They are able to see multiple applications at a time on a single spreadsheet.  This allows them to review the contents of multiple applications on a single screen, and allows them to complete administrative steps through batch processes.  It also allows visa officers to create “risk indicators” and “local word flags” so that officers can identify possible applications in the processing queue of concern or priority.</p>
<p>According to the Federal Court affidavit, when visa officers enter Chinook a message pops up which says, amongst other things, “The Chinook User Interface allows you to view multiple applications for review and initial assessment. It does not replace reviewing documents.. and/or reviewing other information… The refusal notes generator is meant to assist with general <em>bona fide </em>refusals. If the notes do not reflect your refusal reasons, please write an individual note.”</p>
<p>The Chinook user guide can be found here:</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/05/Chinook-User-Guide.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Chinook User Guide<br/></a>
<p>Another version specific to Modules 1 and 2 can be found here:</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/Modules-1-and-2.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Modules 1 and 2<br/></a>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Approaching Members of Parliament</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/approaching-members-of-parliament/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meurrens Law]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 13 Dec 2022 02:59:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Uncategorized]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=11641</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[A frequent question that people ask is what role their Member of Parliament can play in assisting them. Requests In my opinion, the biggest role an MP can play is getting a timely status update.  MPs typically can get an update in 48 hours, as opposed to 30 days for an Access to Information Act request or ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/approaching-members-of-parliament/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>A frequent question that people ask is what role their Member of Parliament can play in assisting them.</p>
<p><strong>Requests</strong></p>
<p>In my opinion, the biggest role an MP can play is getting a timely status update.  MPs typically can get an update in 48 hours, as opposed to 30 days for an <em>Access to Information Act </em>request or 14 days for a Case Specific Enquiry.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="wp-image-11642 aligncenter" src="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/02/Capture.png" alt="" width="978" height="232" /></p>
<p>The following PDF which was obtained through an <em>Access to Information Act </em>request contains IRCC guidance on handling requests from Members of Parliament.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/MP-Assistance.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">MP Assistance<br/></a>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/MP-Limits.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">MP Limits<br/></a>
<p><strong>Letters</strong></p>
<p>MPs can also write letters on files. As Justice Ahmed noted in <a href="https://decisia.lexum.com/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/307497/index.do"><em>Nagarasa v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2018 FC 313</a>, visa officers have to take these letters into consideration when assessing applications.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Humanitarian &#038; Compassionate Applications</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/humanitarian-compassionate-statistics/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meurrens Law]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 29 Nov 2022 00:08:29 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Humanitarian and Compassionate]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=11765</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[People who would not normally be eligible to become permanent residents of Canada may be able to apply on humanitarian and compassionate (&#8220;H&#38;C&#8220;) grounds. Humanitarian and compassionate grounds apply to people with exceptional cases. Here are 2020 approval statistics for humanitarian &#38; compassionate class applications. Sample Decisions Below are sample H&#38;C decisions that were used ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/humanitarian-compassionate-statistics/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>People who would not normally be eligible to become permanent residents of Canada may be able to apply on humanitarian and compassionate (&#8220;<strong>H&amp;C</strong>&#8220;) grounds.</p>
<p>Humanitarian and compassionate grounds apply to people with exceptional cases.</p>
<p>Here are 2020 approval statistics for humanitarian &amp; compassionate class applications.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/2A-2020-95301_Release-package.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">2A-2020-95301_Release package<br/></a>
<p><strong><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-12546 aligncenter" src="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/HCstats.png" alt="" width="502" height="243" /></strong></p>
<p><strong>Sample Decisions</strong></p>
<p>Below are sample H&amp;C decisions that were used in an Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada training session.</p>
<p>For each example, IRCC provided a chat to show a portion of the officer&#8217;s decision-making steps to describe context of the application.</p>
<p>As can be seen, a big deficiency in many H&amp;C applications is the applicant not providing documentary examples to substantiate their assertions in claim.</p>
<p>The H&amp;C requests were based on the following situations:</p>
<ul>
<li>Domestic violence in Mexico from two former partners</li>
<li>Discrimination in Japan</li>
<li>Criminal gangs in Honduras</li>
<li>Members of a drug cartel</li>
<li>Land dispute</li>
<li>Adverse country conditions in Bulgaria</li>
<li>Membership in a political party</li>
<li>Adverse country conditions in China</li>
<li>Adverse country conditions in Fiji</li>
<li>Religious discrimination in Bangladesh</li>
</ul>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/04/Sample-HC.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Sample H&amp;C<br/></a>
<p><strong>COVID-19</strong></p>
<p>In the following years there will likely be many humanitarian &amp; compassionate consideration applications filed by people who worked as front-line workers during COVID-19.  In <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/518678/index.do"><em>Mohammed v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 1</a>, Justice Ahmed made a statement about COVID-19 front-line workers in the humanitarian &amp; compassionate context. He wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">At a time when most people in Canada were staying at home to avoid the spread of COVID-19, frontline workers were risking their own health to provide essential services. This includes those who worked tirelessly in long-term care homes that saw frequent COVID-19 outbreaks and many deaths. The evidence before the IAD in this appeal included evidence demonstrating the heavy toll COVID-19 has taken on female immigrants working in health care.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">An employment letter on the record states that the Applicant has been employed at the Bethany Care Society since December 7, 2020 and is currently working as a Health Care Aide at Bethany Airdrie, a long-term care facility in Airdrie, Alberta. The letter states that the Applicant &#8220;“[…] maintains casual employment at Bethany with the ability to pick up additional shifts.”&#8221; As counsel for the Applicant aptly pointed out during the hearing, there was nothing casual about working at a long-term care facility during those times. This same facility was hit with a COVID-19 outbreak in early January 2021. Evidence before the IAD shows that on January 4, 2021, Bethany Airdrie reported 40 cases at the facility, including 19 employees and 21 residents, and the deaths of two residents from COVID-19. The entire facility remained under lockdown during this time.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">As a health care aide, the Applicant risked her own health and safety to support health-compromised and aging individuals. She is applying the very skills she acquired in Canada over a decade ago at a time when they are desperately needed, while not knowing if she herself will be able to stay in Canada. To frame this commitment and these contributions as only a &#8220;“moderately positive”&#8221; factor in the Applicant’s appeal is unintelligible.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The moral debt owed to immigrants who worked on the frontlines to help protect vulnerable people in Canada during the first waves of the COVID-19 pandemic cannot be understated. I do not find that the IAD gave this contribution the weight it deserved.</p>
<p><strong>The Ordinary Operation of the Law</strong></p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2022/2022fc961/2022fc961.html?autocompleteStr=2022%20FC%20961&amp;autocompletePos=1"><em>Kashyap v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 961</a>, Justice Diner addressed comments made by an officer in an H&amp;C decision, noting:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Furthermore, the remark about paying deference to the law and statutes of Canada suggests a significant misapprehension of the Officer’s role in evaluating a s 25(1) application, which is not to simply pay deference to the ordinary operation of the law, but to weigh and consider whether H&amp;C considerations warrant a flexible and responsive exception thereto (Kanthasamy v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration), 2015 SCC 61, at para 19 [Kanthasamy]).</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">First and foremost, the raison d’être of the H&amp;C exemption is to overcome non-compliance or other obstacles posed by immigration rules, by offering equitable relief in circumstances that “would excite in a reasonable [person] in a civilized community a desire to relieve the misfortunes of another” (Kanthasamy at para 21, citing Chirwa v Canada (Minister of Citizenship and Immigration) (1970), 4 I.A.C. 338 at p 350).</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">There were compassionate circumstances here that the Applicant submitted but the Officer simply did not address, instead reciting a need to be deferential to the law – which, again, includes an exception contained in s 25(1) of the Act. The Officer is owed significant deference in making this highly discretionary determination, but not to the point of failing to weigh all the relevant facts and factors before them (Kanthasamy at para 25).</p>
<p><strong>Discrimination</strong></p>
<p>In <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/scc/doc/2015/2015scc61/2015scc61.html?resultIndex=1"><em>Kanthasamy v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2015 SCC 61</a> Justice Abella, writing for the majority, stated that  direct evidence is not necessary to establish potential discrimination and related hardship.  She wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">The Officer agreed to consider the hardship Jeyakannan Kanthasamy would likely endure as discrimination in Sri Lanka against young Tamil men. She also accepted evidence that there was discrimination against Tamils in Sri Lanka, particularly against young Tamil men from the north, who are routinely targeted by police. In her view, however, young Tamils are targeted only where there is suspicion of ties to the Liberation Tigers of Tamil Eelam, and the government had been making efforts to improve the situation for Tamils. She concluded that “the onus remains on the applicant to demonstrate that these country conditions would affect him personally”.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">This effectively resulted in the Officer concluding that, in the absence of evidence that Jeyakannan Kanthasamy would be personally targeted by discriminatory action, there was no evidence of discrimination. With respect, the Officer’s approach failed to account for the fact that discrimination can be inferred where an applicant shows that he or she is a member of a group that is discriminated against. Discrimination for the purpose of humanitarian and compassionate applications “could manifest in isolated incidents or permeate systemically”, and even “[a] series of discriminatory events that do not give rise to persecution must be considered cumulatively”: Jamie Chai Yun Liew and Donald Galloway, Immigration Law (2nd ed. 2015), at p. 413, citing Divakaran v. Canada (Minister of Citizenship and Immigration), 2011 FC 633.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Here, however, the Officer required Jeyakannan Kanthasamy to present direct evidence that he would face such a risk of discrimination if deported. This not only undermines the humanitarian purpose of s. 25(1), it reflects an anemic view of discrimination that this Court largely eschewed decades ago: Andrews v. Law Society of British Columbia, [1989] 1 S.C.R. 143, at pp. 173-74; British Columbia (Public Service Employee Relations Commission) v. BCGSEU, [1999] 3 S.C.R. 3; Quebec (Attorney General) v. A, [2013] 1 S.C.R. 61, at paras. 318-19 and 321-38.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">Even the Guidelines, expressly relying on this Court’s decision in Andrews, encourage an approach to discrimination that does not require evidence that the applicant will be personally targeted:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">5.16. [Humanitarian and compassionate] and hardship: Factors in the country of origin to be considered</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">While [ss. 96 and 97] factors may not be considered, the decision-maker must take into account elements related to the hardships that affect the foreign national. Some examples of what those “hardships” may include are: […]
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">• discrimination which does not amount to persecution; […]
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">• adverse country conditions that have a direct negative impact on the applicant. […]
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">Discrimination</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">Discrimination is: A distinction based on the personal characteristics of an individual that results in some disadvantage to that individual.</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">In Andrews, [the] Court wrote:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">“Discrimination may be described as a distinction, whether intentional or not but based on grounds relating to personal characteristics of the individual or group, which has the effect of imposing burdens, obligations, or disadvantages on such individual or group not imposed upon others, or which withholds or limits access to opportunities, benefits, and advantages available to other members of society. Distinctions based on personal characteristics attributed to an individual solely on the basis of association with a group will rarely escape the charge of discrimination, while those based on an individual’s merits and capacities will rarely be so classed.”</p>
<p style="padding-left: 80px;">(Inland Processing, s. 5.16)</p>
<p>In <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/522391/index.do"><em>Kaur v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 1483</a>, Justice Brown reiterated that it is contrary to <em>Kanthasamy</em> to require that applicants provide corroroborating evidence that they would experience discrimination.</p>
<p>While there is a split in the jurisprudence on this, in <a href="https://decisions.fct-cf.gc.ca/fc-cf/decisions/en/item/522515/index.do"><em>Al-Aswadi v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 1623</a>, Justice Favel noted that:</p>
<p style="padding-left: 40px;">To reiterate, it is an error for an officer to limit their assessment of hardship in an applicant’s home country to hardship connected to a personal characteristic. This error confuses the criteria applicable to an H&amp;C application under subsection 25(1) of IRPA with those that define a person in need of protection under subsection 97(1) of IRPA (Marafa at para 4; Quiros v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration), 2021 FC 1412 at paras 30-31; Aboubacar v Canada (Citizenship and Immigration), 2014 FC 714 at para 4).</p>
<p><strong>Ad-Hoc H&amp;C Requests</strong></p>
<p>As Justice Manson noted in <a href="https://www.canlii.org/en/ca/fct/doc/2022/2022fc1527/2022fc1527.html?resultIndex=1"><em>Aryan v. Canada (Citizenship and Immigration)</em>, 2022 FC 152</a>, while ordinarily H&amp;C applications take the form of a parallel application accompanying a permanent residence application, H&amp;C requests made ad hoc in the course of other imigration applications must be considered.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Inside Canada vs. Outside Canada Sponsorship Process</title>
		<link>https://meurrensonimmigration.com/the-inside-canada-vs-outside-canada-sponsorship-process/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Meurrens Law]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 26 Nov 2022 18:14:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Family Class (Spousal Sponsorships, Parents & Grandparents)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[12]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[124]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Family Class]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Inside Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Outside Canada]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">http://meurrensonimmigration.com/?p=6040</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[One of the quirkier features of Canadian immigration law is the distinction between what is generally referred to as the &#8220;Inside-Canada Sponsorship&#8221; process and the &#8220;Outside-Canada Sponsorship&#8221; process.  The biggest myth is that if a couple is residing in Canada then they must use the &#8220;Inside-Canada Sponsorship&#8221; process.  This is not true.  However, each program ... <a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/the-inside-canada-vs-outside-canada-sponsorship-process/" class="more-link">Read More</a>]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<p>One of the quirkier features of Canadian immigration law is the distinction between what is generally referred to as the &#8220;Inside-Canada Sponsorship&#8221; process and the &#8220;Outside-Canada Sponsorship&#8221; process.  The biggest myth is that if a couple is residing in Canada then they must use the &#8220;Inside-Canada Sponsorship&#8221; process.  This is not true.  However, each program contains advantages and disadvantages vis-a-vis the other, and I have provided a list of the key features and requirements of each program below.</p>
<p>&nbsp;</p>
<table>
<tbody>
<tr>
<td width="319">
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Inside-Canada Process</strong></p>
</td>
<td width="319">
<p style="text-align: center;"><strong>Outside-Canada Process</strong></p>
</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">The spouse/common-law partner must be in a genuine, conjugal relationship that was not entered into for the primary purpose of acquiring an immigration benefit.</td>
<td width="319">The spouse/common-law partner must be in a genuine, conjugal relationship that was not entered into for the primary purpose of acquiring an immigration benefit.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">The spouse/common-law partner must reside together in Canada.</td>
<td width="319">The spouse/common-law partner do not have to reside together in Canada.  As well, once a common-law relationship is established, periods of separation will not change their common-law status if there is a short separation that does not sever the common-law partnership.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">The applicant must live with the spouse/common-law partner inside Canada during the duration of processing.</td>
<td width="319">The applicant can live with the spouse/common-law partner inside Canada during the duration of processing, but does not have to.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">The immigration paperwork is sent to a processing center inside Canada, and remains in Canada.</td>
<td width="319">The immigration paperwork is sent to a processing center inside Canada, and it then may be transferred to a visa post outside of Canada.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">If the applicant has valid temporary resident status in Canada, and submits an application to extend that status inside Canada with the permanent residence application, then the applicant will have implied status during the processing of the permanent residence application, provided he/she does not leave Canada.</td>
<td width="319">If the applicant has valid temporary resident status in Canada, he/she must maintain his/her status. The process is separate from the permanent residence application, and there is no implied status for the duration of processing.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada will process the application even if the applicant does not have valid temporary resident status in Canada.  If an individual has an application in processing, and is detained by the Canada Border Services Agency for being without status, then the applicant will generally benefit from a 60 day deferral period, and Citizenship and Immigration Canada will endeavour to process the permanent residence application within 60 days.</td>
<td width="319">Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada will not process the application if the applicant does not have valid temporary resident status in Canada.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">The current processing time is 12 months.  The Applicant will receive “first-stage approval” at around the half-way point if it is determined that the spouse/common-law partnership is bona fide, and the applicant will be entitled to an open work permit.</td>
<td width="319">Processing times vary depending on the visa post, and range from 4 months to 38 months.   There is no first-stage approval for the issuance of open work permits.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">There is currently a pilot project in place to provide work permits to applicants who have valid temporary resident status after 2ish months of processing.</td>
<td width="319">The permanent residence application is completely separate from any ability to work in Canada.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">There is no appeal right to the Immigration Appeal Division.  The only recourse is an application to Federal Court for judicial review.</td>
<td width="319">There is a general appeal right to the Immigration Appeal Division, except for refusals based on serious criminality, terrorism, national security, espionage, and similar serious matters.  The only recourse in those situations is an application to Federal Court for judicial review.</td>
</tr>
<tr>
<td width="319">If the applicant leaves Canada and is for whatever reason denied re-entry by the Canada Border Services Agency, then the permanent residence application will be refused, and the applicant must start over from outside Canada.</td>
<td width="319">If the applicant leaves Canada and is for whatever reason denied re-entry by the Canada Border Services Agency, this will generally not impact the permanent residence application.</td>
</tr>
</tbody>
</table>
<p><strong>Children Abroad</strong></p>
<p>Section 5.11 of Citizenship and Immigration Canada&#8217;s Inland Processing Manual 8 &#8211; Spouse or Common Law Partner in Canada states that:</p>
<blockquote><p>For dependent children living outside Canada, the [Case Processing Centre &#8211; Vegreville] will forward a copy of the permanent residence application listing the dependent children and their relevant contact information to the responsible visa office for verification of the relationship, once the sponsor and applicant have been assessed and approved against eligibility requirements.</p>
<p>The visa office will determine admissibility of dependent children outside Canada, conduct interviews if necessary and advise the CPC-V of the outcome by updating the electronic record.  The CPC then informs the CIC [office] responsible for the applicant’s place of residence that permanent residence may be granted.  Once the CIC [office] has granted permanent residence to the principal applicant, it will notify the visa office, which will issue permanent resident visas to the overseas dependent children who are seeking permanent residence.</p></blockquote>
<p>There are many differences between the Inside Canada Sponsorship and the outside Canada sponsorship.  Whether children outside of Canada can accompany the principal applicant in the same application is not one of them.</p>
<p><strong>Statistics</strong></p>
<p>Please note that the statistics below were obtained through an <em>Access to Information Act </em>request.</p>
<p>The following are some statistics regarding the approval rate for the Inside-Canada Spousal Sponsorship program.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-13717" src="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideApproval1-1024x616.png" alt="" width="846" height="509" srcset="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideApproval1-1024x616.png 1024w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideApproval1-300x180.png 300w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideApproval1-768x462.png 768w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideApproval1-100x60.png 100w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideApproval1-846x509.png 846w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideApproval1-1184x712.png 1184w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideApproval1-600x361.png 600w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideApproval1.png 1206w" sizes="(max-width: 846px) 100vw, 846px" /></p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-13718" src="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideCanadaApproval2-1024x108.png" alt="" width="846" height="89" srcset="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideCanadaApproval2-1024x108.png 1024w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideCanadaApproval2-300x32.png 300w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideCanadaApproval2-768x81.png 768w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideCanadaApproval2-100x11.png 100w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideCanadaApproval2-846x89.png 846w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideCanadaApproval2-1184x125.png 1184w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideCanadaApproval2-600x63.png 600w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2015/03/InsideCanadaApproval2.png 1186w" sizes="(max-width: 846px) 100vw, 846px" /></p>
<p>The following shows the approval rates for the Inside-Canada sponsorship process vs. the Outside-Canada sponsorship process.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-large wp-image-13721" src="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Inside-Canada-vs.-Outside-Canada-1024x466.png" alt="" width="846" height="385" srcset="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Inside-Canada-vs.-Outside-Canada-1024x466.png 1024w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Inside-Canada-vs.-Outside-Canada-300x137.png 300w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Inside-Canada-vs.-Outside-Canada-768x350.png 768w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Inside-Canada-vs.-Outside-Canada-100x46.png 100w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Inside-Canada-vs.-Outside-Canada-846x385.png 846w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Inside-Canada-vs.-Outside-Canada-1184x539.png 1184w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Inside-Canada-vs.-Outside-Canada-600x273.png 600w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Inside-Canada-vs.-Outside-Canada.png 1373w" sizes="(max-width: 846px) 100vw, 846px" /></p>
<p>The following shows temporary resident visa vs. electronic travel authorization approval rates for those with Family Class applications in processing.</p>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-13725" src="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Capture1.png" alt="" width="782" height="595" srcset="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Capture1.png 782w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Capture1-300x228.png 300w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Capture1-768x584.png 768w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Capture1-100x76.png 100w, https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Capture1-600x457.png 600w" sizes="(max-width: 782px) 100vw, 782px" /></p>
<p>Here are the statistics for Inside-Canada spousal sponsorship approval rates based on country of citizenship for 2019 &#8211; 2021.</p>
<a href="https://meurrensonimmigration.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/11/Approvals-Country-of-Origin.pdf" class="pdfemb-viewer" style="" data-width="max" data-height="max" data-mobile-width="0"  data-scrollbar="none" data-download="on" data-tracking="on" data-newwindow="on" data-pagetextbox="off" data-scrolltotop="off" data-startzoom="100" data-startfpzoom="100" data-toolbar="bottom" data-toolbar-fixed="off">Approvals Country of Origin<br/></a>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
