<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>The Business Immigrant</title>
	<atom:link href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/</link>
	<description>information, ideas and insights for Canada’s immigrant entrepreneurs.</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 07:13:45 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	<generator>https://wordpress.org/?v=6.1.1</generator>

<image>
	<url>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2021/03/cropped-BIs-1-4-70x70.png</url>
	<title>The Business Immigrant</title>
	<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Goldman Sachs plans to hire 3,000 graduates and skilled immigrants</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/goldman-sachs-plans-to-hire-3000-graduates/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/goldman-sachs-plans-to-hire-3000-graduates/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 07:13:45 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Banking jobs canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Goldman Sachs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Goldman Sachs 2023 recruitment]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Goldman Sachs plans to hire]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5817</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Banking jobs will never go out of fashion Fresh graduates and highly skilled immigrants looking for a career in banking and finance, can apply for jobs at Goldman Sachs , a leading global investment banking, securities and investment management firm. Goldman Sachs plans to hire over 3,000 graduates and other skilled professionals this year. The bank said the recent job cuts have resized its footprint for the current economic environment and it will continue to hire at all levels of the firm. In a Bloomberg Television interview at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Goldman Sachs’ International Head, Richard Gnodde [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/goldman-sachs-plans-to-hire-3000-graduates/">Goldman Sachs plans to hire 3,000 graduates and skilled immigrants</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><em>Banking jobs will never go out of fashion</em></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-5818 size-full" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T080807.017.jpeg" alt="Goldman Sachs plans to hire 3,000 graduates and skilled immigrants" width="600" height="600" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T080807.017.jpeg 600w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T080807.017-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T080807.017-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T080807.017-70x70.jpeg 70w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T080807.017-180x180.jpeg 180w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T080807.017-400x400.jpeg 400w" sizes="(max-width: 600px) 100vw, 600px" /></p>
<p>Fresh graduates and highly skilled immigrants looking for a career in banking and finance, can apply for jobs at Goldman Sachs , a leading global investment banking, securities and investment management firm.</p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/looking-to-find-a-job-go-to-these-top-job-search-sites/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Goldman Sachs plans to hire over 3,000 graduates</a></span> and other skilled professionals this year.</p>
<p>The bank said the recent job cuts have resized its footprint for the current economic environment and it will continue to hire at all levels of the firm.</p>
<p>In a Bloomberg Television interview at the World Economic Forum in Davos, Goldman Sachs’ International Head, Richard Gnodde said: “We’ve sized the firm to suit what we think the outlook will be. But of course you have to be nimble.”</p>
<p>He said the firm will adapt to the environment but it continues to hire people and expects to add more than 3,000 graduates this year as well as more selectively at all levels of the firm.</p>
<p>The industrywide slowdown and threat of a recession later this year pushed the bank’s leaders to ax as many as 3,200 jobs last week. But the bank is still committed to injecting fresh talent into the organization.</p>
<p>With revenues exceeding $47.37 billion, The Goldman Sachs Group, provides a wide range of financial services to a substantial and diversified client base that includes corporations, financial institutions, governments and individuals.</p>
<p><strong>Reference:</strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/quote/GS:US" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bloomberg</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.goldmansachs.com/careers/index.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Goldman Sachs</a></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/goldman-sachs-plans-to-hire-3000-graduates/">Goldman Sachs plans to hire 3,000 graduates and skilled immigrants</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/goldman-sachs-plans-to-hire-3000-graduates/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>How do you compare with the 30 richest families in Canada?</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/how-do-you-compare-with-the-30-richest-families-in-canada/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/how-do-you-compare-with-the-30-richest-families-in-canada/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 07:03:11 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Money]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[30 richest families in Canada]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5810</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>“The rich guy buys a football team, the poor buys a football. Wealth is all relative.” Have you calculated your net worth recently? Ever wondered what’s it’s like to be a billionaire? Comparing your wealth with the 30 wealthiest families in Canada should inspire and not intimidate. To get a sense of which families really run this country, here’s a list of the richest clans in Canada, some of whom are immigrants to Canada. Thomson family With a combined net worth of US$49.2 billion, the Thomson family is the richest family in Canada, and the 26th-richest family in the world, [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/how-do-you-compare-with-the-30-richest-families-in-canada/">How do you compare with the 30 richest families in Canada?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><em>“The rich guy buys a football team, the poor buys a football. Wealth is all relative.”</em></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-5812 size-full" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T075228.905.jpeg" alt="How do you compare with the 30 richest families in Canada?" width="2410" height="2543" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T075228.905.jpeg 2410w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T075228.905-284x300.jpeg 284w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T075228.905-970x1024.jpeg 970w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T075228.905-768x810.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T075228.905-1456x1536.jpeg 1456w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T075228.905-1941x2048.jpeg 1941w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T075228.905-800x844.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 2410px) 100vw, 2410px" /></p>
<p>Have you calculated your net worth recently? Ever wondered what’s it’s like <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/10-surprising-assets-that-can-improve-your-net-worth/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">to be a billionaire</a></span>? Comparing your wealth with the 30 wealthiest families in Canada should inspire and not intimidate.</p>
<p>To get a sense of which <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/6-ways-to-create-protect-and-preserve-your-family-wealth/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">families really run this country</a></span>, here’s a list of the richest clans in Canada, some of whom are immigrants to Canada.</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h6>Thomson family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>With a combined net worth of US$49.2 billion, the Thomson family is the richest family in Canada, and the 26th-richest family in the world, according to the annual Forbes Billionaires ranking.</p>
<p>Now the Thomsons own a long list of media, publishing, pharmaceutical, and financial services companies through the Thomson Reuters Corporation. The family is still based in Toronto.</p>
<ol start="2">
<li>
<h6>Weston family (Loblaws)</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The Weston family’s empire started with a single bakery in Toronto in 1882 and has grown to encompass well-known companies in industries from food to high fashion.</p>
<p>The family owns Loblaws (the biggest supermarket chain in Canada), Holt Renfrew, Shoppers Drug Mart/Pharmaprix, and more instantly recognizable brands across Canada through George Weston Limited, which is currently chaired by Galen G. Weston. The Westons’ net worth is approximately US$15.8 billion.</p>
<ol start="3">
<li>
<h6>Rogers family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Easily one of the most recognizable names in Canada, Rogers Communications has its fingers in everything from television and broadcasting, where it owns Citytv, Omni, and a handful of specialty TV and radio stations, to cable service and wireless cellular communications.</p>
<p>If you own a smartphone or watch any type of major-league sport on TV, streaming or live, you’ve come across this prominent family name. Rogers is largely controlled by the Rogers Control Trust, several of whose members are descendants of Edward S. Rogers Sr. He invented the batteryless radio in 1925 and later went on to manufacture radios and found the CFRB radio station.</p>
<p>The family’s fortune is estimated at about US$10 billion.</p>
<ol start="4">
<li>
<h6>Saputo family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>With a combined net worth of US$5.1 billion, the Quebec-based Saputo family is a prime example of the generational rags-to-riches immigrant story.</p>
<p>Now one of the top 10 dairy processors in the world, Saputo was founded as a small cheesemaking company in 1954 by patriarch Giuseppe Saputo in Montreal, with nothing more than $500 and a bicycle to make deliveries.</p>
<p>The company is chaired by Lino A. Saputo, Giuseppe’s grandson, and is active in over 60 countries. The family is ranked in 586th place on the Forbes Billionaires list.</p>
<ol start="5">
<li>
<h6>Desmarais family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>As a young man, Paul Desmarais bought and rescued Sudbury Bus Lines, an unprofitable business owned by his parents. He then took over bus lines in Gatineau and Quebec City before buying the conglomerate Trans-Canada Corp Fund in 1965. In 1968, he became chairman and CEO of the Power Corporation of Canada.</p>
<p>In 1996, Desmarais made his two sons, Paul Jr. and André, co-chief executive officers of Power Corp. When he died in 2013, he had an estimated net worth of US$4.5 billion.</p>
<ol start="6">
<li>
<h6>Irving family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The New Brunswick-based Irving family in its current empire is descended from James Dergavel Irving, who bought the family’s first sawmill in 1881.</p>
<p>Future generations expanded the company, moving from the sawmill business to forestry, and later, to energy (Irving Oil was founded in 1924) and media (the family owns Brunswick News, which operates almost all of New Brunswick’s major print publications).</p>
<ol start="7">
<li>
<h6>Richardson family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Now five generations old, the Richardson family empire includes holdings in agriculture, oil and gas, financial services, and real estate, a far cry from James Richardson’s origins as a grain trader in the 1850s.</p>
<p>Today, the family’s Winnipeg-based firm, James Richardson &amp; Sons, Limited, is headed by Hartley T. Richardson.</p>
<ol start="8">
<li>
<h6>Azrieli family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The Azrieli family made their billions in the real estate sector in Canada and Israel.</p>
<p>Founder David Azrieli built his empire after fleeing Nazi-occupied Poland and eventually making his way to Montreal in the 1950s. When he died in 2014, the family’s net worth was estimated at US$2.9 billion. Azrieli’s daughters Naomi and Sharon currently sit on the board of the Azrieli Foundation, which funds a wide range of organizations in Canada and Israel.</p>
<ol start="9">
<li>
<h6>Katz family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The Edmonton-based Daryl Katz is no stranger to drugstore shelves. His father, Barry, helped found the Value Drug Mart Associates chain of pharmacies, and after Daryl was old enough to join the family business, the father and son duo went on to purchase the Canadian franchise rights to the Medicine Shoppe.</p>
<p>Later, the Katz family also bought Rexall, expanding it into a major player in the U.S. and in Canada. Now active in real estate and sports (Katz owns the Edmonton Oilers), Daryl Katz has a net worth of US$4.3 billion.</p>
<ol start="10">
<li>
<h6>Lee-Chin family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>A self-made billionaire, Michael Lee-Chin moved to Canada from his native Jamaica in the 1970s. While working as a mutual fund salesman, he took out a loan to buy into Mackenzie Investments—and it paid off.</p>
<p>Since then, Lee-Chin has grown his fortune investing in companies such as AIC Limited and Jamaica’s National Commercial Bank. His estimated net worth is US$1.7 billion.</p>
<ol start="11">
<li>
<h6>Gaglardi family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Bob Gaglardi started his empire when he opened the first Sandman Inn hotel in 1967.</p>
<p>Gaglardi went on to establish more Sandman Inn hotels across Canada and expanded into real estate and restaurants. His family is now one of Canada’s wealthiest, with his net worth estimated at US$3.2 billion. Along with his son Tom, he bought the Dallas Stars hockey team for $240 million in 2011.</p>
<ol start="12">
<li>
<h6>Apostolopoulos family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Before he died in 2021, Andreas Apostolopoulos built his estimated US$4 billion fortune through his real estate corporation, Triple Group of Companies, which was known for buying up large industrial properties in unassuming areas of Detroit and fixing them up.</p>
<p>Headed by Apostolopoulos and his three sons, Steve, Jim, and Peter, the company bought the Pontiac Silverdome (pictured) and the Penobscot Building, both in Michigan.</p>
<ol start="13">
<li>
<h6>Zekelman family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Zekelman Industries is one of the largest steel pipe and tube manufacturers in North America.</p>
<p>The company is owned by Windsor-born Barry Zekelman and his two brothers, Clayton and Alan. Barry Zekelman serves as chair and CEO and has an estimated net worth of US$3.3 billion. He’s also an avid race car driver who frequently turns up at races in his Ferrari.</p>
<ol start="14">
<li>
<h6>Mannix family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Calgary-based brothers Fred and Ron Mannix have inherited over a hundred years of generational wealth. Their grandfather, Frederick Stephen Mannix, was a railroad contractor before founding the Fred Mannix Company in 1936.</p>
<p>His son, Fred Charles Mannix, became a partner at the construction company in his 30s, and expanded the business to include all manner of infrastructure building, from pipelines to highways.</p>
<p>Fred Charles Mannix later handed the reins to his two sons, Fred and Ron, who continued to grow the business before selling off most of their energy assets.</p>
<ol start="15">
<li>
<h6>Aquilini family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Luigi Aquilini came to Vancouver from Italy in the mid-1950s and started his own construction company before getting into real estate development. Over the next few decades, he built Aquilini Investment Group into one of the most successful businesses in Canada.</p>
<p>Today, Luigi’s sons and several of his grandchildren are involved with the company. With investment arms in industries ranging from real estate development to renewable energy to food and wine, the Aquilini family are well secured for future generations ahead.</p>
<ol start="16">
<li>
<h6>Coutu family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Jean Coutu was the son of a pediatrician in Montreal and opened his first pharmacy in 1969.</p>
<p>The drugstore chain now has over 400 franchised locations in Quebec, New Brunswick, and Ontario.</p>
<p>The family, including Jean Coutu’s son François Jean (who was president of the Jean Coutu Group until his retirement in 2019), has a combined net worth of US$3.2 billion.</p>
<ol start="17">
<li>
<h6>Gerry Schwartz and Heather Reisman</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Heather Reisman, the woman behind Heather’s Picks at Indigo stores, is the founder and chief executive of Indigo Books and Music, as well as the co-founder of the Kobo e-book business.</p>
<p>Her husband Gerald Schwartz, whose personal net worth is US$1.3 billion, owns the private equity company Onex.</p>
<ol start="18">
<li>
<h6>Lalji family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The extremely private Lalji family has quietly amassed a fortune after buying up larger and larger pieces of real estate in Vancouver. Brothers Amin, Mansoor, and Shiraz are originally from Uganda but fled in the 1970s when Idi Amin expelled tens of thousands of Asians from the country.</p>
<p>Through their company Larco Investments, the Laljis have bought a number of hotels, malls, and office buildings in B.C., as well as several buildings in Ottawa, including the Château Laurier (pictured).</p>
<ol start="19">
<li>
<h6>Stronach family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>As Notorious B.I.G. wisely said, “Mo’ money, mo’ problems,” and nowhere is that more true than in the Stronach family.</p>
<p>In 2019, intra-family disputes led to major courtroom drama between billionaire patriarch Frank Stronach, who made his fortune in auto-parts manufacturing, and his daughter Belinda, whom he had groomed to take over as his successor.</p>
<p>Father and daughter eventually struck a deal wherein they each took control of some of the family’s business assets, but other family members have since filed their own lawsuits to dispute the settlement.</p>
<ol start="20">
<li>
<h6>Wilson family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The Vancouver-based Wilson family, which includes father Chip, his wife Shannon, and their sons, first made their fortune from the internationally recognized athletic apparel company Lululemon Athletica.</p>
<p>Since Chip stepped down from the board of the brand he founded, the family has moved on to other ventures, managing their various businesses and philanthropic initiatives through their company Hold It All Inc.</p>
<ol start="21">
<li>
<h6>Sobey family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The Sobey family has a long history in Nova Scotia, where J.W. Sobey founded a meat delivery business, carting livestock from local farmers to customers with a horse-drawn carriage in 1907.</p>
<p>Not long after, the family business expanded to include vegetables and more groceries, leading to the establishment of the Sobeys chain of stores in 1939. By 1987, the company had made its first billion dollars in sales; today, it’s worth over C$25 billion.</p>
<ol start="22">
<li>
<h6>Bombardier family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>In 1937, Joseph-Armand Bombardier created a seven-passenger snowmobile. The vehicle—designed to help people travel across the snowy roads of rural Quebec—was a hit, and Bombardier’s company would go on to manufacture more models, including the famous Ski-Doo.</p>
<p>Since then, the company has grown exponentially, branching out into the railway and aerospace sectors. Laurent Beaudoin (pictured), the son-in-law of Joseph-Armand Bombardier, was the company’s longtime CEO and chairman before he stepped down in 2019.</p>
<ol start="23">
<li>
<h6>Rossy family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Four generations have helmed the retail business that operates today as discount goods chain Dollarama. The business originated in 1910, when Salim Rossy opened a small general store in Montreal.</p>
<p>The network of S. Rossy Inc. stores grew slowly until 1992, when Salim’s grandson, Larry, opened the first Dollarama in Matane, Quebec.</p>
<p>There are now more than 1,200 Dollarama stores across Canada. The company is headed by Larry’s son, Neil Rossy, who reportedly made nearly C$8 million in 2021.</p>
<ol start="24">
<li>
<h6>Reichmann family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>After immigrating to Canada from Morocco in the 1950s, brothers Paul and Albert Reichmann founded Olympia &amp; York Developments Ltd.</p>
<p>In 1975, Olympia &amp; York built the 72-storey First Canadian Place in Toronto, which was then the tallest skyscraper in Canada. In the 1980s, the company took on high-profile development projects in New York City and London.</p>
<p>Olympia &amp; York went bankrupt in the 1990s following a global real estate crash, but the Reichmanns were able to partly rebuild their fortune.</p>
<ol start="25">
<li>
<h6>Southern family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The Calgary-based corporation, which provides services in the energy, housing, transportation, and infrastructure sectors, was founded in 1947 as a trailer-hire company to service Alberta’s oil industry.</p>
<p>Before he died in 2016, Ronald Southern had a net worth of US$1.55 billion.</p>
<ol start="26">
<li>
<h6>Slaight family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The late media magnate Allan Slaight made his fortune in broadcasting, having owned dozens of radio stations as the head of Slaight Communications and Standard Broadcasting Corporation. His son, Gary Slaight, now runs the Slaight Family Foundation and Slaight Music, which support a variety of charities and causes.</p>
<p>In 2013, the Slaight family donated C$50 million to the Princess Margaret Cancer Centre; in 2017, the family’s foundation donated C$12 million to not-for-profit organizations working to support Indigenous communities across Canada.</p>
<ol start="27">
<li>
<h6>Bronfman family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The Bronfman family amassed their fortune in the distillery business at an opportune time. Samuel Bronfman founded the Distillers Corporation Limited in 1924, later buying out his competitor Seagram and exporting liquor to the United States during and after the Prohibition era.</p>
<p>Over the next few decades, the company expanded around the world. In 2000, Samuel’s son Charles Bronfman and grandson Edgar Bronfman Jr. sold Seagram for US$30 billion.</p>
<p>Charles Bronfman has an estimated net worth of $2.5 billion</p>
<ol start="28">
<li>
<h6>Leon family (Leon’s and The Brick)</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>One of the most prominent families in Canada, the Leons also run one of the biggest family businesses: Leon’s Furniture Limited. Now one of the country’s largest retailers, the company started out as a general store founded by Ablan Leon in 1909.</p>
<p>Ablan Leon’s son Anthony and grandson Terry (pictured) each served as CEO for many years. Terry oversaw the company’s acquisition of The Brick, another Canadian furniture retailer, in 2013.</p>
<ol start="29">
<li>
<h6>Molson family</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The Molson family empire was launched in 1786 with the establishment of the Molson Brewery, the oldest brewery in North America.</p>
<p>A true pioneer, John Molson also helped create the first steamship and the first railway in British North America. Seven generations later, the Molsons remain one of Canada’s most well-known families. Geoff Molson along with his brothers Andrew and Justin, is the owner of the Montreal Canadiens hockey team.</p>
<ol start="30">
<li>
<h6>Gerald Schwartz</h6>
</li>
</ol>
<p>Owner of Onex, one of Canada’s largest private equity firms, Schwartz has worked with some of the biggest buyout legends in history, such as Henry Kravis and Jerome Kohlberg. He is now chairman and CEO of the firm and manages a staggering C$53 billion.</p>
<p>His family’s net worth is around $2 billion.</p>
<h4>Money quotes for thought</h4>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-5811 size-full" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T075230.843.jpeg" alt="How do you compare with the 30 richest families in Canada?" width="2400" height="1830" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T075230.843.jpeg 2400w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T075230.843-300x229.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T075230.843-1024x781.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T075230.843-768x586.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T075230.843-1536x1171.jpeg 1536w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T075230.843-2048x1562.jpeg 2048w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-2023-01-25T075230.843-800x610.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 2400px) 100vw, 2400px" /></p>
<ul>
<li>“If you want to get rich quicker, then solve bigger problems!” &#8211; Robert Kivosaki</li>
<li>“Analyze your money mistakes. You’ve already paid the tuition, you might as well get the lesson.” &#8211; Tim Fargo</li>
<li>“After a rich man gets rich, his next ambition is to get richer.” &#8211; Proverbs</li>
<li>“It’s not your salary that makes you rich, it’s your spending habits.” &#8211; Charles Jaffe</li>
<li>“Failure defeats losers, failure inspires winners.” &#8211; Robert Kivosaki</li>
<li>“Sight is what you see with your eyes. Vision is what you see with your mind.” &#8211; Robert Kivosaki</li>
<li>“My poor dad often said, I’d rather be happy than rich. My rich dad said, why not be both?” &#8211; Robert Kivosaki</li>
</ul>
<p><strong>Reference:</strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.msn.com/en-ca/news/finance-top-stories/the-richest-families-in-canada/ss-AA15fpnO#image=1" target="_blank" rel="noopener">MSN</a></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/how-do-you-compare-with-the-30-richest-families-in-canada/">How do you compare with the 30 richest families in Canada?</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/how-do-you-compare-with-the-30-richest-families-in-canada/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Canadian house prices drop to their lowest level as recession fear looms</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canadian-house-prices-drop-to-their-lowest-level-as-recession-fear-looms/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canadian-house-prices-drop-to-their-lowest-level-as-recession-fear-looms/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 06:38:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Real Estate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Canadian home prices]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Canadian Real Estate Association]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5806</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>The fear of recession is not the beginning of wisdom Canadian home prices saw the biggest price decline for a calendar year since records began, with a 7.5% drop over a one year period. Home prices crashed as rapidly rising interest rates forced a market adjustment that may have further to go. The country’s benchmark home price fell 1.6% in December to $730,600, bringing the total decrease since February’s peak to 13.2%, the Canadian Real Estate Association said. It was the biggest peak-to-trough falloff since the group started compiling the data in 2005 With the economy in danger of entering [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canadian-house-prices-drop-to-their-lowest-level-as-recession-fear-looms/">Canadian house prices drop to their lowest level as recession fear looms</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><em>The fear of recession is not the beginning of wisdom</em></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5808" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T073052.786.jpeg" alt="" width="1920" height="1264" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T073052.786.jpeg 1920w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T073052.786-300x198.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T073052.786-1024x674.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T073052.786-768x506.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T073052.786-1536x1011.jpeg 1536w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image0-2023-01-25T073052.786-800x527.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></p>
<p>Canadian home prices saw the biggest price decline for a calendar year since records began, with a 7.5% drop over a one year period.</p>
<p>Home prices crashed as rapidly rising interest rates forced a market adjustment that may have further to go.</p>
<p>The country’s benchmark home price fell 1.6% in December to $730,600, bringing the total decrease since February’s peak to 13.2%, the <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/10-of-all-new-toronto-condos-must-now-go-to-affordable-housing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Canadian Real Estate Association</a></span> said. It was the biggest peak-to-trough falloff since the group started compiling the data in 2005</p>
<p>With the economy in danger of entering a recession, and the Bank of Canada warning of more rate hikes to counter persistent inflation, the housing market may face continued pressure in the coming months.</p>
<p>A record number of buyers used floating-rate debt for purchases during the pandemic boom, and those borrowers may come under increasing strain if mortgage costs remain high. Job losses from an economic slowdown also would make it harder for people to keep up with loan payments and stay in their homes.</p>
<p>The housing slump has largely been driven by a pullback among buyers who’ve been priced out due to higher interest rates. The number of transactions in December was down 39% on a non-seasonally adjusted basis from last year, when the market was approaching its peak and before interest rates started rising.</p>
<h4>Is Canada’s housing party finally over?</h4>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5807" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-9.png" alt="Canadian house prices drop to their lowest level as recession fear looms" width="1920" height="1129" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-9.png 1920w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-9-300x176.png 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-9-1024x602.png 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-9-768x452.png 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-9-1536x903.png 1536w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2023/01/image1-9-800x470.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></p>
<p>For the past 25 years, Canada has been in the grip of the world’s biggest housing boom, a near unbroken run of price appreciation unparalleled in the developed world.</p>
<p>Now the party’s almost over, and pain is starting to spread.</p>
<p>By March, it will be a year since the Bank of Canada began raising interest rates — meaning ever more of the record number of people who took out short-term or floating-rate mortgages at historically low rates will find themselves fully exposed to the roughly fourfold jump in borrowing costs since then, a potentially catastrophic shock to their personal finances.</p>
<p>The fate of Canada’s <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/toronto-housing-market-sizzles-again/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">housing market</a></span> will depend on whether or not they can hold on. And just as the country was a leader in the years-long global real estate frenzy, how its downturn plays out — a relatively orderly correction, or a brutal crash — may be a harbinger for what awaits the rest of the world.</p>
<p>Reference:</p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2023-01-16/canadian-home-prices-post-record-drop-as-high-rates-hit-buyers?srnd=premium-canada" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bloomberg</a></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canadian-house-prices-drop-to-their-lowest-level-as-recession-fear-looms/">Canadian house prices drop to their lowest level as recession fear looms</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canadian-house-prices-drop-to-their-lowest-level-as-recession-fear-looms/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>The Gap stores &#8211; going, going, gone in Toronto</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/the-gap-stores-going-going-gone-in-toronto/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/the-gap-stores-going-going-gone-in-toronto/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 22 Dec 2022 06:57:26 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[News]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Forever 21]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gap store closure]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Gap store in Toronto]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[H&M]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Marshals]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Zara]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5761</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Gap store closes down in Toronto: Why have the mighty fallen? The Gap, once one of the world’s greatest clothing brands has reached the end of its road in Toronto, and is closing down its Toronto flagship Fairview Mall branch. It’s a sign of the retail times. The Gap had earlier last year officially shut down its iconic Toronto branch at 60 Bloor Street West. It had been in that same location for over 30 years. The shutting down of Gap stores is apparently part of the company’s strategy to grow and adapt its online presence. The Gap is also [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/the-gap-stores-going-going-gone-in-toronto/">The Gap stores &#8211; going, going, gone in Toronto</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><em>Gap store closes down in Toronto: Why have the mighty fallen?</em></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-5757 size-full" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-21T230707.921.jpeg" alt="The Gap stores - going, going, gone in Toronto" width="1440" height="1028" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-21T230707.921.jpeg 1440w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-21T230707.921-300x214.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-21T230707.921-1024x731.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-21T230707.921-768x548.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-21T230707.921-800x571.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1440px) 100vw, 1440px" /></p>
<p>The Gap, once one of the world’s greatest clothing brands has reached the end of its road in Toronto, and is closing down its Toronto flagship Fairview Mall branch. It’s a sign of the retail times.</p>
<p>The Gap had earlier last year officially shut down its iconic Toronto branch at 60 Bloor Street West. It had been in that same location for over 30 years.</p>
<p>The shutting down of Gap stores is apparently part of the company’s strategy to grow and adapt its online presence.</p>
<p>The Gap is also looking to operate out of strip malls and other favourable retail locations, rather than on its own.</p>
<h4>Is Old Navy and Banana Republic closing down too?</h4>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5756" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-97-scaled.jpeg" alt="The Gap stores - going, going, gone in Toronto" width="1710" height="2560" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-97-scaled.jpeg 1710w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-97-200x300.jpeg 200w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-97-684x1024.jpeg 684w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-97-768x1150.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-97-1026x1536.jpeg 1026w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-97-1368x2048.jpeg 1368w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-97-800x1198.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1710px) 100vw, 1710px" /></p>
<p>The company had also earlier announced plans to split its brands into two publicly traded companies with Old Navy falling into one business and Gap, Banana Republic, Athleta, Intermix and Hill City making up another.</p>
<p>The fear in retail fashion circles is that Old Navy and Banana Republic  may soon fall under the hammer as well.</p>
<p>A Gap spokesperson previously explained: “As part of our company strategy to adapt to the changing needs of our customer and growth of our online business,  we are looking thoughtfully at our real estate to support the best path forward.</p>
<p>As a result, we are closing  a number of stores across Canada.  We remain committed to making appropriate and timely decisions on stores that  don’t fit our vision for the future of Gap Inc. We are confident these closures will help strengthen the health of our company moving forward.”</p>
<p>There are 80 Gap retail stores in Canada as of November 04, 2022.</p>
<h4>What happened to Gap and why is it closing down?</h4>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5765" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56.jpeg" alt="" width="830" height="830" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56.jpeg 830w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56-768x768.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56-70x70.jpeg 70w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56-180x180.jpeg 180w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56-400x400.jpeg 400w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56-600x600.jpeg 600w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-56-800x800.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 830px) 100vw, 830px" /></p>
<p>Gap used to be one of the world’s hottest retail brands, but time has caught up with the retail giant and it has lost its shine. What happened to Gap? Here are five reasons why Gap is closing down:</p>
<ol>
<li>
<h5>Fashion oversight</h5>
</li>
</ol>
<p>A series of fashion misses and failure to quickly anticipate retail trends and catch up with the young market. This is the biggest reason why Gap is closing down in Canada</p>
<ol start="2">
<li>
<h5>High prices</h5>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The quality of Gap clothings was unquestionable, but <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/how-to-save-money-as-an-international-student-in-canada/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">it’s high prices got buyers running for cover</a></span>. It led to Gap closing down</p>
<ol start="3">
<li>
<h5>Inflation</h5>
</li>
</ol>
<p>With consumers feeling the inflation squeeze, the Gap fell out of the radar and was forced to close most of its high-end stores.</p>
<ol start="4">
<li>
<h5>Hot competition</h5>
</li>
</ol>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="size-full wp-image-5754 aligncenter" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-34.jpeg" alt="" width="1280" height="1920" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-34.jpeg 1280w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-34-200x300.jpeg 200w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-34-683x1024.jpeg 683w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-34-768x1152.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-34-1024x1536.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-34-800x1200.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></p>
<p>The shift in consumer demand resulted in shoppers turning away from Gap to fast fashion rivals such as H&amp;M, Zara, Forever 21, Marshals and Winners. This is probably the biggest reason why Gap is closing down in Canada.</p>
<ol start="5">
<li>
<h5>Business strategy direction</h5>
</li>
</ol>
<p>The Gap is changing its business model from brick and mortar stores to online shopping</p>
<h4>Gap closure and shoppers’ delight</h4>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5755" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image4-23.jpeg" alt="The Gap stores - going, going, gone in Toronto" width="1280" height="1920" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image4-23.jpeg 1280w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image4-23-200x300.jpeg 200w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image4-23-683x1024.jpeg 683w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image4-23-768x1152.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image4-23-1024x1536.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image4-23-800x1200.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></p>
<p>While the Gap is counting its losses, Canadians and immigrant shoppers are snapping up jaw- <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/7-things-you-should-not-buy-on-black-friday/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">dropping Seasonal and New Year bargains</a></span> at the Gap store in Toronto.</p>
<p>Sadness and joy can sometimes happen together.</p>
<div id="malwarebytes-root"></div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/the-gap-stores-going-going-gone-in-toronto/">The Gap stores &#8211; going, going, gone in Toronto</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/the-gap-stores-going-going-gone-in-toronto/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Canada reduces immigration backlog of applications by 500,000</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-reduces-immigration-backlog-of-applications-by-500000/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-reduces-immigration-backlog-of-applications-by-500000/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 20 Dec 2022 07:30:13 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Travel + Immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Canada study permit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Canada Work permit]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Immigrate to Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[IRCC]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5742</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Canada on the roll Highly-skilled professionals planning to immigrate to Canada are now getting their applications processed faster than ever before. Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (IRCC) has been taking steady action to strengthen Canada’s immigration system—reducing wait times, and modernizing its services so they work better for everyone Today, Canada’s Minister of Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship, the Honourable Sean Fraser, highlighted progress that has been made this year, in reducing backlogs of applications that have been in IRCC’s inventories beyond its service standards. Record year for processing immigration applications to Canada Since August, IRCC has reduced its overall inventory [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-reduces-immigration-backlog-of-applications-by-500000/">Canada reduces immigration backlog of applications by 500,000</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><em>Canada on the roll</em></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-5744 size-full" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-55.jpeg" alt="Canada reduces immigration backlog of applications by 500,000" width="1280" height="1920" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-55.jpeg 1280w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-55-200x300.jpeg 200w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-55-683x1024.jpeg 683w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-55-768x1152.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-55-1024x1536.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image2-55-800x1200.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></p>
<p>Highly-skilled professionals planning to immigrate to Canada are now getting their applications processed faster than ever before.</p>
<p>Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (IRCC) has been taking steady action to strengthen Canada’s immigration system—reducing wait times, and modernizing its services so they work better for everyone</p>
<p>Today, Canada’s Minister of Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship, the Honourable Sean Fraser, highlighted progress that has been made this year, in reducing backlogs of applications that have been in IRCC’s inventories beyond its service standards.</p>
<h5>Record year for processing immigration applications to Canada</h5>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5743" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-20T082032.379.jpeg" alt="Canada reduces immigration backlog of applications by 500,000" width="1280" height="856" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-20T082032.379.jpeg 1280w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-20T082032.379-300x201.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-20T082032.379-1024x685.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-20T082032.379-768x514.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-20T082032.379-800x535.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></p>
<p>Since August, IRCC has reduced its overall inventory by nearly half a million applications. The department has also been setting the bar higher  for processing.</p>
<p>At the end of November, IRCC had processed approximately 4.8 million applications—nearly twice the 2.5 million processed during the same period last year.</p>
<p>To help strengthen our immigration system, IRCC has digitized applications, hired and trained new employees, streamlined processes, and harnessed automation technologies to increase processing efficiency while protecting the safety and security of Canadians.</p>
<p>The department remains on track to meet its goal to process 80% of new applications within service standards for most programs and continues to make strides in improving processing, resulting in shorter wait times for our clients.</p>
<p>For study permit processing, Canada is also on pace to set a new record this year. As of November 30 this year, IRCC had processed over 670,000 study permits, compared to more than 500,000 during the same time period last year. As a result of these efforts, most new study permits are now being processed within the 60-day service standard.</p>
<p>Work permit processing also saw vast improvements, with nearly 700,000 work permits processed by November 30, compared to about 223,000 during the same period in 2019, before the pandemic.</p>
<p>IRCC continues to reduce backlogs and process visitor visas more quickly to respond to the growing number of people who want to visit Canada.</p>
<p>On a monthly basis, Canada is now processing more visitor visa applications than it did prior to the pandemic. In November alone, over 260,000 visitor visas were processed. By contrast, the monthly average in 2019 was about 180,000 applications.</p>
<h6>Permanent residents to Canada.</h6>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-immigration-increases-permanent-residence-fees/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Permanent residence applications</a></span>, improving service and reuniting spouses and families are also being processed faster.</p>
<p>Canada welcomed a <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.canada.ca/en/immigration-refugees-citizenship/news/2021/12/canada-welcomes-the-most-immigrants-in-a-single-year-in-its-history.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">record-breaking 405,000 new permanent residents</a></span> in 2021, surpassing the previous record from 1913. After another record year in 2022, Canada remains on track to reach its target of more than 431,000 new permanent residents.</p>
<p>All new spousal sponsorship applications are now processed within the pre-pandemic service standard of 12 months and new Express Entry applications within 6 months.</p>
<p>Permanent residents can also expect shorter wait times when renewing their permanent resident cards as IRCC has reduced its pandemic backlog of applications for card renewals by 99%.</p>
<p>Canada is proud to have one of the highest naturalization rates in the world and encourages all newcomers to complete their journey by becoming Canadian citizens. IRCC expects a record number of new Canadian citizens in 2022–2023, with approximately 251,000 new citizens welcomed from April to November—surpassing the total number of new Canadian citizens for the last fiscal year.</p>
<p>The Honourable Sean Fraser, Minister of Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship said, “our actions are ensuring that we can continue to welcome and support newcomers who come to Canada to work, study, visit, or settle here.</p>
<p>“It is through the dedication and hard work of those who administer our immigration system, and our willingness to modernize and adapt, that we are able to uphold Canada’s reputation as a welcoming and inclusive country.”</p>
<div id="malwarebytes-root"></div>
<div id="malwarebytes-root"></div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-reduces-immigration-backlog-of-applications-by-500000/">Canada reduces immigration backlog of applications by 500,000</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-reduces-immigration-backlog-of-applications-by-500000/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Work in Spain remotely with the new Digital Nomad Visa (DNV)</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/work-in-spain-remotely-with-the-new-digital-nomad-visa-dnv/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/work-in-spain-remotely-with-the-new-digital-nomad-visa-dnv/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Sat, 17 Dec 2022 07:53:10 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Jobs]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Digital Nomad Visa (DNV)]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Ley de Startups]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[migration route]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Spain Nomad Visa]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5729</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Travel, work and leisure in a new Spanish mix Canadians looking to escape the winter and work in Spain or other European country now have a chance to do so, as Spain rolls out its Nomad Visa. Capitalizing on the enormous rise in post-pandemic remote work, Spain has announced a new visa program that will allow non–European Economic Area residents (including British, US and Canadian citizens) working for foreign companies to live in the country without having to obtain a full work visa. The Ley de Startups (Startups Law), which aims to attract tech companies, remote workers and digital nomads [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/work-in-spain-remotely-with-the-new-digital-nomad-visa-dnv/">Work in Spain remotely with the new Digital Nomad Visa (DNV)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><i>Travel, work and leisure in a new Spanish mix</i></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5731" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-32.jpeg" alt="Work in Spain remotely with the new Digital Nomad Visa (DNV)" width="1280" height="853" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-32.jpeg 1280w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-32-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-32-1024x682.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-32-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image3-32-800x533.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></p>
<p>Canadians looking to escape the winter and work in Spain or other European country now have a chance to do so, as Spain rolls out its Nomad Visa.</p>
<p>Capitalizing on the enormous rise in post-pandemic remote work, Spain has announced a new visa program that will allow non–European Economic Area residents (including British, US and Canadian citizens) working for foreign companies to live in the country without having to obtain a full work visa.</p>
<p>The Ley de Startups (Startups Law), which aims to attract tech companies, remote workers and digital nomads to Spain, is expected to come into force in January 2023.</p>
<p>This will open a new <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/immigrating-to-canada-use-an-immigration-lawyer-or-go-on-your-own/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">migration route for foreign workers</a></span> who might fancy a move to the country, including digital nomads. While it doesn’t carry this particular name, the new regulation is, in effect, an equivalent to a Digital Nomad Visa (DNV)</p>
<p>The visa will initially be valid for one year, with the possibility of extending it afterward for up to five years. To be eligible, you must be employed by a non-Spanish company operating outside Spain, or, if self-employed, earn no more than 20% of your income from Spanish clients.</p>
<p>There will be a minimum monthly income requirement and applicants will need to show some kind of proof of accommodation. Additionally, private health insurance and a higher-education qualification or three years’ worth of work experience are likely to be other prerequisites. Visa holders will benefit from substantial non-resident tax breaks (exact figures are still to come), and have the option to bring along close family members.</p>
<p>Does a life in Spain sound enticing? As you wait the release of all the program’s details, start dreaming in the meantime of the perfect place to live.</p>
<h5>Top destination in Spain for working remotely</h5>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5732" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image5-22.jpeg" alt="" width="2082" height="2398" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image5-22.jpeg 2082w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image5-22-260x300.jpeg 260w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image5-22-889x1024.jpeg 889w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image5-22-768x885.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image5-22-1334x1536.jpeg 1334w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image5-22-1778x2048.jpeg 1778w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image5-22-800x921.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 2082px) 100vw, 2082px" /></p>
<p>Some of the top destinations to consider when moving to Spain are:</p>
<ul>
<li><strong>Valencia</strong>, an often overlooked coastal gem with a growing population of American and British expats</li>
<li><strong>Gran Canaria and Tenerife</strong>, two ‘workcation’ hubs in the Canaries that have <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.traveloffpath.com/airbnb-partners-with-this-beautiful-sunny-destination-to-attract-digital-nomads/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">partnered with AirBnB</a></span> recently to attract more digital nomads</li>
<li><strong>Barcelona</strong>, the historical capital of the autonomous Catalonia, where <em>La Sagrada Familia</em> and countless works by Gaudi can be found</li>
<li><strong>Seville</strong>, the largest city in Andalusia and one of Spain’s most culturally-charged, home to La Giralda and the landmark Plaza de Espana</li>
<li><strong>Formentera</strong>, the smaller of the Balearic islands and Ibiza’s smaller, southern neighbor, packed with marine parks and pristine beaches</li>
<li><strong>Bilbao</strong>, a vibrant metropolis in Northern Spain, more specifically Basque Country, famous for its world-class museums and colorful Old Quartet</li>
</ul>
<p>Joining video calls from a sun-drenched terrace. Spending weekends kicking back by the Mediterranean or hiking through rugged hills. Sound tempting yet? Spain’s much-anticipated new digital-nomad visa could be just the ticket.</p>
<p><strong>References:</strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.traveloffpath.com/spain-is-launching-a-digital-nomad-visa-in-2023-find-out-if-youre-eligible/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Travel of Path</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.lonelyplanet.com/news/spain-best-digital-nomad-cities" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lonely Planet</a></span></p>
<div id="malwarebytes-root"></div>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/work-in-spain-remotely-with-the-new-digital-nomad-visa-dnv/">Work in Spain remotely with the new Digital Nomad Visa (DNV)</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/work-in-spain-remotely-with-the-new-digital-nomad-visa-dnv/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Sex outside marriage is now a crime in Indonesia- what it means for Canadians</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/sex-outside-marriage-is-now-a-crime-in-indonesia-what-it-means/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/sex-outside-marriage-is-now-a-crime-in-indonesia-what-it-means/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 16 Dec 2022 07:06:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Travel + Immigration]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[indonesian sex law]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5725</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Pleasure lost or pleasure redefined? Indonesia has now made sex outside marriage a crime. Unmarried couples and Canadian tourists planning a holiday trip to Indonesia may have to think again. Indonesia’s parliament has just passed the new law that  bans sex outside marriage with a punishment of up to one year in jail, despite worries the laws may scare away tourists from its shores and harm investment. Lawmakers approved a new criminal code which will apply to Indonesians and foreigners alike. It will also ban insulting the president or state institutions, spreading views counter to the state ideology, and staging [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/sex-outside-marriage-is-now-a-crime-in-indonesia-what-it-means/">Sex outside marriage is now a crime in Indonesia- what it means for Canadians</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><em>Pleasure lost or pleasure redefined?</em></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone wp-image-5727 size-full" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-16T075628.730.jpeg" alt="Sex outside marriage is now a crime in Indonesia- what it means for Canadians" width="1920" height="932" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-16T075628.730.jpeg 1920w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-16T075628.730-300x146.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-16T075628.730-1024x497.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-16T075628.730-768x373.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-16T075628.730-1536x746.jpeg 1536w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-16T075628.730-800x388.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></p>
<p>Indonesia has now made sex outside marriage a crime. Unmarried couples and Canadian tourists planning a holiday trip to Indonesia may have to think again.</p>
<p>Indonesia’s parliament has just passed the new law that  bans sex outside marriage with a punishment of up to one year in jail, despite worries the laws may scare away tourists from its shores and harm investment.</p>
<p>Lawmakers approved a new criminal code which will apply to Indonesians and foreigners alike. It will also ban insulting the president or state institutions, spreading views counter to the state ideology, and staging protests without notification.</p>
<p>Sex outside of marriage can be punished with up to a one-year prison term; living with someone who isn’t your spouse can lead to six months. Charges must be based on police reports filed by parents, children or spouses.</p>
<p>However, the code will not come into effect for three years to allow for implementing regulations to be drafted.</p>
<p>Currently, Indonesia bans adultery but not premarital sex.</p>
<p>Maulana Yusran, deputy chief of Indonesia&#8217;s tourism industry board, said the new code was &#8220;totally counter-productive&#8221; at a time when the economy and tourism were starting to recover from the pandemic.</p>
<p>We deeply regret the government have closed their eyes. We have already expressed our concern to the ministry of tourism about how harmful this law is,&#8221; he said.</p>
<p>The world’s largest Muslim-majority nation, Indonesia has seen a rise in religious conservatism in recent years. Strict Islamic laws are already enforced in parts of the country, including the semi-autonomous Aceh province, where alcohol and gambling are banned. Public floggings also take place in the region for a range of offenses including homosexuality and adultery.</p>
<p>Foreign arrivals in the holiday destination of Bali are expected to reach pre-pandemic levels of six million by 2025, the tourism association has said previously, as the island recovers from the impacts of COVID-19. Indonesia is also trying to attract more so-called &#8220;digital nomads&#8221; to its tropical shores by offering a more flexible visa.</p>
<h5>What the new sex law means to Canadians</h5>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="aligncenter wp-image-5726 size-full" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-96.jpeg" alt="Sex outside marriage is now a crime in Indonesia- what it means for Canadians" width="1920" height="1280" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-96.jpeg 1920w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-96-300x200.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-96-1024x683.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-96-768x512.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-96-1536x1024.jpeg 1536w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-96-800x533.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></p>
<p>Canada and Indonesia share a long-standing partnership of over 65 years. Since 2000, Canada has provided  over $1 billion in official development assistance (ODA) to Indonesia with an average of  $44 million (all channels combined) per year over the past 5 years. Bilateral funding to Indonesia in the fiscal year 2021 to 2022 was approximately $13.5 million.</p>
<p>Tourism is a vital part of Indonesia’s economy and the World Bank reported that over 4 million tourists visited Indonesia in 2020.</p>
<p>The ambiguity of the new criminal code and how it will be enforced leaves foreigners in a gray zone. Because charges of adultery or cohabitation can only be filed by close relatives, law-breaking tourists might go undetected. Moreover, reporting foreigners goes against the interests of Western-style hotels in vacation destinations like Bali, which rely on tourist dollars to stay afloat.</p>
<p>But for singles looking to mingle or unwed couples hoping for a romantic escape to the gorgeous Indonesia beaches, possible jail time isn’t synonymous with “a paradise vacation.” Unless Indonesia relaxes the laws, travelers must consider if the risk is worth the reward.</p>
<p><strong>References:</strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.reuters.com/world/asia-pacific/indonesias-parliament-passes-controversial-new-criminal-code-2022-12-06/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Reuters</a></span></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.lonelyplanet.com/news/indonesia-bans-extramarital-sex-what-to-know" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Lonely Planet</a></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/sex-outside-marriage-is-now-a-crime-in-indonesia-what-it-means/">Sex outside marriage is now a crime in Indonesia- what it means for Canadians</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/sex-outside-marriage-is-now-a-crime-in-indonesia-what-it-means/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Get ready for a mortgage interest rate of 8% to buy a house in Canada</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/get-ready-for-a-mortgage-interest-rate-of-8-to-buy-a-house-in-canada/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/get-ready-for-a-mortgage-interest-rate-of-8-to-buy-a-house-in-canada/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 07:08:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Real Estate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[buy a house in Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Dominion Lending Centres Edge]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Get ready for a mortgage interest rate]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Shahab Shahisavandi]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5721</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Low interest rates are gone with the wind  If you are planning to buy a house in Canada, your mortgage qualifying rate will now be over 8%. The Bank of Canada’s most recent interest rate hike may force homebuyers to prove they can pay mortgages with interest rates above 8%. This will be a severe blow to prospective house buyers and another headwind for the country’s cooling housing market. Canadian regulators require that buyers pass a “stress test” showing that they can afford mortgages with rates that are two percentage points higher than lenders are offering. Major banks’ variable mortgage [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/get-ready-for-a-mortgage-interest-rate-of-8-to-buy-a-house-in-canada/">Get ready for a mortgage interest rate of 8% to buy a house in Canada</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><i>Low interest rates are gone with the wind </i></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5723" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-6.png" alt="" width="1280" height="1212" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-6.png 1280w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-6-300x284.png 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-6-1024x970.png 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-6-768x727.png 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-6-800x758.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></p>
<p>If you are planning to buy a house in Canada, your mortgage qualifying rate will now be over 8%. The Bank of Canada’s most recent interest rate hike may force homebuyers to prove they can pay mortgages with interest rates above 8%.</p>
<p>This will be a severe blow to prospective house buyers and another headwind for the country’s cooling housing market.</p>
<p>Canadian regulators require that buyers pass a “stress test” showing that they can afford mortgages with rates that are two percentage points higher than lenders are offering.</p>
<p>Major banks’ variable mortgage rates are close to their prime lending rates, which in turn are 2.2 points above the <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/looking-for-a-bank-job-in-canada-check-out-this-complete-guide/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bank of Canada</a></span>’s overnight rate.</p>
<p>The central bank on Wednesday announced a 4.25% interest rate as it continues its campaign to quell inflation. That will push the commercial-bank prime rate to 6.45% — about double where it was in April.</p>
<h5>The economics and emotions of interest rates</h5>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5722" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94.jpeg" alt="" width="1920" height="1920" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94.jpeg 1920w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-300x300.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-1024x1024.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-150x150.jpeg 150w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-768x768.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-1536x1536.jpeg 1536w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-70x70.jpeg 70w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-180x180.jpeg 180w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-400x400.jpeg 400w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-600x600.jpeg 600w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-94-800x800.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></p>
<p>Currently, major banks such as  TD Bank and RBC have posted mortgage rates slightly below prime — though top customers may be given bigger discounts. In other words, advertised variable mortgage rates are likely to move to the low 6% range, pushing the stress-test rate to more than 8%.</p>
<p>Consumers may be able to get a slightly lower rate if they agree to lock in for five years. <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/rbc-to-buy-up-hsbc-canadawhat-it-means-to-immigrants/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">RBC’s  five-year</a></span> fixed mortgage is at 5.7% and tends to track the yield on benchmark government bonds, not the Bank of Canada policy rate.</p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/interest-rates-jump-higher-and-canadas-house-prices-stay-lower/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Home prices in Canada</a></span> already have fallen 10% from their February peak, with previously hot markets including Toronto and its surrounding area posting steeper declines.</p>
<p>The  available houses for sale have dropped even more, as sellers cling to hopes that prices will rebound — or remain hesitant to move and take on new mortgages at today’s higher rates.</p>
<p>Shahab Shahisavandi, a mortgage agent at Dominion Lending Centres Edge, counseled that “despite the sudden spike in interest rates and the disruption to the housing market, home owners should stay calm and take a long -term view. For first-time home buyers, early preparation is the key success factor.”</p>
<p><strong>Reference:</strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.bloomberg.com/news/articles/2022-12-07/mortgage-qualifying-rate-in-canada-may-top-8-after-latest-central-bank-move" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Bloomberg</a></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/get-ready-for-a-mortgage-interest-rate-of-8-to-buy-a-house-in-canada/">Get ready for a mortgage interest rate of 8% to buy a house in Canada</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/get-ready-for-a-mortgage-interest-rate-of-8-to-buy-a-house-in-canada/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Government increases EI pay (Employment insurance) to $61,500</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-government-increases-ei-pay-employment-insurance/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-government-increases-ei-pay-employment-insurance/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 14 Dec 2022 06:38:23 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Money]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Employment Insurance]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Government increases EI pay]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[maximum insurable earnings]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[skilled immigrants]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5718</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Your money and your new year  The Government of Canada is increasing the maximum amount workers can get on Employment Insurance (EI) from January 1, 2023. This is great news for all categories of workers, especially highly skilled immigrants in job transitions. The maximum insurable earnings (MIE) is the income level up to which Employment Insurance (EI) premiums are paid. It determines the maximum rate of weekly benefits paid for all types of benefits under the EI program. Effective January 1, 2023, the MIE will increase from $60,300 to $61,500. This means that an insured worker will pay EI premiums [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-government-increases-ei-pay-employment-insurance/">Government increases EI pay (Employment insurance) to $61,500</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><i>Your money and your new year </i></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5719" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-14T072750.380.jpeg" alt="Government increases EI pay (Employment insurance) to $61,500" width="1920" height="1285" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-14T072750.380.jpeg 1920w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-14T072750.380-300x201.jpeg 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-14T072750.380-1024x685.jpeg 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-14T072750.380-768x514.jpeg 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-14T072750.380-1536x1028.jpeg 1536w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-2022-12-14T072750.380-800x535.jpeg 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1920px) 100vw, 1920px" /></p>
<p>The Government of Canada is increasing the maximum amount workers can get on Employment Insurance (EI) from January 1, 2023. This is great news for all categories of workers, especially highly <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/looking-for-a-bank-job-in-canada-check-out-this-complete-guide/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">skilled immigrants</a></span> in job transitions.</p>
<p>The maximum insurable earnings (MIE) is the income level up to which Employment Insurance (EI) premiums are paid. It determines the maximum rate of weekly benefits paid for all types of benefits under the EI program.</p>
<p>Effective January 1, 2023, the MIE will increase from $60,300 to $61,500. This means that an insured worker will pay EI premiums in 2023 on insured earnings up to $61,500.</p>
<p>In 2023, the employee EI premium rate will be $1.63 per $100. This premium rate and the MIE increase means that insured workers will pay a maximum annual EI premium in 2023 of $1,002.45 compared with $952.74 in 2022.</p>
<p>Because of the increased MIE, beginning in January 2023, the maximum weekly EI benefit rate will increase from $638 to $650 per week. Claims established before December 31, 2022, will not be affected by the 2023 MIE increase.</p>
<p>Insured workers will pay EI premiums on all earnings up to the annual maximum salary of $61,500. This means a deduction of $1.63 will be made for every $100 of salary until the $61,500 for the year has been reached.</p>
<p>For example, if an individual earns $65,000 a year, premiums are payable on the first $61,500.</p>
<p>The premium rate for workers in Quebec will be $1.27. This rate is lower than in the rest of Canada, because the Province of Quebec has been collecting premiums from their workers since January 2006 to administer its own maternity, parental, and paternity benefits under the Quebec Parental Insurance Plan.</p>
<p>People can <span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.canada.ca/en/services/benefits/ei/ei-regular-benefit/apply.html" target="_blank" rel="noopener">apply for EI online</a></span> at Service Canada. It usually takes more than 4 weeks for Service Canada to review an application and start paying benefits.</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-government-increases-ei-pay-employment-insurance/">Government increases EI pay (Employment insurance) to $61,500</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/canada-government-increases-ei-pay-employment-insurance/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Interest rates jump higher and Canada’s  house prices stay lower</title>
		<link>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/interest-rates-jump-higher-and-canadas-house-prices-stay-lower/</link>
					<comments>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/interest-rates-jump-higher-and-canadas-house-prices-stay-lower/#respond</comments>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[publisher]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 08 Dec 2022 17:26:00 +0000</pubDate>
				<category><![CDATA[Money]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Bank of Canada]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Canadian housing market]]></category>
		<category><![CDATA[Canadian Real Estate Association]]></category>
		<guid isPermaLink="false">https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/?p=5713</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[<p>Hard pressed borrowers have nowhere to run Interest rates in Canada have jumped to a record level of 4.25%, while house prices have crashed to historic lows at the opposite end. The Bank of Canada has just announced the interest rate increase by 50 basis points but signalled that aggressive hikes could be ending soon. This is the seventh consecutive increase since the Bank began hiking rates in March in a bid to slow the economy and curb runaway inflation. The central bank said in a press release, “looking ahead, the Governing Council will be considering whether the policy interest [&#8230;]</p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/interest-rates-jump-higher-and-canadas-house-prices-stay-lower/">Interest rates jump higher and Canada’s  house prices stay lower</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[<h6 style="text-align: center;"><em>Hard pressed borrowers have nowhere to run</em></h6>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5715" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-5.png" alt="" width="1280" height="917" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-5.png 1280w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-5-300x215.png 300w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-5-1024x734.png 1024w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-5-768x550.png 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image0-5-800x573.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1280px) 100vw, 1280px" /></p>
<p>Interest rates in Canada have jumped to a record level of 4.25%, while house prices have crashed to historic lows at the opposite end.</p>
<p>The Bank of Canada has just announced the interest rate increase by 50 basis points but signalled that aggressive hikes could be ending soon.</p>
<p>This is the seventh consecutive increase since the Bank began hiking rates in March in a bid to slow the economy and curb runaway inflation.</p>
<p>The central bank said in a press release, “looking ahead, the Governing Council will be considering whether the policy interest rate needs to rise further to bring supply and demand back into balance and return inflation to target. “</p>
<p>Since the interest rate hikes, core inflation, which strips out the cost of food and energy, has begun to moderate and the housing market has cooled dramatically.</p>
<h5>Canadian housing market stays cool and prices drop by over $170,000</h5>
<p><img decoding="async" loading="lazy" class="alignnone size-full wp-image-5714" src="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-4.png" alt="Interest rates jump higher and Canada’s  house prices stay lower   " width="1267" height="1280" srcset="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-4.png 1267w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-4-297x300.png 297w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-4-1014x1024.png 1014w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-4-768x776.png 768w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-4-70x70.png 70w, https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/wp-content/uploads/2022/12/image1-4-800x808.png 800w" sizes="(max-width: 1267px) 100vw, 1267px" /></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/10-of-all-new-toronto-condos-must-now-go-to-affordable-housing/" target="_blank" rel="noopener">Canada&#8217;s housing market</a></span> has continued its downward trend, with the volume of home sales down by more than a third compared to the boom times of last year — and prices down by almost 10 per cent or more than $170,000 since then.</p>
<p>The Canadian Real Estate Association, which represents Realtors, said the national average selling price of a home that sold in October went for $644,643. That&#8217;s down by 9.9 per cent compared to the same month a year earlier, and down by even more from the peak of $816,720 in February 2022.</p>
<p>This is probably the best time to buy a house…if you can qualify for a mortgage.</p>
<p><strong>Reference:</strong></p>
<p><span style="color: #3366ff;"><a style="color: #3366ff;" href="https://www.cbc.ca/news/business/crea-house-data-october-1.6651867#:~:text=Canada's%20housing%20market%20continued%20its,per%20cent%20since%20then%2C%20too" target="_blank" rel="noopener">CBC</a></span></p>
<p>The post <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/interest-rates-jump-higher-and-canadas-house-prices-stay-lower/">Interest rates jump higher and Canada’s  house prices stay lower</a> appeared first on <a rel="nofollow" href="https://thebusinessimmigrant.com">The Business Immigrant</a>.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
					<wfw:commentRss>https://thebusinessimmigrant.com/interest-rates-jump-higher-and-canadas-house-prices-stay-lower/feed/</wfw:commentRss>
			<slash:comments>0</slash:comments>
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
