<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss version="2.0"
	xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/"
	xmlns:wfw="http://wellformedweb.org/CommentAPI/"
	xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/"
	xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"
	xmlns:sy="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/syndication/"
	xmlns:slash="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/slash/"
	>

<channel>
	<title>VisaPlace</title>
	<atom:link href="https://www.visaplace.com/feed/" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
	<link>https://www.visaplace.com/</link>
	<description>Toronto Immigration Lawyers, US &#38; Canadian Visa Services</description>
	<lastBuildDate>Wed, 25 Jan 2023 16:09:04 +0000</lastBuildDate>
	<language>en-US</language>
	<sy:updatePeriod>
	hourly	</sy:updatePeriod>
	<sy:updateFrequency>
	1	</sy:updateFrequency>
	

<image>
	<url>https://www.visaplace.com/wp-content/uploads/2019/12/cropped-favicon-32x32.png</url>
	<title>VisaPlace</title>
	<link>https://www.visaplace.com/</link>
	<width>32</width>
	<height>32</height>
</image> 
	<item>
		<title>Indian Engineering Students Thrive in Canada&#8217;s Top-Ranked Programs</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/indian-engineering-students-thrive-in-canadas-top-ranked-programs/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 19:20:40 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53843</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Canada is an excellent choice for Indian engineering students looking to study abroad. With its diverse culture, high-quality education system, and welcoming society, Canada provides students with a unique and enriching experience. In this article, we will look at some of the reasons why an Indian engineering student should consider studying in Canada, as well [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Canada is an excellent choice for Indian engineering students looking to study abroad. With its diverse culture, high-quality education system, and welcoming society, Canada provides students with a unique and enriching experience. In this article, we will look at some of the reasons why an Indian engineering student should consider studying in Canada, as well as provide an overview of engineering programs available at universities across the country.</p>



<p>The quality of education is one of the main reasons why Canada is a great choice for Indian engineering students. Universities in Canada are known for their world-class facilities, highly qualified professors, and cutting-edge research. This is particularly true for engineering programs, which are consistently ranked among the best in the world.</p>



<p>Another important consideration is the variety of engineering programs available in Canada. There is something for everyone, from traditional disciplines like mechanical and electrical engineering to newer fields like sustainable energy and biomaterials. </p>



<h2 id="h-top-engineering-programs-in-canada">Top Engineering Programs in Canada</h2>



<p>Some of Canada&#8217;s top engineering programs include:</p>



<p>&#8211;<a href="https://discover.engineering.utoronto.ca/programs/engineering-programs/">The University of Toronto</a>: This prestigious institution has a long history of engineering excellence. The Faculty of Applied Science and Engineering is one of Canada&#8217;s most prestigious engineering schools, offering a diverse range of undergraduate and graduate programs.</p>



<p>&#8211;<a href="https://engineering.ubc.ca/programs">The University of British Columbia</a>: This west coast university is known for its strong engineering program, especially in areas like sustainable energy and transportation.</p>



<p>&#8211;<a href="https://www.mcgill.ca/engineering/students/undergraduate/undergraduate-programs">McGill University</a>: This Montreal-based university has one of Canada&#8217;s most prestigious engineering programs, with an emphasis on interdisciplinary research and innovation.</p>



<p>&#8211;<a href="https://www.ualberta.ca/engineering/index.html">University of Alberta</a>: This university provides engineering programs in a variety of fields, including petroleum, environmental, mechanical, and software engineering.</p>



<p>&#8211;<a href="https://uwaterloo.ca/engineering/">Waterloo University</a>: This university is Canada&#8217;s largest engineering school which is well-known for its engineering programs in fields such as computer science, mechatronics, and nanotechnology.</p>



<p>Aside from the high quality of education and the wide range of programs available, there are numerous other reasons why an Indian engineering student should consider studying in Canada. These include the country&#8217;s welcoming culture, excellent living conditions, and international experience opportunities. Furthermore, immigration policies in Canada are very welcoming to international students, and many of them are able to stay and work in Canada after graduation.</p>



<p>In conclusion, Canada is an excellent choice for Indian engineering students looking to study abroad. With its world-class education system, a diverse range of programs, and welcoming culture, Canada offers a unique and enriching experience that can&#8217;t be found anywhere else. Whether you&#8217;re interested in traditional disciplines like mechanical and electrical engineering or newer fields like sustainable energy and biomaterials, there is something for everyone in Canada.</p>



<h2>Do You Want to Study in Canada as an Engineer?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>A New Program Allows Americans to Directly Sponsor Refugees for Resettlement in the US</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/a-new-program-allows-americans-to-directly-sponsor-refugees-for-resettlement-in-the-us/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Fri, 20 Jan 2023 18:45:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53836</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The United States State Department has unveiled a new initiative called the Welcome Corps, which allows groups of American citizens to sponsor refugees from Cuba, Haiti, Nicaragua, and Venezuela resettlement in the United States. This represents a substantial shift in policy and could lead to an increase in the number of migrants accepted while also [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The United States State Department has unveiled a new initiative called the Welcome Corps, which allows groups of American citizens to sponsor refugees from <strong>Cuba, Haiti, Nicaragua, and Venezuela </strong>resettlement in the United States. This represents a substantial shift in policy and could lead to an increase in the number of migrants accepted while also cutting costs for the government. In order to participate in the program, parties of five or more people must raise a minimum of $2,275 per sponsored refugee in order to pay for their accommodation and other essentials during their first three months in the nation.</p>



<p>According to <a href="https://welcomecorps.org/">an associated website</a>, sponsor groups made up of <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/usa-immigration/permanent-residence-green-card/citizenship/">US citizens</a> or <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/usa-immigration/permanent-residence-green-card/">permanent residents</a> will have to go through background checks and develop a support plan.</p>



<p>Secretary of State Antony Blinken stated that the sponsorship program is the most innovative development in refugee resettlement since the program&#8217;s inception in the United States in 1980. He also stated that the program is open to a variety of organizations, including religious groups, veterans, businesses, universities, and others.</p>



<h2 id="h-how-many-sponsors-and-refugees-will-be-chosen">How Many Sponsors and Refugees Will Be Chosen?</h2>



<p>The State Department announced that the program&#8217;s goal for the fiscal year 2023, which ends on September 30, is to recruit 10,000 American sponsors for 5,000 refugees. Each organization may sponsor multiple refugees. Reuters previously reported that the program would be launched. </p>



<h2>What is the Goal of this New Program?</h2>



<p>The program, which is modeled after Canada&#8217;s refugee sponsorship program, is part of President Joe Biden&#8217;s initiative to help foreign nationals seeking asylum.</p>



<p>The administration sees the new model as a way to increase support for refugees. Former President Donald Trump portrayed refugees as a security risk, and the number of admissions was drastically reduced and has yet to fully recover. Republicans have criticized President Biden&#8217;s approach to border security as a record number of migrants attempt to cross illegally from Mexico. </p>



<p>The Welcome Corps program is not expected to have an immediate impact on the border situation because refugees from abroad, primarily from conflict-affected areas, must go through a lengthy application process.</p>



<p>President Biden has implemented additional sponsorship programs in response to the growing number of arriving migrants. The administration recently launched a humanitarian entry program that allows up to 30,000 migrants per month from Cuba, Haiti, Nicaragua, and Venezuela to enter the country via &#8220;parole&#8221; if they are sponsored by the United States and travel by air.</p>



<p>The refugees will be admitted via the United States Refugee Resettlement Program, which accepts referrals from the United Nations and US embassies. However, there is concern that proper safeguards are required to ensure that sponsors are thoroughly vetted and have sufficient financial means to support the refugee.</p>



<h2>Do You Need Help Sponsoring or Being Sponsored in the US as a Refugee?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1 on 1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we can help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Canada will Become More Diverse by 2041</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/canada-will-become-more-diverse-by-2041/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Ella Niren]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 18 Jan 2023 16:37:49 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53314</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[It’s no surprise that Canada is a major target for immigration as seen by the increasing number of immigrants each year. If this trend continues in the upcoming decade, by 2041 the Canadian population will reach 47.7 million, half of which will consist of immigrants and their Canadian-born children. There are significant demographic changes in [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>It’s no surprise that Canada is a major target for immigration as seen by the increasing number of immigrants each year. If this trend continues in the upcoming decade, by 2041 the Canadian population will reach 47.7 million, half of which will consist of immigrants and their Canadian-born children.</p>



<p>There are significant demographic changes in Canada and its regions due to this continuous increase in newcomers. For example, in 2016 it was reported that 13.5% of the Canadian population was born in Asia or Africa, and in 2041 it’s predicted that this group will make up 23.1% to 26.9%. In fact, by this period 2 in 5 Canadians are projected to be part of a visible minority group. </p>



<h2 id="the-youth-have-a-higher-projected-percentage-of-the-population-belonging-to-a-racialized-community">The Youth Have a Higher Projected Percentage of the Population Belonging to a Racialized Community</h2>



<p>Interestingly, the predicted proportion of visible minorities is higher among youth, ranging between 44.0% and 49.7 of those aged 0 to 14. In addition to the increase in immigration, a reason for a significant increase in the racialized population is largely due to the rise in immigrant Canadian-born children. The second-generation racialized population was reported to be 2.2 million in 2016 and is predicted to increase between 4.8 million and 6.3 million in 2041. As more time passes by, Canada will continue to grow as a nation of diversity and multiculturalism due to it being such a desired destination for immigrants and a home to their children.</p>



<h2 id="what-ethnicities-will-be-most-common-to-see-immigrate-to-canada-by-2041">What Ethnicities Will Be Most Common to See Immigrate to Canada by 2041?</h2>



<p>The racialized population in Canada consists of many different groups which change and grow over time. In fact, it’s predicted that by 2041 the Black population will double from 1.2 million people in 2016 to over 3.0 million, surpassing the <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/country/china-to-canada/">Chinese</a> and Indigenous populations for the first time. On the other hand, while a smaller group, Western Asians and Arabs are the fastest-growing among the racialized population, with a growth rate between 3.8% and 5.2% in 2016 which is predicted to be between 3.7% and 5.1% in 2041. The annual growth rate of the entire racialized population, however, is projected to lie between 2.9% and 4.2%, a striking contrast to the 0.7% to 1.5% annual growth rate of the Canadian population as a whole. It’s evident that the nation is to become a more diverse place in the years to come as people from all over the world immigrate to Canada.</p>



<h2 id="the-envisioned-representation-of-diversity-differs-significantly-depending-on-the-location">The Envisioned Representation of Diversity Differs Significantly Depending on the Location</h2>



<p>In 2041, 80% of Toronto&#8217;s population will be composed of individuals who are foreign-born or have immigrant parents. <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/resources/settle/toronto/">The Greater Toronto Area</a> will remain the most heavily populated metropolitan area in the country and will continue to be home to the largest number of immigrants. The South Asian group will remain the largest racialized group. Depending on the projection scenario, this group could number between 2.3 million and 3.2 million, an increase from 1.0 million in 2016. According to the reference scenario, the South Asian group will make up 38.6% of Toronto&#8217;s total racialized population in 2041.</p>



<p>The most populous cities in Canada would still be Vancouver and Montréal, which are situated east and west of Toronto, respectively. The ethnic and cultural composition of these three cities would be very different by 2041, though.</p>



<h3 id="montreal">Montreal</h3>



<p>In <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/resources/settle/montreal/">Montréal</a>, the Black population will remain the largest racialized group and will increase from 276,000 in 2016 to 673,000 people by 2041, as per the reference scenario. The Arab population will continue to be the second-largest group, rising from 194,000 people in 2016 to 496,000 people by 2041 under the reference scenario. The reference scenario predicts that these two groups will make up 30.9% and 22.8% of the total racialized population in Montréal by 2041.</p>



<h3 id="vancouver">Vancouver</h3>



<p>The Chinese are the most numerous racialized group in <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/resources/settle/vancouver/">Vancouver</a>, accounting for 504,000 people in 2016. The Chinese population would increase to between 737,000 and 972,000 by 2041, depending on the projection scenario. South Asians would be the second largest group, with a population of between 638,000 and 859,000 in 2041, up from 308,000 in 2016. By 2041, these two groups will account for 31.7% and 27.9% of the total racialized population in Vancouver, respectively.</p>



<h2 id="h-are-you-interested-in-immigrating-to-canada">Are You Interested in Immigrating to Canada?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>CDC Announces Negative COVID Test Will Be Needed for Those Traveling to the US from China, Hong Kong and Macau</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/cdc-announces-negative-covid-test-will-be-needed-for-those-traveling-to-the-us-from-china-hong-kong-and-macau/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 05 Jan 2023 17:01:41 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53735</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The US CDC announced new COVID-19 testing requirements for air passengers arriving from China, Hong Kong, and Macau on Wednesday, December 28, 2022. All travelers aged 2 and older must be tested no more than two days before departure and show a negative test result to the operating airline, regardless of nationality or vaccination status, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The US CDC announced new COVID-19 testing requirements for air passengers arriving from China, Hong Kong, and Macau on Wednesday, December 28, 2022. All travelers aged 2 and older must be tested no more than two days before departure and show a negative test result to the operating airline, regardless of nationality or vaccination status, beginning at 12:01 a.m. (Eastern time) on Thursday, January 5, 2023.</p>



<p>CDC is announcing this step to slow the spread of COVID-19 in the United States during the surge in COVID-19 cases in the PRC. These data are critical for effectively monitoring the case surge and reducing the possibility of the entry of a novel variant of concern. The CDC will continue to monitor the situation and adjust our strategy as needed.</p>



<h2 id="h-what-are-the-new-requirements-and-who-will-they-apply-to">What Are the New Requirements and Who Will They Apply To?</h2>



<p>Beginning at 12:01 a.m. ET on January 5, all air passengers two years and older departing from the PRC will be required to get a test (such as a PCR test or an antigen self-test administered and monitored by a telehealth service or a licensed provider and approved by the Food and Drug Administration or the relevant national authority) no more than two days ahead of departure and display a negative test result to the airline upon departing.</p>



<ul><li>The requirement applies to all passengers on the plane, despite&nbsp;nationality or vaccination status.</li><li>This will also apply to people traveling from the PRC via third-country transit, as well as passengers connecting through the US to other destinations.</li><li>In addition to direct flights from the PRC, passengers transiting through Incheon International Airport, Toronto Pearson International Airport, and Vancouver International Airport on their way to the US will be required to present a negative COVID-19 test if they have been in the PRC in the last 10 days and no more than 2 days before their departure to the US. These three transit hubs serve the vast majority of passengers traveling from the PRC and Special Administrative Regions. The CDC states they will continue to monitor travel patterns, adjust their approach as needed, and keep Americans up to date as soon as possible.</li><li>Passengers who tested positive more than 10 days prior to the flight can provide documentation of COVID-19 recovery in lieu of a negative test result.</li><li>Airlines must confirm the negative COVID-19 test result or provide documentation of recovery for all passengers before boarding or denying boarding.</li></ul>



<h2>Do You Need Help Immigrating to the United States?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>International Experience Canada (IEC) is Now Accepting Applications for the Year 2023</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/international-experience-canada-iec-is-now-accepting-applications-for-the-year-2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 19:57:25 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53710</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The pools for the 2023 season of International Experience Canada (IEC) were opened for new candidates on December 19th. Candidates who are eligible to participate in IEC 2023 can now create their profile online. Immigration Minister Sean Fraser announced at a press conference in Banff that the International Experience Canada (IEC) program will begin on [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The pools for the 2023 season of <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/work-permits/iec/">International Experience Canada (IEC)</a> were opened for new candidates on December 19th. Candidates who are eligible to participate in IEC 2023 can now create their profile online.</p>



<p>Immigration Minister Sean Fraser announced at a press conference in Banff that the International Experience Canada (IEC) program will begin on January 9, 2023.</p>



<p>There will be 90,000 spots available, a 20% increase from the previous year, for foreigners between the ages of 18 and 35 from the 36 participating countries.</p>



<h2 id="h-what-is-the-iec-program">What is the IEC program?</h2>



<p>IEC is divided into three categories:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/working-holiday-visa/">Working Holiday Visa</a>: This visa is appropriate for those who wish to work for any employer in Canada. Candidates under this scheme are granted an open work permit. This means you can change jobs and locations while remaining in Canada.</li><li><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/iec-young-professionals-canadian-immigration/">Young Professional</a>: In this category, applicants can gain Canadian work experience by working with a Canadian company. Candidates must have a legitimate Canadian job offer in order to apply. Due to the fact that this program provides an employer-specific work visa, you must work for the same company in the same location.</li><li><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/iec-international-co-op-internship-canadian-immigration/">International Co-op</a>: International students can complete an internship or work placement in Canada through this program. However, this is only true when there is a requirement.</li></ul>



<h2>How Do I Apply for the IEC 2023 Program?</h2>



<p>When the 2023 IEC season begins on January 9, you will be able to complete the following tasks:</p>



<ol><li>Submit profile: To be considered for an invitation, you must first submit a profile through your IRCC account. If you previously submitted a profile, you can use the same account, but you must create a new profile.</li><li>Get an invitation: To apply for a work permit, you must first be invited. A randomized lottery system is used to distribute invitations each week. The sooner you enter the pool, the more invitation rounds you will be considered for.</li><li>Fill out a work permit application: If you are invited, you have 10 days to accept or decline the invitation. If you accept, you will have 20 days to prepare and submit your application.</li></ol>



<p>Once the season begins on January 9, candidates will be able to submit their profiles to the IEC pool. Invitation rounds usually begin in the weeks following the start of the season.</p>



<h2>How to Prepare for an IEC Invitation</h2>



<p>In the meantime, here are some things you can do to prepare for an invitation:</p>



<ul><li>Police certificates: For countries where you have lived for six or more consecutive months since the age of 18, police certificates &#8211; also known as police clearances or background checks &#8211; must be provided.</li><li>Biometrics: IEC now requires the submission of biometrics, including fingerprints.</li><li>Resume: Prepare a resume that will help you land a job in Canada.</li><li>Look for jobs in Canada: Begin your job search before you even arrive.</li></ul>



<h2>Do You Need Help Preparing for the 2023 IEC Program?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Canada Extends Work Permits for Family Members of Temporary Foreign Workers</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/canada-extends-work-permits-for-family-members-of-temporary-foreign-workers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Thu, 29 Dec 2022 19:02:58 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53705</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The slow pace of Canada&#8217;s economic growth has made it difficult for business owners, particularly those in the tourism industry, to find the workers they require. Sean Fraser, Minister of Immigration, Refugees, and Citizenship, and Randy Boissonnault, Minister of Tourism and Associate Minister of Finance, announced that Canada is extending work permits to family members [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The slow pace of Canada&#8217;s economic growth has made it difficult for business owners, particularly those in the tourism industry, to find the workers they require.</p>



<p>Sean Fraser, Minister of Immigration, Refugees, and Citizenship, and Randy Boissonnault, Minister of Tourism and Associate Minister of Finance, announced that Canada is extending <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/work-permits/">work permits</a> to family members of temporary foreign workers. Extending work permit eligibility to family members supporting the principal applicant to Canada will help address labor shortages by aiding employers in finding the workers they require.</p>



<h2 id="h-what-are-the-changes-to-work-permit-eligibility">What Are the Changes to Work Permit Eligibility?</h2>



<p>Prior to this announcement, spouses could only obtain a work permit if the primary applicant worked in a <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/temporary-foreign-worker-program-for-high-wage-earners/">high-skilled occupation</a>. By keeping families together, this temporary measure aims to improve workers&#8217; emotional well-being, overall health, and economic stability. As a result, the worker is expected to integrate better into their overall work community and environment.</p>



<p>Starting in January 2023, Canada will broaden eligibility to work in Canada to spouses and working-age children through a phased approach for workers of all skill levels through a temporary 2-year measure. Families of workers in health care, trades, and hospitality, for example, would be included. It is estimated that as a result of this new approach, family members of more than 200,000 foreign workers could start work in Canada, providing more opportunities for both foreign workers looking to work in Canada and employers addressing their labor needs.</p>



<h3>3 Phases to Ensure Success</h3>



<p>To ensure its success, the temporary measure will be implemented in three stages, according to the official website of Immigration, Refugees, and Citizenship Canada (IRCC):</p>



<ul><li>Phase 1: Family members of workers coming to Canada through the high-wage stream of the Temporary Foreign Worker Program or the International Mobility Program will be able to apply for an open work permit.</li><li>Phase 2: Following consultations, phase 2 intends to extend the measure to family members of workers from the Temporary Foreign Worker Program&#8217;s low-wage stream.</li><li>Phase 3: This will involve consultation with agricultural partners and stakeholders to determine the operational feasibility of extending the measure to agricultural workers&#8217; families.</li></ul>



<p>Immigration will continue to play an important role in addressing Canada&#8217;s labor shortages, and the government will continue to implement policies to assist employers with their hiring needs at all skill levels.</p>



<h2>Do You Have Questions About the Changes to Work Permits for Family Members of Temporary Foreign Workers?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Canadian Graduates: Study to Canada PR Steps</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/study-to-canada-pr/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sierra]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Tue, 27 Dec 2022 03:41:03 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53686</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Thousands of young adults are coming to Canada each year for higher education. A huge benefit to this and a reason many immigrants choose this route is the opportunity to gain permanent residency after their studies. What&#8217;s better than knowing you could come to Canada for education and then have a good chance of making [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Thousands of young adults are coming to Canada each year for higher education. A huge benefit to this and a reason many immigrants choose this route is the opportunity to gain permanent residency after their studies. What&#8217;s better than knowing you could come to Canada for education and then have a good chance of making Canada your home? Canadian officials have created a straightforward pathway for those looking to achieve this goal by utilizing a Post Graduate Work Permit (PGWP) and the Canadian Experience Class through Express Entry. We want to help you better understand this process so below we have broken down the 5 steps from Study to Canada PR!</p>



<h2 id="h-study-to-canada-pr-process">Study to Canada PR Process</h2>



<h4 id="h-step-1-apply-for-study-permit">Step 1: Apply for study permit</h4>



<p>First, you must apply for your Canadian study permit and finish your studies! To apply for a study permit in Canada, you must get accepted to a qualified designated learning institution (DLI). Learn more about&nbsp;<a href="/canadian-immigration/study-permit-for-students/">Canada study permits</a>.</p>



<h4 id="h-step-2-work-while-studying-optional">Step 2: Work while studying (optional)</h4>



<p>Most international students studying in Canada like to take the opportunity to work while studying so they can not only gain work experience but cover their day-to-day expenses as a student. When studying in Canada you can work on-campus, off-campus, and apply to internships. Then you are ready for a Post-Graduate Work Permit!</p>



<h4 id="h-step-3-apply-for-post-graduate-work-permit">Step 3: Apply for Post-Graduate Work Permit</h4>



<p>Once you have graduated, you can apply for a <a href="/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/post-graduate-work-permit-pgwp/">Post-Graduate Work Program</a> to start gaining valuable Canadian work experience. Your PGWP validity is based on how long your studies were!</p>



<h4 id="h-step-4-apply-for-express-entry-canadian-experience-class">Step 4: Apply for Express Entry (Canadian Experience Class)</h4>



<p>Once you’ve received your degree and at least one year of Canadian work experience, you may be ready for permanent residency! The best option for graduates in this scenario is to apply through the&nbsp;<a href="/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/canadian-experience-class/">Canadian Experience Class (CEC)</a>&nbsp;which is managed under&nbsp;<a href="/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/express-entry/">Express Entry</a>. You will then be entered into an online lottery that will invite candidates to apply for Canada PR based on their CRS score.&nbsp;Usually, by this time, the candidate with have a Canadian job offer and a good amount of Canadian work experience which are huge boosters for your CRS score.</p>



<p>Related Article:&nbsp;<a href="/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/express-entry/crs-calculator/">CRS Score Calculator</a></p>



<h4 id="h-step-5-recieve-an-ita-and-apply-for-canada-pr">Step 5: Recieve an ITA and Apply for Canada PR</h4>



<p>Once your score is the cut-off score or higher within an&nbsp;<a href="/blog-immigration-law/c/canada/permanent-residence/express-entry/">Express Entry draw</a>, you will recieve an&nbsp;<a href="/ita-service/">ITA (invitation to apply)</a> allowing you to apply for&nbsp;<a href="/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/">Canada PR</a>.</p>



<h2>Do You Need Legal Immigration Help?</h2>



<p>Just because the study to Canada PR pathway seems straightforward, there is always room for complications so it&#8217;s important to have immigration help on speed dial! If you need immigration assistance in Canada, we can help! </p>



<p><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>US Immigration Changes in 2022: Year in Review</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/us-immigration-changes-in-2022-year-in-review/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 21 Dec 2022 21:19:15 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53650</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[According to US Citizenship and Immigration Services (USCIS), nearly a million immigrant adults were naturalized as American citizens in the fiscal year 2022, the third-highest annual tally in US history. Naturalizations have reached a 14-year high, a year after President Biden directed federal agencies to promote naturalizations by removing bureaucratic barriers in the citizenship process, [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>According to US Citizenship and Immigration Services (USCIS), nearly a million immigrant adults were naturalized as American citizens in the fiscal year 2022, the third-highest annual tally in US history.</p>



<p>Naturalizations have reached a 14-year high, a year after President Biden directed federal agencies to promote naturalizations by removing bureaucratic barriers in the citizenship process, expediting case adjudications, and developing a government-wide strategy to boost eligible immigrants to become citizens.</p>



<h2 id="united-states-visa-changes-and-new-visa-programs-in-2022">United States Visa Changes and New Visa Programs in 2022</h2>



<h3 id="h-ukraine-relief-in-the-united-states">Ukraine Relief in the United States</h3>



<p>Ukrainians who would face extreme hardship if forced to return to homelands devastated by armed conflict or natural disasters are eligible for the relief, which is known as Temporary Protected Status.</p>



<p>Learn more about <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/ukraine-us-relief/">TPS for Ukrainians</a>. </p>



<h3 id="eb-5-investor-visa-regional-center-program-is-back">EB-5 Investor Visa Regional Center Program is Back</h3>



<p>In March 2022, the Senate approved a reauthorization of the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/usa-immigration/permanent-residence-green-card/employment-based-petitions/eb-5-visa/">EB-5</a>&nbsp;Regional Center Program – the EB-5 Reform and Integrity Act of 2022 (“Integrity Act”) as part of the FY 2022 Consolidated Appropriations Bill. The same bill had been passed by the House the night before.</p>



<p>Learn more about the <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/eb-5-visa-update/">EB-5 Investor Visa program returning</a>.</p>



<h3 id="us-immigration-reaches-h-1b-immigration-visa-cap">US Immigration Reaches H-1B Immigration Visa Cap</h3>



<p>In March of 2022, the US received enough applications to meet the federally mandated 65,000 H-1B visa ceiling for the fiscal year 2022.</p>



<p>This year, the USCIS was required to hold three visa lotteries in order to reach the mandated quota of 65,000 normal visas and 20,000 master’s visas. The agency had also performed two lotteries the previous year, which was uncommon. After the first round of choices, the USCIS usually gets a sufficient number of applications. Because there were insufficient applicants after the first lottery, the US immigration office held a second random selection in July 2021.</p>



<p>Learn more about the <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/us-immigration-reaches-h-1b-visa-cap-for-2022/">H-1B Visa Cap</a>.</p>



<h3 id="biden-administration-proposes-new-id-card-for-migrants">Biden Administration Proposes New ID Card for Migrants</h3>



<p>A new national identification card program for unauthorized immigrants has been suggested by the Biden administration. The “ICE Secure Docket Card program” would provide temporary ID cards to border crossers and other undocumented immigrants so they could legally identify themselves while navigating their immigration cases or removal court processes.</p>



<p>Learn more about <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/undocumented-immigrants/">New ID cards for migrants</a>.</p>



<h3 id="h-h-2b-visa-cap-update">H-2B Visa Cap Update</h3>



<p>Congress has set the H-2B cap at 66,000 per fiscal year, with 33,000 workers being invited each half of the year. On September 14th, 2022, the&nbsp;<a href="https://www.uscis.gov/" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">USCIS</a>&nbsp;announced that the as of September 12th, 33,000 H-2B visas had already been issued to qualified candidates. Cap-subject H-2B petitions requesting employment start dates prior to April 1, 2023, will now be rejected by USCIS.</p>



<p>Learn more about the <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/h-2b-visa-mid-year-cap-update-fy2023/">H-2B cap update</a>.</p>



<h2 id="do-you-need-help-immigrating-to-the-united-states">Do You Need Help Immigrating to the United States?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>9 Canadian Immigration Changes in 2022: Year in Review</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/9-canadian-immigration-changes-in-2022-year-in-review/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 19 Dec 2022 18:39:18 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53509</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[In the year 2022, many significant immigration changes occurred in Canada. We have seen a growth of visas being applied&#160;for following the pandemic, and Canadian immigration is vastly&#160;increasing. Canada has&#160;welcomed&#160;a record number of immigrants in 2022! The most significant events in Canadian immigration in the last year are discussed below. Canadian Visa Changes and New [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>In the year 2022, many significant immigration changes occurred in Canada. We have seen a growth of visas being applied&nbsp;for following the pandemic, and Canadian immigration is vastly&nbsp;increasing. Canada has&nbsp;welcomed&nbsp;a record number of immigrants in 2022!</p>



<p>The most significant events in Canadian immigration in the last year are discussed below.</p>



<h2 id="h-canadian-visa-changes-and-new-programs-2022">Canadian Visa Changes and New Programs 2022</h2>



<h3>Express Entry Draws</h3>



<p>Up until July 6, 2022, all of the Express Entry draws in 2022 had been&nbsp;Provincial Nominee Program (PNP)&nbsp;draws. After July 6, all draws have been all program draws, meaning they include CEC, FSW, and PNP draws. </p>



<p>There have been a total of 24 Express Entry draws in 2022, the last draw taking place on November 23rd. The CRS cut-off score started high in the beginning of the year at 808 but steadily declined each draw with the latest score being 491. As the CRS score declined, the number of invitations issued grew. </p>



<p>Learn more about <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/express-entry/">Canada&#8217;s 2022 Express Entry draws</a>.</p>



<h3>Alberta Launches New Foreign Tech Worker Stream</h3>



<p>In January 2022, Alberta saw a significant tech worker shortage. In response, The province announced the development of the Accelerated Tech Pathway, which gives highly talented tech workers who wish to live and work in Alberta a fast road to permanent residency.</p>



<p>Learn more about <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/accelerated-tech-pathway/">Alberta&#8217;s foreign tech worker stream</a>.</p>



<h3>New Atlantic Immigration Program Launch</h3>



<p>On March 4th, the Government of Canada released details about the newest&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/atlantic-immigration-pilot-program/">Atlantic Immigration Program (AIP)</a>&nbsp;launch. Formally known as the Atlantic Immigration Pilot Program (AIPP), this pathway gives skilled foreign workers and international graduates the opportunity to gain Canada PR.</p>



<p>Canada announced the new permanent Atlantic Immigration Program, recognizing the need to build on this success as the country continues to recover from the pandemic and address labor shortages across Atlantic Canada.</p>



<p>Learn more about the new <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/new-launch-atlantic-immigration-program-aip-2022/">Atlantic Immigration Program launch</a>.</p>



<h3>Saskatchewan Launches New Immigration Pathway for Tech Workers</h3>



<p>On March 7, 2022, Saskatchewan launched a new tech-immigration program. This program joined the other streams created for skilled workers, experienced professionals, and entrepreneurs but specifically targets foreign tech workers.</p>



<p>The Tech Talent Pathway was created to fill the labor shortages within particular occupations within Canada’s rapidly growing tech sector.</p>



<p>Learn more about <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/saskatchewan-launches-new-immigration-pathway-for-tech-workers/">Saskatchewan&#8217;s new Immigration Pathway for tech workers</a>.</p>



<h3>New Occupation Categories through Express Entry</h3>



<p>With a lot of industries experiencing labor shortages country-wide, the IRCC has added 16 occupations that are now eligible through Express Entry through the NOC code update. This will open doors for many foreign workers interested in immigrating to Canada and some of those who are working entry-level jobs.</p>



<p>Learn more about the <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/16-new-eligible-occupations-through-express-entry/">new occupation categories through Express Entry</a>.</p>



<h3>Canada Increases Immigration Fees</h3>



<p>On April 30, 2022, Canada increased immigration fees for all permanent residency applications. These fee hikes were implemented for the economic, permit holder, family, and humanitarian categories. This is mainly due to costs to account for inflation in 2020.</p>



<p>Learn more about <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/canada-to-increase-immigration-fees-in-2022/">changes to Canada&#8217;s immigration fees</a>.</p>



<h3>Canada Increases Length of Stay for Parents and Grandparents Super Visa Holders</h3>



<p>As of July 4, 2022, the length of stay for&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/family-immigration/super-visas/">Super Visa</a>&nbsp;holders in Canada will be expanded to five years per entrance.</p>



<p>People who presently hold a Super Visa can also obtain an extension of up to two years while in Canada. This implies that existing Super Visa holders can now stay in Canada for up to seven years in a row.</p>



<p>Learn more about the <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/canada-increases-length-of-stay-for-parents-and-grandparents-super-visa-holders/">changes to Canada&#8217;s parents and grandparents super visa</a>.</p>



<h3>Canada Looks to Fix Immigration Backlog</h3>



<p>On August 24, Canada’s Minister of Immigration spoke in Vancouver on IRCC’s ongoing efforts to minimize application backlogs, enhance client satisfaction, and solve labor shortages.</p>



<p>Learn more on updates about <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/new-updates-on-canadas-immigration-system/">Canada&#8217;s immigration backlog</a>.</p>



<h3>Permanent Residency Program for Relatives of Victims of Air Disasters</h3>



<p>Families of the Canadian victims of Ethiopian Airlines Flight 302 and Ukraine International Airlines Flight 752 can now apply for permanent residency through a new program established by Immigration, Refugees and Citizenship Canada (IRCC).</p>



<p>Learn more about the new <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/canada-offers-new-avenues-for-foreign-relatives-of-victims-of-air-disasters-to-obtain-pr/">PR pathway for victims of air disasters</a>.</p>



<h2>What to Expect for Canadian Immigration 2023</h2>



<h3><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/canada-plans-to-welcome-500000-immigrants-by-2025/">Canada&#8217;s New Immigration Levels Plan</a></h3>



<p>Canada has announced plans to significantly increase the number of immigrants entering the country, with a goal of 500,000 arriving each year by 2025 in order to address a critical labor shortage. According to the new plan, 465,000 people will enter the country from outside the country in 2023, rising to 500,000 in 2025.</p>



<p>Express Entry and PNP targets are also expected to increase in 2023.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Work Opportunities for Canadian and Italian Youth</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/new-work-opportunities-for-canadian-and-italian-youth/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 07 Dec 2022 04:14:47 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53419</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On November 14, 2022, the Canadian government announced a new Youth Mobility Agreement with Italy to expand employment opportunities for Canadian and Italian youth. This agreement allows Canadian and Italian youth to apply for international work and travel opportunities through the International Experience Canada Program. Participants must be between the ages of 18 and 35 [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>On November 14, 2022, the Canadian government announced a new Youth Mobility Agreement with Italy to expand employment opportunities for Canadian and Italian youth.</p>



<p>This agreement allows Canadian and Italian youth to apply for international work and travel opportunities through the <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/work-permits/iec/">International Experience Canada Program</a>. Participants must be between the ages of 18 and 35 to participate. Eligible applicants will be allowed to work and travel for a total of 24 months. The program is divided into three sections:</p>



<ul><li><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/working-holiday-visa/">The Working Holiday program</a>: this program&nbsp;provides participants with an open work permit, allowing them to work anywhere in the host country to fund their travel.</li><li><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/iec-international-co-op-internship-canadian-immigration/">The International Co-op (Internship) program</a>: this program provides participants with an employer-specific work permit that allows students to obtain targeted experience in a field of study of their choice.</li><li><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/iec-young-professionals-canadian-immigration/">The Young Professional program</a>: this program provides participants with an employer-specific work permit in order to gain directed, professional work experience in a particular field of study or career path.</li></ul>



<p>Canada and Italy have long been youth mobility partners, supporting international work and travel opportunities. The program also assists youth in exploring new cultures, languages, and societies, all while developing life skills and improving their future job prospects.</p>



<p>This agreement with Italy creates new opportunities for future work and travel, strengthens our people-to-people ties, and improves labor market access for Canadian and Italian youth.</p>



<h2 id="h-do-you-need-help-applying-for-one-of-the-programs-above">Do You Need Help Applying for One of the Programs Above?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>New Brunswick Launches Immigration Pilot for Critical Workers</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/new-brunswick-launches-immigration-pilot-for-critical-workers/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 28 Nov 2022 18:04:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53376</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On November 7, 2022, the New Brunswick Provincial Government announced a brand new immigration pilot project: the New Brunswick Critical Worker Pilot (NBCWP). The pilot (a joint federal-provincial project) aims to alleviate critical worker shortages in New Brunswick. The pilot is unique in that it will not only offer economic immigration to the province, but [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>On November 7, 2022, the New Brunswick Provincial Government announced a brand new immigration pilot project: the New Brunswick Critical Worker Pilot (NBCWP).</p>



<p>The pilot (a joint federal-provincial project) aims to alleviate critical worker shortages in New Brunswick. The pilot is unique in that it will not only offer economic immigration to the province, but it will also provide settlement services (including skills and language training) to newcomers who arrive as a result of the project.</p>



<p>Learn more about other <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/provincial-nominee-program-pnp/brunswick-provincial-nominee-program/">New Brunswick programs.</a></p>



<h2 id="h-what-are-employers-required-to-do">What Are Employers Required to Do?</h2>



<p>Cooke Aquaculture, Groupe Savoie Inc., Groupe Westco, Imperial Manufacturing, J.D. Irving Ltd., and McCain Foods have all agreed to participate in the pilot. These employers have a strong reputation with the New Brunswick Provincial Nominee Program; have steady immigrant recruitment practices; have newcomer settlement programs in place; and are willing to provide onsite training as well as language support.</p>



<p>Participating employers must meet a number of requirements. They are required to:</p>



<ul><li>have robust settlement plans for housing and transportation to best support candidates&#8217; successful integration into their new jobs and communities, with strong commitments to long-term retention</li><li>have comprehensive human resource planning in place for recruiting and hiring skilled international talent, as well as enhancing on-the-job skills;</li><li>Recruited candidates will receive up to 200 hours of language training as needed; and</li><li>provide guidance and support to candidates interested in pursuing their Canadian secondary education equivalency</li></ul>



<p>The five-year pilot program will be monitored and evaluated on a regular basis to ensure that it remains responsive to immigration needs while also achieving the desired results for the province.</p>



<h2>Do You Need Help Applying for the New Brunswick Immigration Pilot?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Options for H1-B Workers Affected by a Layoff</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/options-for-h1-b-workers-affected-by-a-layoff/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Wed, 23 Nov 2022 21:00:33 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=53335</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[An unexpected layoff can cause&#160;panic in anyone&#8217;s life, but when an H-1B worker loses their job, it can be especially daunting. This is because they must leave the country unless they find a new job or change their immigration status within 60 days. H-1B visa holders may stay in the United States for up to [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>An unexpected layoff can cause&nbsp;panic in anyone&#8217;s life, but when an <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/usa-immigration/us-work-visas/h-1b-visa-work-permit/">H-1B worker</a> loses their job, it can be especially daunting. This is because they must leave the country unless they find a new job or change their immigration status within 60 days.</p>



<p>H-1B visa holders may stay in the United States for up to 60 days after their last day of employment in H-1B status. During the 60-day grace period, the H-1B employee may look for a new job and find a new employer sponsor. Within the 60-day grace period, the new employer must file an H-1B change of employer petition. After receiving the H-1B transfer petition from US Citizenship and Immigration Services, the H-1B employee is eligible to begin working for the new employer (USCIS).</p>



<h2 id="h-what-happens-if-i-can-t-find-a-new-job-in-60-days">What Happens If I Can&#8217;t Find a New Job in 60 Days?</h2>



<p>Individuals in H-1B status who are unable to find a new job and an employer sponsor within the 60-day grace period must leave the United States before the grace period expires. If this is not possible and the H-1B worker requires additional time to settle in the United States, they may change their status.</p>



<h2>How Do I Change My H1-B Status?</h2>



<p>If finding a job in the 60 days is not possible and the H-1B worker requires additional time to settle in the United States, they may file a Form I-539 application to change status from H-1B to <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/usa-immigration/visitor-visas/b2-tourist-visa/">B-2 visitor status</a> for up to 6 months. </p>



<p>There are also other nonimmigrant statuses that an H1-B visa holder may qualify to apply for. These include an <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/h4-ead/">H-4 status</a> as the spouse of an H-1B visa holder or an <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/usa-immigration/us-work-visas/o-visas/">O-1 status</a> as an individual with extraordinary ability.</p>



<h2>When Should I File to Change My Status?</h2>



<p>Any application for a change of status must be submitted before the end of the 60-day grace period. We advise against international travel following a layoff and during the grace period because it may jeopardize eligibility to transfer H-1B status to another employer. We also advise keeping pay stubs and requesting an employment verification letter as proof of the last day of H-1B employment.</p>



<h2>Is It Possible to Immigrate to Canada as an H-1b Holder?</h2>



<p>Yes! H1-B workers in the United States have a fantastic opportunity to immigrate to Canada via <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/express-entry/">Express Entry</a>, which is heavily weighted toward favoring young, educated, and ambitious workers with proven potential to succeed in their field.</p>



<h2 id="h-do-you-need-help-changing-your-h1-b-status">Do You Need Help Changing Your H1-B Status?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Canada Plans to Welcome 500,000 Immigrants by 2025</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/canada-plans-to-welcome-500000-immigrants-by-2025/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 07 Nov 2022 14:27:37 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=52971</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[Canada has announced plans to significantly increase the number of immigrants entering the country, with a goal of 500,000 arriving each year by 2025 in order to address a critical labor shortage. On Tuesday, Immigration Minister Sean Fraser unveiled the new plan. It prioritizes admitting more permanent residents with needed work skills and experience while [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>Canada has announced plans to significantly increase the number of immigrants entering the country, with a goal of 500,000 arriving each year by 2025 in order to address a critical labor shortage.</p>



<p>On Tuesday, Immigration Minister Sean Fraser unveiled the new plan. It prioritizes admitting more permanent residents with needed work skills and experience while setting more modest goals for family members and refugees. The plan was welcomed by the opposition Conservative Party.</p>



<p>“Make no mistake. This is a massive increase in economic migration to Canada,” Fraser said. “We have not seen such a focus on economic migration as we’ve seen in this immigration levels plan.”</p>



<p>According to the new plan, 465,000 people will enter the country from outside the country in 2023, rising to 500,000 in 2025. In comparison, the Department of Immigration reports that 405,000 <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/">permanent residents</a> were admitted last year.</p>



<p>The majority of those new arrivals will be economic immigrants, who will be expected to fill some of the roughly 1 million vacant jobs in various sectors of the economy.</p>



<h2 id="h-express-entry-and-pnp-targets-expected-to-increase">Express Entry and PNP Targets Expected to Increase</h2>



<p>The majority of new permanent residents enter the country through economic class programs such as Express Entry or <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/latest-pnp-canada-updates-and-draws/">Provincial Nomination Programs</a> (PNPs).</p>



<p>The <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/express-entry/">Express Entry</a> landing targets (principal applicants, spouses, and dependents) are expected to increase as follows:</p>



<ul><li>82,880 in 2023</li><li>109,020 in 2024</li><li>114,000 in 2025</li></ul>



<p>The PNP will continue to be Canada&#8217;s leading admissions program for low-income immigrants, and targets will be increased to:</p>



<ul><li>105,500  in 2023</li><li>110,000 in 2024</li><li>117,500 in 2025</li></ul>



<h2>More PGP Admissions</h2>



<p>IRCC is also tasked with reuniting families. Following economic class programs, family class sponsorship is the Immigration Levels Plan&#8217;s second-largest permanent residence class. Applicants for permanent residence are sponsored for permanent residence by a spouse, partner, children, or other family members under family class immigration programs.</p>



<p>Under the Spouses, Partners, and Children program, Canada will continue to welcome approximately 80,000 new immigrants annually.</p>



<p>The Parents and Grandparents Program&#8217;s goals will rise to 28,500 in 2023, 34,000 in 2024, and 36,000 in 2025.</p>



<h2>Refugee and Humanitarian Targets Will Be Reduced</h2>



<p>Refugees and humanitarian immigrants are also given priority under the Immigration Levels Plan. Canada has a long history of granting asylum to people fleeing dangerous situations in their home countries.</p>



<p>Canada currently has high humanitarian class targets due to ongoing efforts to complete several campaigns, such as welcoming approximately 40,000 Afghan refugees.</p>



<p>The overall refugee class target will be slightly more than 76,000 new arrivals in 2023 and 2024, before falling to 72,750 in 2025.</p>



<p>The humanitarian class target is also decreasing, from nearly 16,000 in 2023 to 8,000 in 2025.</p>



<h2>Are You Interested in Immigrating to Canada?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>H-2B Visa Mid-Year Cap Update: FY2023</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/h-2b-visa-mid-year-cap-update-fy2023/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Sierra]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 18:51:31 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=52665</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[The H-2B visa program for seasonal workers has invited thousands of temporary workers to the United States each year since 1952 and continues to this day! The H-2B visa was created to help fill short-term labor shortages in the US within specific non-agricultural occupations during busy seasons. A few occupations you could see being qualified [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>The H-2B visa program for seasonal workers has invited thousands of temporary workers to the United States each year since 1952 and continues to this day! The <a href="/usa-immigration/us-work-visas/h-2b-visa-work-permit/">H-2B visa</a> was created to help fill short-term labor shortages in the US within specific non-agricultural occupations during busy seasons. A few occupations you could see being qualified for the H-2B visa include ski resort workers, construction laborers, business trainers, athletes, entertainers, plus more.</p>



<h2 id="h-h-2b-visa-cap-count">H-2B Visa Cap Count</h2>



<p>Currently, Congress has set the H-2B cap at 66,000 per fiscal year, with 33,000 workers being invited each half of the year. On September 14th, 2022, the <a href="https://www.uscis.gov" target="_blank" rel="noreferrer noopener">USCIS</a> announced that the as of September 12th, 33,000 H-2B visas had already been issued to qualified candidates. Cap-subject H-2B petitions requesting employment start dates prior to April 1, 2023, will now be rejected by USCIS.</p>



<p>This first half of the year H-2B visa cap was reached two weeks earlier than last year which seems to decrease the chances of workers starting later in the year being approved. For those who were not accepted under the first H-2B cap, we advise applicants to continue their application processing so that certifications are ready if and when visas become available for start dates prior to April 1, 2023, or in case you fall under the visa cap-exempt category.</p>



<p>Related Article: <a href="/blog-immigration-law/h-2b-visa-cap-for-2022/">US Hits Mid-Year H-2B Visa</a> </p>



<h2 id="h-h-2b-visa-cap-exempts">H-2B Visa Cap-Exempts</h2>



<p>Those H-2B petitions exempt from the H-2B visa cap include:</p>



<ul><li>Change of employer petitions with a request to extend stay in H-2B status</li><li>Out-of-country petitions for beneficiaries who have already been counted against the first 33,000 limits for FY2023, and</li><li>Petitions for workers in the fish roe processing industry and labor services in the Commonwealth of the Northern Mariana Islands or Guam</li></ul>



<h2 id="h-do-you-need-help-with-your-h-2b-visa-application">Do You Need Help With Your H-2B Visa Application?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
		<item>
		<title>Canada Parent and Grandparents Program Update</title>
		<link>https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/canada-parent-and-grandparents-program-update/</link>
		
		<dc:creator><![CDATA[Casey]]></dc:creator>
		<pubDate>Mon, 17 Oct 2022 16:42:35 +0000</pubDate>
				<guid isPermaLink="false">https://www.visaplace.com/?p=52668</guid>

					<description><![CDATA[On October 11, 2022, The IRCC announced the Parent and Grandparents Program (PGP) &#8211; 2022 application process. The IRCC said they will send Invitations to Apply (ITAs) to 23,100 potential sponsors this year. Family reunification is essential in attracting, sustaining, and integrating immigrants who make a contribution to our country&#8217;s success. Canada has a very [&#8230;]]]></description>
										<content:encoded><![CDATA[
<p>On October 11, 2022, The IRCC announced the <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/blog-immigration-law/parent-and-grandparent-program-turns-into-a-lottery/">Parent and Grandparents Program</a> (PGP) &#8211; 2022 application process. The IRCC said they will send Invitations to Apply (ITAs) to 23,100 potential sponsors this year.</p>



<p>Family reunification is essential in attracting, sustaining, and integrating immigrants who make a contribution to our country&#8217;s success. Canada has a very expansive family sponsorship program that allows Canadian citizens and <a href="https://www.visaplace.com/canadian-immigration/canada-permanent-residence/">permanent residents</a> to bring their parents and grandparents to the country as permanent residents.</p>



<h2 id="h-what-does-the-pgp-do">What Does the PGP Do?</h2>



<p>The PGP essentially allows Canadian permanent residents and citizens to sponsor their parents and grandparents for a PR (Permanent Residence) visa to come to Canada. Each year, the Canadian government invites a set number of individuals to complete an interest to sponsor form in order to sponsor their parents/grandparents.</p>



<p>Because there are still a number of interest to sponsor forms in the pool of submissions from 2020, IRCC will send invitations to apply to randomly selected potential sponsors from that pool rather than opening a new interest to sponsor form. This is the same strategy used for the 2021 intake. Anyone who submitted an interest to sponsor form in 2020 but did not receive an invitation to apply in January 2021 or September 2021 should check the email address they provided when they submitted their interest.</p>



<h2>How to Apply for Canada Parents and Grandparents Program 2022</h2>



<ul><li><strong>Get Your ITA</strong>: Through a lottery system, the IRCC will select and invite 23,100 prospective sponsors to apply to sponsor their parents/grandparents. Following that, it will meet its goal of accepting up to 15,000 complete applications.</li><li><strong>Apply Online</strong>: Make sure you do not submit an application unless you have received an ITA for the 2022 process. If you apply but do not receive an ITA for the 2022 process, the IRCC will reject your application and will not refund your application fee.</li></ul>



<p>You need to submit both applications (i.e. sponsorship and the permanent residence application) together online at the same time. You must submit your application by December 24, 2022.</p>



<h2>Do You Need Help with Your PGP Application?</h2>



<p>If so,&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/">Contact VisaPlace today</a>. All our cases are handled by competent and experienced immigration professionals who are affiliated with VisaPlace. These professionals consist of&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/about-us/team/">lawyers</a>, licensed paralegals, and consultants who work for VisaPlace Legal, an award-winning immigration firm that adheres to the highest standards of client service.</p>



<p>Ready for the next step?&nbsp;<a href="https://www.visaplace.com/bookonline/">Book your 1-on-1 consultation now</a>&nbsp;or call us at&nbsp;<a href="tel:1-888-317-5770">1-888-317-5770</a>.</p>



<p><strong>Have a Question related to your Immigration Needs?</strong></p>



<p>Fill out the&nbsp;<strong><a href="https://www.visaplace.com/immigration-assessment/">FREE Immigration Assessment</a></strong>&nbsp;form and get a response within 24 hours to see if you’re eligible.</p>



<p>The assessment form should take approximately 5-7 minutes to complete. We will get back to you within one business day to let you know if we are able to help.</p>
]]></content:encoded>
					
		
		
			</item>
	</channel>
</rss>
